just want to pass on my best regards to
your
brother and
condemn outright what happened yesterday
in Dublin.
I am very sorry for him, for yourself and
for your family.
I wish him a speedy recovery.
He is a tough guy
I
get through
This should not happen.
should never have happened.
I just wanted to say
and
the demands being placed on the grid.
We introduced a Bill yesterday about the
prioritisation network.
Can the infrastructure that we have
withstand the increased demand coming from
data centres?
Will the Minister accept that public
infrastructure should be given priority
for housing, water connections and
electricity to deal with the scarce
grid capacity ahead of the new data centre
developments?
Ireland's industrial
This is our core energy-intensive
industry.
Data centres are fundamental to Ireland's
position as a leading
global hub for digital and
technology-driven enterprise.
They form a critical part of the State's
digital infrastructure, supporting
activities including cloud computing,
artificial intelligence, financial
services and public sector digital
services.
Their economic footprint is substantial
with €104 billion in gross value
added - that is about 20% of Ireland's
economy - enabled by data centre-dependent
sectors.
Approximately 183,000 people are working
in Ireland's technology sector with around
19,000 jobs directly in the data
While Ireland has attracted some of the
best data centre and tech companies in the
world, the integration of large-scale
demand on our grid must be facilitated in
a sustainable way.
Government's large energy user action
plan, LEAP, will progress a plan-led
approach for future energy-intensive
industry which will unlock investment and
innovation in Ireland's renewable energy
sector, maximise wider benefits in jobs
and skills across Ireland's regions and
ensure
the cost of developing additional
infrastructure is borne in a manner that
is fair.
This is being reinforced by unprecedented
grid investment of up to €18.9 billion,
and that is beneficial to our whole
economy and to our society.
Alongside LEAP, the CRU large energy user
connection policy establishes a
sustainable connection pathway for new
data centres that manages demand by
requiring generation and system support,
addressing security of electricity supply
and network constraint considerations, and
promoting Ireland's renewable energy
ambitions by bringing 80% of new energy
demand for any new data
connection through renewable sources.
I thank the Minister for the reply.
about the economic footprint and the
necessity for a plan-led approach.
I will come back to that in some of my
later questions.
However, we have had and continue to have
a first-come, first-served, laissez-faire
attitude, and
some larger energy users have been
facilitated in hoarding
connections that they have.
Some housing developments, like the one
the midlands, that have tried to get
connections have been put behind data
centres.
A significant proportion of the connection
queue consists of speculative
applications, and communities
other connections have been left behind.
The European Commission last December said
we need strategic prioritisation of scarce
grid capacity.
Will the Minister move away from the
first-come, first-served attitude?
the demand that is there.
Ireland's demand will grow and will double
between now and 2050.
That is why the grid investment programme
is so important,
that we improve the resilience,
distribution and capacity of our grid.
To get to the kernel of the Deputy's
question,
no housing development has not been
connected
because of a data centre.
PR6, which is our investment programme,
outlines all the various things we need to
do across the economy and society, that
is, the 300,000 new homes we need to
build, industrial growth, economic growth
and infrastructural projects like
MetroLink that we announced yesterday.
That will require further electricity
demand.
We want to drive that through renewables.
About 50% of our electricity so far this
year has been generated through clean
renewable sources.
We have doubled our wind capacity in ten
years and solar is a major part of our
energy mix now as well.
That said,
large energy user demand has to be managed
in a planned way and that is what the LEAP
does.
The
LEU,
final decision from
that it could not have a prioritisation
and had to deal with
on a first-come, first-served basis.
At this time, when there are soaring
energy bills and businesses are struggling
with costs, we see that there are new
proposals to give data centres access to
cut-price gas infrastructure.
The public cannot understand how the
Government could justify asking ordinary
families to pay more and more for
electricity, heating and energy prices
while facilitating further subsidies
and preferential treatment of some of the
wealthiest and the largest corporate
energy users in the whole State.
For years we know that ordinary households
and small businesses have been shouldering
a disproportionate amount of energy
taxation, network charges and energy
costs, but at the same time the cost
associated with expanding and reinforcing
infrastructure for large energy users
continues to grow.
We see the amount of energy in the Dublin
area, for example, that the large
data centres are taking up.
All we are calling for is fairness between
the ordinary people who are struggling
with
energy bills and the large corporate
energy users.
I did make reference to the Bill that Sinn
Féin published yesterday.
As with any Bill, from wherever
it comes, be that Opposition or
Government, I will look at it and do so in
The network charges are set by CRU.
From 2020 to 2026, the data centre sector
saw an average increase of 175%
in network costs.
I do not set the network charges; that is
just the reality.
There is, though, an overall issue of
affordability, which I know we will get to
during the course of the morning, whereby
we see elevated prices right the way
across the developed world, including here
in Ireland.
That is where the work of the national
energy affordability task force, which
will conclude soon and report to me, is
very important.
We have to do our best to soften the blow
of increases,
particularly for households and small
businesses, but how we get to a
sustainable way
is
accelerating renewable delivery and
delivering the infrastructure projects we
need, like the North-South interconnector.
interesting that the Minister mentioned
the task force because I wanted to speak
to him about the recent energy price hikes
and what resources he is taking to address
those.
What will the budget say?
Will there be an energy credit?
Will
commit that there will be no carbon tax
increases?
What other supports will be available for
households facing soaring heating costs
this winter?
announce the budget yet but I understand
energy will be an important part of it.
To deal with both the questions, we know
the situation in the Middle East.
That is having a serious impact on prices.
That follows from the continuing illegal
war in Ukraine, which has caused
significant disruption to energy markets.
I and
Government fully recognise the pressures
the resulting high prices are placing on
Irish consumers and businesses.
We have introduced a series of measures to
reduce fuel prices and further
measures are under consideration through
the energy affordability task force
as part of the budgetary process.
Specifically on fuel, the package of
Government support measures, which now
totals over €1.4 billion
which is the largest per capita in the
European Union, is helping
reduce the cost burden at the petrol pump
and diesel pump and assists key sectors
such as agriculture, haulage and the
productive sectors that are critical to
keeping our economy moving.
A range of measures in budget 2026 also
supported households, including the
reduction of
to 9% right the way through to 2030;
enhanced social protection payments, in
particular the extension of the fuel
allowance payment to those in receipt of
the working family payment, that is, about
468,000 households; and the €400 income
disregard for households involved in
Very
a record allocation of over €640 million
for
residential and community grant schemes
through the SEAI, allowing us to target
73,000 households this year.
Why is that really important?
because when we retrofit homes and
businesses, we bring about permanent
savings for those households and
businesses.
I amended the grants earlier this year.
We have seen a really significant increase
in the number of applications.
In some areas they have doubled because we
have broken them down.
You
have to
just one deep retrofit.
We brought in windows and doors grants,
wall cavity and attic insulation grants
and a heat pump grant of €12,500.
To the end of August, we got 89,000
applications.
That is more than in all of last year, so
people are responding to the supports
that are there.
It is important from a climate perspective
that we are reducing energy consumption
and emissions from households and
businesses, but critically it
is decreasing costs.
As far as we can estimate, a home retrofit
can lead to savings of between
€750 and €1,120 per annum on energy costs.
These are real measures.
If anything, during the course of the
budget I want to accelerate that and look
at other areas we can help through
permanent changes.
Other areas are under consideration in
advance of the budget.
The
will feed into that, and we are in the
middle of budget discussions right now.
A big focus will be on continuing
€2 billion has been invested there since
2019.
That is an area where we need to refocus
our efforts and accelerate delivery.
There are those who are struggling with
energy.
While the 90 days arrears figures have
plateaued,
are still a concern.
I
say to people
if they are in arrears they should ensure
they engage with their energy providers
and enter into repayment arrangements.
No one who is engaging with energy
companies will be cut off.
We will have protections during the course
of the winter.
Our disconnection rates are absolutely
miniscule, and rightly so.
However, we have to continue doing
everything we can to work to soften the
blow of increases we are seeing right the
way across the world and the European
Union.
retrofitting and heat pumps.
Does he accept that he is way behind on
his targets?
There is a crowd called Centrica, which,
when the State sold off the family silver
15 years ago, bought Bord Gáis Energy.
Centrica made a profit
only €814 million last year,
way down from €1.55 billion the year
before.
Its energy section, Bord Gáis Energy,
made profits of €72.5 million.
They are the ones increasing their bills.
We know all about the geopolitical
conflict and all of that, but the
Government has the resources to make extra
direct
commitments to people who are struggling,
such as not increasing, or removing, the
carbon tax on home heating oil in
particular and dealing with other energy
credits.
With the windfall profits they are making,
there should be extra charges
and an
I want to talk about the price of green
diesel.
has gone up to €1.60.
There is no package in place for
construction works vehicles,
even though the Tánaiste and the Taoiseach
promised it in early
May and the Taoiseach reiterated it where
is sitting now.
He said
construction vehicles would be included.
They are involved in construction of
houses and roads and everything.
The vehicles involved
None of those vehicles have been included
even though the promise was made.
The Minister mentioned it himself.
They have not been included.
Since 1 September, farmers have been left
hanging.
That is why I did not vote for what the
Government proposed in this Chamber on 28
August.
Farmers and agricultural contractors were
not included on
The Government has €100
million left over after some scheme.
Where is that now?
Who has it?
Are
going to spend it and give it out?
People have parked bigger machinery
because they
to Deputy Daly and the area of potential
windfall taxes on energy companies.
That is
being discussed at EU-wide level.
It was discussed in Brussels when I was
there earlier this month.
If
an approach on that it will probably be a
pan-European approach.
Taoiseach referred to it yesterday.
The last time, after the outbreak of the
war in Ukraine, approximately €200 million
was collected.
It is not going to move the dial on energy
bills, but it might give the State more
in its armoury to make permanent changes
to households such as acceleration of
solar and things we are doing
already.
to Deputy Healy-Rae.
I will answer the other one,
is the road transport support scheme,
which is for the hauliers.
There were more than 4,000 applications.
More than 3,000 have been paid out
already.
We are working through the rest of them
and there will be an appeals process once
that scheme closes.
Agricultural contractors were included in
the original scheme managed by the
Department and the Minister for
agriculture.
However, the Deputy is correct to say that
Government did agree on a scheme in
relation to
construction vehicles.
That is being worked through at the
moment.
Again, that does not fall directly under
my remit but as a member of Government, it
is a Government decision that has been
made.
and are working to now over the coming few
weeks are the measures we can take in
the budget.
One is about permanent changes and the
second is on supports and what can be done
there.
We have to focus it on those who need it
most.
More than a quarter of Irish households
receive direct fuel support payments.
It is
a difficult time
across the world with regard to elevated
prices.
We will do our best, but
not going to be able to deal with every
single cost increase.
home heating oil.
As the Minister knows, the prices for home
heating oil have surged by approximately
60% over the past year.
It particularly affects people in rural
A lot of those people have not had the
resources or the funds to pay for solar
upfront or to pay for retrofitting.
They feel excluded from this scheme.
People in those families need relief,
which means reducing or removing the
carbon tax on this home heating oil and
reintroducing the energy credits worth at
least €400 per household.
They are the fairest approach.
Everybody can benefit from it.
Will the Minister commit to looking at
that
and making some real difference to the
people living in fuel poverty?
Maybe that is what is wrong.
If the Minister is not responsible for the
construction industry, and Martin
because he is the Minister for
agriculture, maybe that is where the
problem lies.
The facts are
the Tánaiste and the Taoiseach promised
that construction and the vehicles
involved in construction would be covered.
Many of those construction companies were
locked into
prices they had for jobs at the start of
the year and locked into contracts.
The Tánaiste even
mentioned quarries and processing
materials.
None of those people
got one bob yet.
I am asking in the name of God - does the
Minister think these people can carry on
in the wind?
diesel has gone from 90
last January up to €1.68 yesterday.
Everything I know is using green diesel.
The Government has seen after the haulage,
but I have to say that is
the tax that they have paid.
The Government did not find it anywhere
else.
It came from them and the Government is
only giving it back to those people.
It is the same with the people who are
paying for green diesel.
The Government will have to do something
for them.
Every machine involved in civil works,
maintenance of roads and maintenance of
waterworks is using green diesel and they
have
nothing.
How long more is it going to take to
develop a scheme for them?
First,
of supports have been brought in already.
I
think anyone will dispute that.
going to get to it.
We have to put it in context.
That is not a small amount of money.
That is a major support and marked diesel
was included in that in the context of the
excise reductions.
Actually, when you look at it overall it
is approximately 7 cent per litre.
In fairness, the question put
relates to progress with the establishment
of the scheme for construction contractors
that are not covered under the other two
schemes.
On foot of the Deputy raising this, I will
make urgent inquiries with regard to the
progress on that scheme.
We provided significant moneys to the
haulage sector, and rightly so.
I was at the Irish Road Haulage
Association's conference in Killarney
in the Deputy's county the week before
last and addressed about 900 delegates
there.
They are very important to our
economy, as are construction contractors.
To get back to Deputy Daly's question,
home heating oil is an area where we have
seen significant increases.
We have stated already that, in
particular, there is a reliance in rural
Ireland - not exclusively but the majority
We are very aware of the substantial
increases in that
space.
I, the Minister for Finance and the
Taoiseach are working on proposals around
that.
We will work through that between now and
the budget.
The provisions that will be in the budget
will be announced on budget day.
We have not concluded the work on that.
Suffice to say we are acutely aware of the
issue around home heating oil and,
as I mentioned already, the issue around
accelerating the deployment of further
grants to make permanent changes to
households and businesses.
My question is very simple.
Will the Minister commission a report into
the number of data centres the Irish
energy grid and water networks can handle?
It is incredible we are in 2026 still
asking for
a simple report on the capacity of the
energy and water systems
to
handle the huge increase in data centres
over the past ten years.
I answered
in detail earlier on
the importance of ICT to the Irish
economy.
I want to put that in context.
We have about 190,000 people working in
the ICT sector, underpinned
by data centres.
It is an important part of our digital
infrastructure and it is part of
our large industrial energy use.
It has to be managed appropriately.
transmission system operator,
responsible for the operation and planning
of the electricity transmission system.
EirGrid balances supply and demand
continually while also planning for
Ireland’s long-term electricity needs.
Ireland has attracted some of the best
tech companies in the world and some of
the best data centres in the world.
When considering their impact, we need to
weigh wider economic benefits, including
employment, broader digital infrastructure
value and significant support and linkages
provided to other high-value sectors of
the economy.
The Government and I recognise the need to
balance those opportunities
with the challenges being faced and we
continue to work with the sector towards a
secure and decarbonised energy future.
The large energy user action plan,
which we published in January of this
year, sets out a plan-led approach to
planning to sustainable new energy
intensive industrial developments.
That is critical.
Through LEAP, a range of
development scenarios, including spatial
considerations, will be assessed to inform
policy choices going forward and to
support a more integrated approach to a
plan-led energy system across the system
operators, the regulator and Government.
Water usage management and conservation
across commercial and industrial - that
is, non-domestic - sectors, including data
centres, is under the remit of
Éireann.
Uisce Éireann has advised that, overall,
data centres are not a major driver of
demand on the public water supply network.
It is my understanding
they account for, on average, less than
0.3%
of
water supplied by
Éireann.
We have seen incredible growth in data
centres.
In 2015, 5% of our electricity use was by
data
centres.
It is now 23%, is projected to grow to 30%
in
the coming years and will continue to grow
even further than that.
I know the Minister's and Government's
argument for the red carpet being rolled
However, the report the Government came
out with in relation to that was
essentially a work of fiction.
why we need so many data centres.
That also is fiction because Sweden has
the highest proportion of
its workforce working in the ICT sector at
9%, yet
only
3% to 4% of its electricity use is by data
centres.
Ireland has 6% of its workforce in ICT,
which is significant
and
not understating it, but it does not mean
we have to allocate
23% of our electricity use to that sector.
Where is the comparability with what is
happening in Europe?
We are way off the scale with data
centres.
no red carpet being rolled out.
The Deputy has acknowledged, to be fair,
the significant employment underpinned by
ICT in this country - high-paid jobs, good
jobs and careers paths
for many of our people.
Ireland is at the leading edge of new
technologies and we want to remain in that
place.
That said, we have to manage demand and
supply.
That is why
the grid investment programme is critical.
We have to get ahead of demand
projections, and we will do that through
renewables.
The LEAP and the large energy user
decision published by CRU are critical
because any new connection
will only be provided to a data centre or
large user in that space who brings
forward 80% of the energy through
additional, renewable sources.
That will be managed in a plan-led way.
We published that earlier this year.
That is the policy.
It is not
anyone
applies to be connected gets connected.
That is not the way it is done.
That has been changed.
The LEAP would enable, potentially, 50% of
our electricity to go to
data centres in the coming years.
While the Minister said 80% has to come
from
renewables, there is a six-year path to
that happening.
In those six years, they can be based on
gas.
Data centres are pushing up our energy
prices, they are making our grid unstable
and they will make it impossible to meet
our climate targets, which should be a
concern to the Minister.
That risks us having to pay €28 billion in
fines.
There is no point in
shaking his head.
That is what will happen unless the
Minister knows something different.
Has he been told by Europe those fines
will not be imposed on countries that have
not met their targets?
We have to work on the assumption there is
a €28 billion fine coming our way in
2030.
The Minister is playing chicken with the
EU on this.
If it makes us pay it, we will be in
serious trouble.
that the grid is unstable is incorrect.
It is not.
We have to be responsible in what we say
in that regard.
It might suit a certain
political narrative of large energy users
and big corporations against everyone
else, eating up all our energy.
That might play well on social media.
There is a reality to managing economic
growth.
Why do we want to manage economic growth?
For the good of our people, for jobs, for
people's
so they can pay their mortgages, so they
can live well - that is why.
This is part of our industrial policy.
The LEAP sets out how that is done in a
plan-led way.
It is not a question of anyone rocking up
and, as the Deputy puts it, a red carpet
is put out.
That is not true.
That does not happen.
I take it the Social Democrats want to see
continued investment in our country.
Maybe they do not but we do.
We have to accelerate the delivery of grid
infrastructure, which
doing through PR 6.
That will enable us to get ahead of demand
projections.
That is the reality.
There is no cost of compliance agreed with
the EU and no formula.
None of that is agreed.
Anyone bandying around figures of €20
€28 billion is just incorrect.
The
replay my answer to the last four
questions but I understand why this is an
area of interest.
I thank him for tabling this question.
Our industrial electricity demand is
primarily concentrated in our digital
economy.
I say this because we are not a large
industrial nation.
We do not make trains or cars.
We do not have heavy industry here.
Our heavy industry is ICT.
Other countries in Europe have large heavy
industrial bases and use
energy for these.
Part of our competitiveness as a country,
and
attractiveness, is because of the
expertise of our people and the digital
economy.
A critical part of supporting jobs in the
economy and future growth is supporting
services, right down to public sector
digital services.
The economic footprint that
the ICT sector brings,
and I am talking about ICT in general, is
about €104 billion in gross added value.
This is about 20% of Ireland's economy.
It is significant but it has to be managed
appropriately.
The large energy user action plan is the
way forward.
We will always keep it under review.
It is very clear now with regard to new
connections that there have already been
connection agreements.
As mentioned earlier, about 23% of our
energy is used by large
data centres and large energy users.
Going forward from the adoption of LEAP,
it is very clear how new connection
agreements would be granted.
I do not grant them; they are granted
independently of me, and rightly so.
It all has to be balanced.
To answer the question directly, we
published the policy and adhere to it.
It is constantly kept under review.
My big focus as energy and climate
Minister is accelerating renewables,
reducing our dependence on fossil fuels
and getting our bills down, while also
ensuring that we can continue to attract
indigenous investment and foreign direct
investment.
It might be a bit tedious answering the
same question three times but
a reason
the
three Opposition climate spokespeople
has been on data centres.
It is because of the level of concern that
exists in the Opposition.
We see around the world that people are
waking up to the impact that data centres
are having in their communities, from
energy use to water use.
The Minister spoke about industrial
strategy.
We hear time and again that we have no
heavy industry here and, therefore, we can
have a big data centre industry but the
Minister for agriculture uses the exact
same argument.
He used it on the radio the other day when
trying to justify no changes to the status
We cannot have it both ways.
Even in Germany, where there is heavy
industry and a lot of jobs attached to it,
it accounts for about 25% of the country's
energy use.
We are going to exceed 25% over the next
few years given the trajectory.
This is why we are concerned and we just
want to make sure the Minister is staying
on
I welcome the fact it has been raised and
note it has been raised by three of the
It is a matter that is appropriate for
discussion.
This is why, in fairness, when I came into
this portfolio we looked at the situation
and what existed before and moved forward
with the large energy user action plan,
which is a plan-led approach, looking at
regions also.
This is the appropriate way to do it.
I mentioned to Deputy Daly earlier the PR
6 capital investment in the
grid.
This takes into account, over the next
five- or six-year period, all of the
growth that we need across various
sectors.
It also shows what we need to deliver
infrastructurally, such as the north-south
interconnector and the Celtic
interconnector.
It is a year late because of weather and
other issues but
needs to be delivered.
The acceleration of renewables is
critical.
In the first five or six months of this
year, about 50% of our electricity was
generated through renewables.
It is certainly going in the right
direction, with solar being a major part
of our mix.
Offshore will be the next critical part
and we are expecting planning decisions
over the course of the next few months to
get these projects into construction
between now and 2030.
It will be a massive game-changer for the
country.
on bringing through more renewable energy.
Offshore wind is vital.
Our issue on this side of the House is
that the renewable energy we are creating
at the moment is being gobbled up by data
centres.
We also know the impact this is having on
energy bills.
We
know how much water they use.
I know it is a relatively small percentage
but there is an unfairness at the heart of
how they are treated, whereby ordinary
people were asked to abide by a hosepipe
ban this summer whereas data centres
actually doubled their water consumption
during that time.
It is in situations like this that people
feel the unfairness.
They see they are not getting a fair
shake.
That is why we are bringing up the issue.
We completely acknowledge the importance
of underpinning jobs in the ICT sector
but, on the other hand, we have to be
concerned about some of the types of jobs
these hyper-scale AI data centres are
going to
keep this under review.
We spend half our time here talking about
how we will regulate and rein in these big
ICT companies while, on the other hand, we
are doing everything we can to facilitate
We have to watch
Any connection application made goes
through an independent process and it can
be accepted or declined.
Not every connection application that is
made is approved.
That is a fact,
if we look at how many new data centres
have been built or delivered in the past
few years, there are very few.
Someone referenced Sweden.
If we look at Finland, it has received
extremely large data centre
investment, to the tune of about €20
billion.
Obvious we
have to step through what is appropriate
and what can be managed and manage overall
demand, while really focusing on
expanding our grid capacity for everybody,
for the good of jobs and our
reduce bills.
This is where the focus is at.
Deputy Ahern is perfectly entitled to
raise
to AI regulation, it is a debate that is
current and that will continue.
It is important that
What additional measures is the Minister
taking to address the fact the EPA
recently stated emissions are falling far
too slowly?
Will he make a statement on the
committed to supporting emissions
reductions in the built environment sector
across the economy.
That is what Deputy Daly specifically
asked in the question.
We are taking action every day to
implement climate mitigation measures,
which also provide warmer and more
comfortable homes and support energy
affordability, energy security and energy
sustainability for households and
businesses.
The EPA's latest provisional greenhouse
gas emissions inventory, published in
July, shows the impact this work is
having.
Emissions fell in all main sectors in 2025
and emissions from buildings decreased by
4.7%.
Overall emissions have fallen for a fourth
consecutive year and
at the lowest level they have been for 36
years.
Emissions per capita are now at the lowest
level since 1990.
On
of
record reductions, we are projected to
achieve the first carbon budget and the
sectoral emissions ceiling in the
residential and public
and
They
get us to 50% by 2030 but the EPA
projections to 2030 have improved across
most sectors.
This is a clear sign
making progress.
importantly, for four years we have been
able to decouple economic growth from
emissions growth.
We are back to
1990 emissions level but we have 1.5
million more people in the Republic,
1 million more homes and more than 1
million more cars.
We need to accelerate this and try to
bridge that gap.
A big part of this, and
mentioned the built environment in
particular, is made up of the grant
schemes and
investment in retrofitting that I
mentioned.
There have been about 287,000 home
upgrades.
We need to do more on the public built
environment also.
Some very good work
being done in our university sector and in
hospitals and local authorities.
It is our job to accelerate this.
The next climate action plan, which I will
publish
well before the end of this year and
intend to bring to Cabinet at the end of
October, will cover this year and 2027.
It will be a more focused plan and will
identify strategic climate priorities
that will shape our approach to closing
the gap to 2030.
what additional measures the Minister will
be taking.
He knows that many people feel excluded.
In my view,
a just transition because people cannot
afford to get on a lot of these schemes.
There is the risk of fines from Europe,
up to €28 billion, as has been said.
The Minister also mentioned offshore wind.
I spoke with developers yesterday who told
me it is unlikely that a turbine will be
wet by 2035.
We had a target of 5 GW.
Clearly, that is not going to happen.
way behind on solar energy too.
The programme for Government outlined that
there will be solar guidelines, but we are
still waiting for them nearly one and a
half years later.
Developers, communities and people need to
know and have clarity
about what is going to be allowed into
their community.
Some of the solar developers work better
than others.
Some have better community engagement than
others.
Does the Minister have any views?
Is he going to tell us when those
guidelines will come
mentioned
accessibility of grants.
That is what I changed earlier this year.
We
want to leave anybody behind.
There are some questions later about the
warmer homes scheme, which is
the
full 100% grant.
We have done full deep retrofits, which
are 100% grant-aided, for close to 40,000
homes for lower income families.
That is really important.
I changed the grants earlier this year to
break them down
brought
the windows and doors
unless they did a deep retrofit.
The combined grant is €4,800.
I doubled the heat pump grant to €12,500.
Wall, cavity and attic
all increased.
These grants are all accessible.
It is not necessary to do everything
together.
get the windows and doors grant with only
one additional measure, like attic
insulation.
We are seeing people respond to that.
I gave a figure earlier of well over
80,000 grant applications.
I always keep this
under review in respect of whether there
are additional
not increased grants -
we can bring in.
That is paid for through the carbon tax,
and this is why
important that
tax is used to make permanent changes for
households.
I responded to the Deputy earlier in
relation to home heating oil.
We are looking at
in advance of the budget.
The Government gives the impression it is
completely ring-fenced, but it clearly
Apart from committing not to have any more
carbon tax increases, because people in
poorer households are suffering much more
than others because of the carbon tax,
will the Minister consider solar energy
guidelines?
I ask him to answer this question because
we
got an answer to it yet.
We see what is done in the Netherlands.
It has a solar ladder that prioritises
rooftop, followed by urban and industrial
land, then brownfield sites and then
agricultural land as a last resort.
There is a more plan-led approach in
Denmark, underpinned by strong local
engagement, municipal-led site selection
and a long tradition of community
participation.
Some of the solar companies work much
better than others with their community
engagement.
I see that in the various developments
happening around County Kerry, but
guidelines are needed, as opposed to
having communities depend on industry-led
guidelines that the companies themselves
operate to varying degrees.
On the planning guidelines, work is being
done on them.
The Minister for Housing, Local Government
and
Obviously, we feed into it.
I agree with the Deputy.
Most
in the development sector engage well with
communities.
After these questions conclude,
out in my own county, in Ballyboughal, for
the opening of a very large solar farm up
there.
Solar
is a very important clean resource.
There are 3 GW of it in our energy system
now.
If
go back 11 years,
It has grown
rooftop solar energy installed and
having a significant impact in reducing
people's bills.
I want us to do more on this.
I will speak to
Minister, Deputy Browne, over the next few
days and seek an update on the progress
with the solar PV guidelines.
a
approach to climate adaptation underpinned
by the 2024 national adaptation
framework, NAF.
This framework, as
is co-ordinated by our Department via the
national adaptation steering committee,
In 2025, the
EPA, published Ireland’s first national
climate change risk assessment, NCCRA.
It identifies national climate change
risks and ranks areas where action is
needed to be prioritised to make Ireland
more resilient to the impacts of climate
change.
We know from the NCCRA, and from the
standardised climate data from Met
Éireann, that more frequent and intense
storms, longer periods of drought, rising
sea levels, heatwaves, floods and coastal
change are just some of the impacts of our
changing climate to which we must adapt.
data and knowledge which has underpinned
the development of ten sectoral adaptation
plans,
covering 13
sectors such as agriculture, water
management, flood risk management and
health.
Those plans were approved and published by
Government
in November 2025.
In developing the plans, sectors were
required to collaborate on cross-cutting
issues
with climate action regional offices,
to ensure a cohesive approach at both the
national and local
In 2024, 31 local authority climate action
plans,
were published, which included adaptation
actions to build resilience against flood,
heat, and drought in our communities.
Since 2022, approximately €19 million has
been paid to local authorities by our
Department to develop the implementation
of their local plans.
A new adaptation taskforce, which
Minister established at the end of last
year, provides for senior-level oversight
and co-ordination of Ireland’s approach to
adaptation, including systemic delivery
barriers and cross-cutting issues and
risks.
In terms of water restrictions, which I
know is one of the most important issues
and the one that was very much in play
during the most recent period
of warm weather, reduced rainfall and
ecosystems and river levels, these are
matters for
in the first instance and not ones
which the Minister has any function.
We had a great summer here.
We all enjoyed the bit of heat, but it is
the second year in a row where we have
experienced our hottest summer on record.
Temperatures that used to be anomalies in
the past are now becoming consistent.
It is that direction of travel that we are
really concerned about, because we all
know it has such huge impacts on our
society.
This is the case in urban areas when it
Even new apartment designs that are single
aspect do not allow for draughts
to come through apartments.
We have huge societal issues
we have to grasp here.
aside from the impact it is going to have
on our agricultural sector, our growers
and all of that as well.
There will also be an impact on our
biodiversity from the wildfires we saw
across huge swathes of our mountains and
forests during the summer.
In my area in Dublin South-West, this
included the beautiful Featherbeds, where
We need a co-ordinated approach.
The Minister of State spoke about local
authorities, but what is the co-ordinated
approach?
got it, as we have.
The challenge is real.
We have moved to a point where the
doubters in relation to climate change are
starting to understand that it is real and
that
here.
We have to put in place a systemic
approach to addressing it in respect of
the adaptation and mitigation measures we
put in place.
As I said, it is co-ordinated centrally.
The involvement of the local authorities
is the appropriate way.
We have the sectoral plans in the first
instance across the various areas.
The Deputy identified agriculture and the
impact climate change is having on that
sector.
We saw the intensity of that in the south
east.
of course, issues that will have to be
addressed there in relation to winter
It also, however, has implications for
cities and towns.
The Deputy identified those areas.
This is why the local authorities will
play a key role and
why
being funded by central government to
develop their plans.
is
going to get worse.
We are likely to have another record
heatwave next summer.
Aside from
issues we spoke about earlier, there are
also serious health implications here as
well for vulnerable communities and older
people.
The 2023 climate action plan said it was
necessary to develop a new public health
heatwave plan and
seek to ensure more uniform planning
for heatwaves.
That recommendation was not included in
the 2024 or 2025 versions of the climate
action plan.
I wonder
Other things we need to look at are
temperature regulations for workers,
maximum working temperatures and a legal
maximum it is safe for people to work
at.
Multi-departmental work needs to happen.
We want to make sure it is being done.
important area, in particular for people
with compromised immune systems or
categorised illnesses and the elderly who
find themselves depending
on their accommodation.
That is why, as I identified, there are 13
sectoral plans, one of which is health.
That
clearly for the Department of Health and
the HSE to work on, developing plans and
procedures to mitigate, insofar as
possible, the greatest impacts of
significant increases in heat.
It also has
the supply of food and food security,
which is an important component.
That is why the agricultural piece is in
there.
Local authorities and entities like Uisce
Éireann need to be able to ensure that
there is a ready supply of water,
and that we will not be left in a position
that there
a ready supply of clean water.
All of the elements the Deputy identified
are appropriate and right.
A plan
in place.
The sectoral approach is the way to do it.
We believe the funding to local
authorities from central government
addresses the concerns
the
The
Minister
will have heard me raise this issue in the
past.
It relates to the better energy warmer
homes scheme.
The Government has taken significant steps
to increase the number of people eligible
for the fuel allowance.
However, there will be people this winter
who do not have a heating system in their
home and have no mechanism
to gain one because of recent EU
regulations in regard to
stand-alone fossil fuel boilers.
The warmer homes scheme aims to improve
the energy efficiency and warmth of homes
owned by people at risk of energy poverty
by providing fully funded retrofits to
households in receipt of certain
Department of Social Protection income
supports.
I am pleased to say delivery under the
scheme has ramped up hugely in recent
years.
Just over 3,000 homes were upgraded in
2019, compared with
8,100 last year, or 109% of what we
targeted.
Between 2019 and August of this year, we
did
39,500 fully funded upgrades for
households at risk of energy poverty.
Budget 2026 provided €340 million for
warmer homes,
with a target to complete 11,500 homes
this year.
We must also remember the scheme has
developed over time and it is delivering
deeper upgrades that take longer to
complete.
The average cost per home under the scheme
in the first half of 2026 was
€28,500.
It is a significant investment,
rightly
so.
In addition, under the national retrofit
plan, a new, higher fixed-amount grant for
attic insulation and cavity wall
insulation was introduced for homeowners
who are qualifying social protection
payment recipients.
That allows qualifying homeowners at risk
of energy poverty to get these works done
using SEAI-registered grant contractors on
a shorter timeline.
Eligible applicants can keep their place
on the warmers homes scheme list.
That is a
for, which we were happy to make.
The success of the scheme has meant a
serious increase in applications, with
over 10,800 this year, up 52% on last
year.
A waiting list action plan is being
developed.
I met the SEAI only last week about this.
also engaging with contractors to increase
their output.
Under the warmer homes scheme, upgrades
recommended by the SEAI technical surveyor
will depend on many factors including age,
size and
type and condition of the property.
Heating system upgrades, which the Deputy
specifically asked about, can be
recommended under the scheme in certain
cases where the home is being insulated
Where more than 25% of the area of the
walls is being externally or internally
insulated, the existing heating system
must be appraised for replacement.
People with existing boilers, because of
EU regulations
in place in Ireland under the energy
performance of buildings directive, cannot
receive a grant to replace it with another
fossil
boiler.
I am looking at measures on that in
advance of the budget.
The warmer homes
is great and we are seeing turnaround
times
between
application and completion of works
reduce.
I will have an update on that in the next
couple of weeks.
The number of homes done through the
scheme has increased year on year.
It will be close to 11,500 this year.
I do not have the projections for the end
of the year but it will be an increase on
last year.
On what we can do to help people with
boilers that are coming to end of life, I
am working on that in advance of the
budget.
correct that the warmer homes scheme is
hugely popular.
That and the increase in the fuel
allowance are exactly the kind of
ring-fenced funding that carbon tax
provides.
The difficulty is that people
heading into this winter have either no
central heating system, no back boiler
system or a broken gas boiler and they
cannot get the warmer homes
because they have no boiler to register
the heat loss indicator.
They used to be able to get the local
council grant but that is gone.
As a last resort, I was able to send them
to the
Social Protection for an emergency
payment, but the Department is now saying
it will not fund it either.
I
people heading into a second winter with
no heating system and no way of getting it
who also cannot get the warmer homes
grant.
There is clearly a regulatory gap.
It is not an issue of funding but there is
a problem whereby people just do not have
the €2,500 or €3,000 to get a boiler and
they cannot get the warmer homes scheme or
any sort of support so they will have no
heating this year.
That is
not Government
I agree with the Deputy.
I mentioned in my first response that I am
looking at this very issue right now
in advance of the budget.
I announced earlier this year that we
would trial high-temperature heat pumps,
plug-in heat pumps, which I think will be
an option.
A pilot of about 100 homes
I think a number
We
get the data from that.
It could be a very good near-term
solution.
We
get the data by the end of the year
early next year.
Should the data stack up, it provides us
with an opportunity to roll this out at
scale.
It has the potential to
really good option.
also looking at other measures in advance
of the budget, which I discussed only last
week with Cabinet colleagues,
and the Tánaiste in budget preparation,
boilers either are gone or
about to go, and what we can do in that
space.
The high-temperature heat pump has real
potential but we are in the middle of that
pilot right now.
I met the European Heat Pump Association
last week, something I
often say.
We had a good meeting looking at what is
being done across Europe.
pumps.
I am focusing on
because it could make a significant
difference for many households if the data
stacks up that it would work without a
major retrofit on top.
That is something we want to ensure we can
do.
keep
aware of
cases he has raised with me where people
in this bind cannot afford to replace the
boiler and are going into their second
winter post the European buildings
directive, which precludes local
authorities from providing grants.
I know
the issue.
I have even raised this issue with Michael
McGrath, the
Commissioner, because it is a good example
of how something intended to have a
positive contribution to our environment
goals is having a negative impact.
These kinds of things undermine confidence
in the EU because they are a silly
application of something.
The problem is the technology does not
exist.
There is no gap between a €2,500 gas
boiler and a
or €40,000 electric heat pump.
The new pilots are welcome.
a balance with regard to Exchequer funding
as well.
I accept that.
The SEAI has met me.
It has been proactive.
It has had the pilot scheme, which was
implemented in a number of cases I brought
to the SEAI, where compassion was needed.
the budget.
needs to be easy to use.
A lot of these people are older people who
understand all the mechanisms of different
grant schemes.
I appreciate the Minister's support
because there are people who really need
it.
our work on this over the course of the
next couple of weeks.
There will be a lead-in period.
If I am able to get approval to do
something specific in this space, I
will see it implemented in January.
I recognise the costs.
We doubled the existing heat pump grants
to €12,500.
They are significant, but for lower income
families, can we go that bit further and
just cover the heat pumps?
It involves labour costs and installation.
The grant covers a significant amount of
the cost of the equipment.
Where the plug-in heat pump has real
potential is
it reduces the need for a lot of other
work, such as radiator replacement and
that type of thing, which sometimes puts
people off doing the work.
expect to be able to make announcements in
the coming weeks.
If I get approval, there will be a lead-in
period.
I just wanted to say that.
If I get it, I would love to bring it in
in January of next year.
You certainly can.
All interventions are
gratefully received.
to
the impact of electricity demand from data
centres on the public network.
What studies have been carried out by the
Department to determine the impact
on householders and any additional costs
to the public in general?
It is not a case of arguing against all
data centres.
There will be data centres, but the
proliferation of them in this country is
high and they are having a significant
impact on the grid and on costs.
Many Deputies have raised this matter
and I have answered in detail.
However, to answer the Deputy, for fear of
repetition, data centres provide essential
knowledge-intensive location for
digital and tech
in ICT,
so it is significant.
We are not a large, heavy industry country
but I would contend
is that sector.
The digital infrastructure is underpinned
in many ways by data centres, which
provide significant support to all areas
of our economy.
We brought forward the Large Energy User
Action Plan, which I published in January
2026.
It sets out the plan-led approach to
enable Ireland to attract the next
generation of investment in strategic
energy-intensive sectors in the medium to
long term.
It will ensure future growth remains
aligned with Ireland's green transition,
energy affordability and security
objectives, as well other strategic
Government priorities such as the
provision of
transport and water.
The Government remains committed to
investing in critical infrastructure to
deliver electricity to a growing
population and growing economy, with new
housing and expanding businesses.
Our grid investment programme provides an
historic investment in Ireland's
electricity grid infrastructure
up to €18.9 billion,
over 520 capital projects to be delivered
over the next five
years.
They include 29 significant transmission
infrastructure projects and 32
distribution substations.
I meet every month with EirGrid and ESB
Networks about their work programme to
monitor that investment.
In the Deputy's area of Laois, in July I
was delighted to open the ESB Networks
Bracklone 110kV substation, which was the
first major substation
delivered under this capital programme.
It will have a massive positive impact on
the area and on energy and electricity
The Minister outlined the 190,000 jobs,
but very few of them are
in data
The point I am making is that almost a
quarter of the available supply is being
used by data centres and there are reports
it could grow to more than one third and
more.
That puts huge pressure on the network.
It puts a
of pressure on EirGrid and ESB Networks to
upgrade the grid and put significant
investment
in favour of the investment in it because
I welcome the opening of the substation in
my area, where it is needed for the
increased industry and jobs in the area
increased population, not to mention the
housing that is being built, but a recent
study has shown data centres are putting
an additional cost on householders.
The data centres are getting cheaper
electricity than Joe and Mary Public.
That is the point.
They are getting cheaper electricity while
the public is paying for the upgrade.
There is now an upgrade levy on everyone's
bill.
That is the key point the Minister needs
to take home.
We have a huge proliferation of them
compared with other EU states and some
American states are
saying "No, not on our patch" to them now,
but we are accepting everything.
We need to have a more measured approach
to this.
important
we debate it, but not every application is
accepted.
I do not just accept every application
that comes in.
for
connection agreements are made and they
can be accepted or refused.
We have set out how new applications have
to be processed in a plan-led way.
It is not just first come, first served or
that people just apply for a data centre
and get it.
PR6, the grid investment programme,
outlines what we need to do to get ahead
of the energy demand projections and
a big
In response to another Deputy's question
earlier, I mentioned network charges,
which are set by the Commission for
Regulation
Utilities, CRU.
I do not set them.
I know the Deputy did not say I
data centres, between 2020 and 2026, the
network charges have increased by
175%.
That is just to put the facts on the floor
of the House.
It has to be managed appropriately.
I agree with the Deputy about that.
of issues.
We are trying to construct 50,000 homes
per year and
again
this week that the supply of housing is
being hampered by the supply of water
and electricity connections.
There is clearly a pull factor and the
Government has to take into consideration
that there have to be jobs in other
sectors and homes have to be built.
There is pressure here every day with
people talking about it.
We are putting pressure on
Government about it.
The Government is under pressure and
putting pressure on officials and local
authorities to step up to the plate and
drive on the
We have to look at things in the round,
but we have a habit in this country - and
I
want to give
a history lesson going back to the crash
and so on - of putting too many eggs in
one basket.
I agree that not all of them get planning
permission, but the sheer number going in
and the supply of water and electricity
going into them could throw the economy
off to one side and have a negative effect
on other sectors.
That is the key point.
centres.
They are its figures.
I just wanted to put that on the record of
the House again.
However, I reiterate
it has to be managed and
doing that.
That is why Peter Burke
brought forward the Large Energy User
Action Plan.
It sets out how, in a plan-led way,
of the conditions of future connection
agreements for data centres
We
seen a large number of data centres
connected
to be fair, that when applications are
made, not even for planning but for a
connection agreement, they are all
granted.
We have set down clearly what
the criteria for getting a connection
agreement
is
important.
It is important
Earlier this year, the Minister wrote to
the SEAI expressing concern that it had
left €120 million
capital unspent.
Since then, he has highlighted the rising
numbers
for
There is a recognition among the public
that, to be as energy secure as possible,
they need to retrofit.
The Government has fantastic ambition in
this space but is the
SEAI set up for success?
Does it have sufficient resources and
capacity and
skill sets?
What are we doing to make sure it delivers
on
Government's ambition in
to highlight the fact that the SEAI
underspent last year, even though it did
more homes than it had ever done before.
That is not a situation that we want.
We want this money invested in permanent
changes to reduce energy consumption in
households and businesses to reduce their
costs and reduce emissions.
That is why, earlier on this year,
I worked directly with the SEAI and
instructed it to break down the grants to
make them more accessible.
We brought forward new windows and doors
grants
the fixed grant levels for attic and
cavity wall insulation.
We put a greater focus on supports for
undertaking retrofit measures on an
incremental basis as opposed to
just one deep retrofit,
which
A
very purist approach was taken before.
A retrofit had to cover everything.
We
changed that to give people a pathway
towards a full retrofit.
I see
Deputy O'Gorman has arrived.
I listened to his interview on this issue
on the radio earlier, when he said there
no changes to SEAI grants over the course
of the past year, which is not correct.
this year we have seen 88,000
applications.
We have to watch the spend, however.
I do not have the final year projections.
Obviously,
see what has been expended yet.
I know the SEAI is spending and investing
more than ever.
I expect an element of underspend this
year.
I
know what that amount will be.
It will be substantially less than last
year.
It is not something I welcome but I
acknowledge the fact that we
brought in a whole suite of new schemes.
With the support of Deputy Boland and of
additional supports.
not
increased grant amounts but
additional things that we discussed here
earlier, such as boiler replacements.
Frankly, these are things that should have
been done before.
We are
looking at storage.
That is what
working through right now.
We are watching the spend very carefully.
I met
the SEAI
just last week.
I meet with the authority regularly on
this.
Real progress
being made on the
of homes being retrofitted and
to be welcomed but we need to make sure
that the moneys raised are
invested in retrofitting measures for
households and businesses.
I agree with
absolutely essential that the money
Government is providing to the SEAI is
actually used and given to people for
retrofits.
I also very much welcome the improvements
the Minister has made in the scheme this
year.
They have made it much easier and more
financially viable for people to put in
new windows,
and so
I appreciate that.
In terms of the warmer homes schemes the
Minister mentioned earlier, the issue has
been raised that there are people who are
in serious danger of not having heating in
their homes this year.
What is the SEAI doing to decrease
turnaround times and
reduce them from
on.
We did 8,100 warmer homes schemes
in the last full year, 2025, which is a
big increase.
Overall, just short of 40,000 homes have
been done.
We will exceed that this year.
Obviously, we still have a few months to
go.
We will exceed the number done
the previous year.
the issue of those who have end-of-life
boilers.
There are specific things that we can do.
We are piloting high-temperature heat
pumps, the
heat pumps, at the moment.
That pilot will continue for the next few
months.
Should
efficiencies
from that, should it be an option and
the data from that pilot stack up, there
will be an opportunity for us to roll that
out at scale.
That would be a very viable replacement
for boilers.
However, in the meantime and in advance of
the budget, I am working on measures for
that particular cohort.
get the exact figure but turnaround times
have gone from 22 months to 15 months.
That is from
date of application to
completion of works.
It is still a long time.
There is a lag in getting a contractor and
so on.
However, there is a big focus on that
because there are significant savings
for people, particularly those in energy
poverty.
I welcome that.
I had not heard
the 15 months.
When I looked at the SEAI's website
yesterday, it was still telling me
26 months.
It is important that be updated,
notwithstanding whatever we can do to
reduce the times.
actually getting this work done, the SEAI
appoints a contractor from its approved
list.
Is there
sufficient
contractors on the SEAI's approved list?
What can we do to increase the number?
We really need to do whatever we can to
make sure that people are warm in their
homes this winter.
On the
contractors, that was part of the
discussion I had with the SEAI last week.
It went out to public procurement for
contractors for the warmer homes
and selected a number of contractors.
I have asked
to review that with a view to adding more.
I know of a couple of contractors
very good companies, that
I am looking at Deputy Carthy, who might
be aware of one
in his own area.
These omissions surprised me.
I have asked those questions of the SEAI
at our meeting.
I met
on that particular issue the week before
last.
It is going to come back to me.
I think we have an opportunity to get more
contractors into the warmer homes scheme,
notwithstanding the fact that the
authority has awarded contracts
recently.
It is about having additional resources to
fast-track delivery.
Particularly during an energy crisis and
when we are seeing such price increases,
these really good climate measures and
energy reduction measures are also
permanent cost reduction measures.
We need to treat that appropriately.
I will come back
the Minister of State's Department
received any reports from the National
I do not know if his prepared remarks
touch on the issue of
the number of waste collectors in each
local authority area but
there is a fear around the
consolidation is having on consumer
prices.
The National Waste Collection Permit
Office, which the Deputy will know is
hosted by Offaly County Council, is the
designated nominated authority for the
processing and review of all waste
collection permits issued within the
State.
The Department is,
in regular contact with the NWCPO.
This contact includes meetings, fora and
steering committees to discuss topics
the collection of the waste recovery levy,
and the implementation of relevant actions
in the Waste Action Plan for a Circular
Economy.
The Waste Action Plan for a Circular
Economy contains a commitment to introduce
further measures to incentivise the
prevention and segregation of waste.
Arising from this commitment, the National
Waste Collection Permit Office
commissioned an independent study on
incentivised waste charging and its
potential implementation through the waste
collection permitting system.
This study, which has been shared with our
Department, examines what changes could be
made to the permitting system for waste
collectors to fully incentivise waste
prevention and improve source segregation
practices by their customers to minimise
their waste collection bills.
Recommendations will be considered in
conjunction with outcomes from the
feasibility study into transitioning our
national waste collection
from the current competitive licensing
system to a franchise model.
Both will inform the development of the
next iteration of the WAPCE with a view to
recycling among households and businesses
to meet targets
established by the EU waste framework
directive.
The reason I ask this question is that I
believe there is a need for
a hands-on approach to one particular
issue.
I
know if
the same across the board but in many
rural counties we have seen a pattern of
behaviour where large multinational waste
collection companies
decide to come into a county.
In the first instance, they try to
purchase all the local waste collection
services.
Where that does not happen, what appear to
me to be very aggressive
marketing strategies are employed.
This can sometimes involve multiple
representatives calling to doors and
leaflets such as
I have here
offering knock-down discount prices.
The fear is that this is an attempt to
monopolise the system
outside of the regulations.
Is the Minister of State aware of this
practice and is he planning to take any
action in response?
familiar with the practices the Deputy is
talking about.
There has been debate
for some time.
There is widespread concern
that, in some places, there is a
multiplicity of waste collection trucks
moving around the same area one after
another.
That obviously has an impact on the
environment,
traffic congestion and so
All
these matters are under review under a
broader outlook in terms
of the circular economy.
From a Government perspective, the
strategic approach is to try to reduce and
minimise the amount of waste that is out
there and to try to get greater reuse of
commodities that are generated from scarce
resources.
It is about reducing the impact on our
environment - much of that is about
behavioural change and ensuring the
appropriate systems are there to encourage
our citizens to not disregard
or dispense with products that have the
capacity to be upcycled.
That is very much feeding into our
strategy.
I know what the Deputy is talking about,
which is the operationalisation of that on
the ground.
However, over time, the ambition of
the Government is to reduce the amount of
waste that will ultimately be collected.
We all have a shared objective in that
regard; we all want to reduce the amount
of waste.
The difficulty is that in the scenario I
spoke about, where these multinational
companies essentially secure de facto
monopolies in local authority areas where
they are the only real option, the
knockdown prices go very quickly.
You are then back to what are eye
watering, staggering costs
for waste collection that would not be in
place if there were local competitors.
Will
ask his Department to carry out an
analysis, in conjunction with the National
Waste Collection Permit Office, in respect
of how many operators have licences and
are operating within each local authority
area and what the average costs are?
I think the analysis will find a
correlation between a reduction in
providers and an increase in cost.
Ultimately, this is a twin-track approach.
I agree entirely with
that
but we also need to ensure that our
families are not being fleeced by these
large corporations which are knocking out
all of their competitors outside of an
agreed policy framework.
to is the need for a comprehensive policy
framework in place
that looks at, in the first instance, the
reduction of waste through recycling,
upcycling and minimisation.
That is a given and we all support that.
In getting to that better place we want to
get to, we
still have a competitive edge or a
capacity to manage the cost of waste
disposal where certain waste products have
to be disposed of.
I am certainly prepared to ask the
Department to have a further look at what
that entails.
There are different models out there that
have been looked at.
There is competition for the marketplace.
There is the direct competition of a
series of local operators.
That is challenging because it is possible
for others to buy up licences -
that is the marketplace - but, of course,
we also have to ensure
citizens are not fleeced in the event of
predatory practices of some
large operators.
operators, EirGrid and ESB Networks, are
charged with responsibility for upgrading
our electricity system, including planning
and constructing new investments in the
grid.
They are accountable to
in that regard.
However, investing in and ensuring a fit
for purpose electricity grid is
an absolute priority for me and the
Government.
I regularly meet with ESB Networks and
with
meeting with EirGrid later today on its
work as well.
I meet EirGrid and ESB Networks together
every month, specifically on PR 6
and the work
In July,
I was very pleased to open ESB Networks'
new Bracklone 110 kV substation
in Laois.
That was the first one of
delivered under the PR 6 programme.
There was really good work done.
There was also the North-South
interconnector, the Moneypoint 400 kV
series capacitor and the Letterkenny 100
kV line redevelopment, which are
covered under the Critical Infrastructure
Act.
We saw Moneypoint come through pretty much
straight away after that.
The system operators are waiting for
confirmation from local authorities on
planning conditions for the North-South
interconnector.
Monaghan County Council is the
local authority.
I hope it discharges its consent without
any further delay.
The Moneypoint capacitor has
up to €18.9 billion - it is really
critical.
When you break down the 520 projects, it
is really down to 29 transmission projects
and 32 distribution projects.
Ten of these transmission projects are
already under construction.
That is really good.
One of the priority distribution projects
is already completed and three further
projects are in construction.
I meet
every single month to go through the list
of the main projects to
make sure
timelines are not slipping, to identify
any risks that are there and to keep the
pressure on.
I thank ESB Networks and
for the reply.
We saw the Central Bank report yesterday
and its concerns
that the connection for essential
infrastructure like energy and water are
clear barriers to the delivery of
essential housing, particularly
social and affordable housing, and it
takes up to four years now.
We also saw
the impacts
Storm
flooding in the Listowel area.
The Minister mentioned some of the
projects that are
under way, such as the 29 projects and ten
under construction.
What are the delivery timelines for them
and when
expect they will be completed?
we look at some other
really have an energy crisis.
They are totally resilient.
The infrastructure is in place there and
they are almost completely
energy independent.
Could the Minister give me some insight
into the timelines?
visibility across the projects and there
is.
I have no difficulty in getting that
to
but the operators make
that detailed information on the progress
of investments, and
rightly so.
In December, CRU published the
transmission baseline programme, which
sets out all
the transmission projects in PR 6, along
with the associated delivery milestones.
EirGrid publishes updates in respect of
delivery against these
milestones every quarter.
They are available on their website.
It is rightly made public.
We are not saying every single project
will be delivered on time under this
massive programme but I have asked it to
really identify and focus on the most
critical projects under PR 6.
I meet them every month together and I am
meeting EirGrid again
today.
Above all else, this provides that
resilience for the grid, allows us to
increase our capacity, get more renewables
into our system and provide more storage -
we are third in Europe for long duration
battery storage but we still need more.
This is the absolute focus of what we do
and the real priority area
them
saying
the delivery of the projects are all up to
date and on time?
I
have two questions arising from what
said.
How far behind are some of the projects or
what projects concern the Minister?
What steps are being taken to get them up
to speed?
Second, on grid prioritisation, what is
the Minister's view on that
and will he support the legislation we
brought forward yesterday?
the projects that are outlined, from the
detail I get as to where they are, a lot
of them have already commenced and that is
good.
There is not major slippage within it.
We will get
some details on that.
Not every milestone in every project will
be hit
but I want the majority of them hit.
Already, I have given the example of
Bracklone in Laois, which was delivered
ahead of time and on budget.
We really need to get the North-South
interconnector started.
That is why
so important that consent is discharged by
the lead local authority.
met representatives from Monaghan, Cavan
and Meath over the summer.
They were the three local authorities.
That needs to start.
Above all else, if
to pick one project that needs to happen
it is the Noth-South one.
We will look at the Deputy's Bill, which
was only published yesterday.
I am happy to see what is in
I have to cut the time in a few minutes.
always take your direction,
The Government is committed to delivering
on Ireland’s responsibility to address the
climate crisis and work remains ongoing
across government to implement climate
mitigation measures every day.
We have a robust climate delivery
framework and detailed plans in place
across all sectors.
The priority is driving implementation,
particularly of high-impact measures with
multiple societal and economic benefits.
The EPA's latest provisional greenhouse
gas emissions inventory, published in
July, shows that this is working.
Ireland recorded overall emissions
reductions for a fourth consecutive year.
All main sectors saw reductions in 2025.
The Green Party's time in government
was helpful in ensuring we remain on that
trajectory.
Emissions from energy industries decreased
for the fourth consecutive year, by 7.1%
in 2025, to an all-time low as investment
in renewables continues to reduce
emissions.
Emissions from buildings decreased by 4.7%
and tonnes of CO2 per household are at
their lowest recorded level.
In addition, other sectors also showed
reductions with the industry sector
emissions down by 3.3%, transport down by
1.5% and agriculture down by
0.2%.
Significantly, the EPA's report shows that
the first carbon budget has now been
achieved on the back of these record
emissions reductions.
Ireland now has the lowest level of
greenhouse gas emissions in 36 years which
is notable given a concurrent population
increase of approximately 1.5 million
people,
more than 1 million new homes and over 1
million extra vehicles on our roads.
Given the strong economic growth over this
period, we can now see a clear decoupling
of growth from emissions which is a key
milestone in Ireland's transition to
climate neutrality.
September and there is still no climate
action plan for 2026.
The idea behind the climate action plan
was
on the one hand we have the five-year
carbon budgets making the big economy-wide
changes but
had to have accountability for what was
being done on an annual basis.
Those of us in the Opposition,
environmental NGOs and the public need to
see on an annual basis if the Government
is actually
passing the measures and implementing the
steps that will make those big five-year
economy-wide changes possible.
We had a series of climate action plans
published annually so the Government could
be
to account.
That is the fundamental problem with the
Government's failure to publish the
climate action plan for this year: it
cannot be held to account.
The Minister of State can give his answers
with these great five-year plans for the
future but what confidence do we have that
they will be achieved when we
know what is to be done
the plan would be published by the end of
quarter 3.
I heard the Minister refer to the plan for
2026 being published by the end of October
as well as the plan for 2027.
It would be very welcome if
confirm that.
It is better late than never that
getting its act together.
This is about transforming our theoretical
targets into practical measures for
Departments and Ministers.
We cannot hold those Ministers to account
unless we know what they are actually
trying to do.
meaningfully inform the next plan.
Publication of the plan is expected later
this year.
This plan will be more focussed and will
identify strategic climate priorities that
will shape our approach to closing the gap
to 2030 and include a range of new actions
to support mitigation in all key sectors.
In the meantime, the roll-out of
retrofitting measures, renewable energy
deployment and more affordable electric
vehicles continues at increasing pace.
The climate action plans for 2024 and
2025, which build on the series of
preceding plans, remain in place and
provide a strong framework for delivery of
climate action to 2030.
Many of their commitments are multi-annual
in nature and we will continue to focus on
accelerating their delivery.
as they reach adulthood, adults living
with ageing parents who have no idea what
will happen when they can no longer care
for them, older adults with no consistent
care pathway, and people being placed far
from their families because services have
not been planned locally.
Behind those figures are people living
with immense stress, uncertainty and
exhaustion.
The HSE has commissioned this work to
establish the scale of current and future
need.
The draft material clearly confirms that
demand is outstripping capacity
that planning, funding, capital and
investment are not aligned with long-term
needs.
If that is the HSE's own analysis, why on
earth would the response be not to publish
The information that I have is that the
HSE commissioned the report to conduct the
national disability service needs analysis
in the spring of this year.
The HSE stated that the report was
intended as a baseline planning exercise
rather than a definitive assessment of
future disability services requirements.
It was designed to identify trends,
pressures and areas requiring further
examination rather than to provide a
conclusive statement of need.
The work examined demand, capacity,
workforce requirements, service pathways
and regional variation with the intention
of informing future internal planning,
internal policy development and investment
decisions.
The Deputy is right that it is up to the
HSE
to publish the report and the information
I have is that it has decided not to
due to recognition of the limitations in
the underlying data and the significant
The findings of the needs analysis will
continue to be used internally to inform
strategic thinking and contribute to
ongoing planning work.
However, it is the body of work that my
Department is doing that is giving us a
more holistic view, a better landscape to
operate in and more information.
the Before We Die group, which the Deputy
referred to, for its involvement as a
stakeholder.
The information the HSE has given me is
that it received a slide deck of how its
contributions were evidenced in the needs
analysis.
thank the Minister of State.
I find this rationale extraordinary.
For years, disabled people and their
families have told us that services have
developed reactively, after people reach
crisis points, if they are developed at
all.
The HSE has now commissioned what sounds
like a substantial analysis drawing
together population data, waiting lists,
workforce information and the experiences
of families, providers and disabled
people.
Before We Die participated in that
research and is now being denied access to
it.
The response, as I mentioned, from the HSE
was that it is
not being published but it is not being
withheld.
That sounds like a phrase straight out of
Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four.
It is completely contradictory.
The context here is one of abject
political failure, chronic neglect of
services and immense suffering as a
result, documented over and over again
across the disability sector.
We need the figures to set that out
systematically and begin addressing it.
If the report exposes serious gaps,
publish it.
If the data have limitations, publish
these too.
Do not commission a major analysis of what
disabled people need and then bury the
findings.
in the HSE decided not to publish it?
Will the Minister of State intervene in
that decision?
The HSE has decided not to
This is its report and
not for me to publish it.
I will provide the Deputy's feedback to
and I ask that
do the same.
It is important to note that the HSE
report was baseline
to help inform current need and capital
planning.
What my the Minister,
Foley, I and the team
are doing is working to provide a
disability capacity review to 2040 that
will look further to the future and will
have wider scope.
That is the report that is most relevant
here.
It is
important that we publish
afterwards and that we work hard to ensure
it gives a holistic and accurate view
of the current landscape and future needs.
That is why we are focusing on that
report.
An awful lot of work has gone into it.
I have mentioned the national disability
support system,
the
HSE day services and the census.
Many data points
going into this.
That report will give us the information
that we need to be able to plan better.
That is the report that
focused on.
I send my best wishes to Deputy Michael
Healy-Rae and his family.
I ask the Minister for an update on the
eight locations that will
be chosen for the first time for State-led
childcare facilities.
Deputy
in sending best wishes to my constituency
colleague, Deputy Michael Healy-Rae.
We are mindful of what
had to endure and we wish him the
speediest of recoveries.
I am also mindful of his family.
This is a traumatic time for them too.
I know the whole House sends our best
wishes.
the
question, substantial progress has been
made in the State-led early learning and
childcare capital programme, which was
launched at the end of January.
The full business cases are being
developed for a number of projects in
preparation for final approval, with some
of these close to completion now.
Projects are developed into full business
cases following the approval of a
preliminary business case in line with the
framework set out in the infrastructure
guidelines.
The nature and the development of the work
required to prepare the full business case
varies by project.
They are all different and individual.
It can include things like independent
property valuation, building surveying,
due diligence checks on the property,
conveyancing, procurement and appointment
of technical advisers, detailed design
work and associated cost planning and
operator selection.
This is all required to be underpinned by
appropriate legal and contractual
arrangements.
In some instances, properties are at the
point of being sale agreed.
Operator selection has been undertaken in
some projects and will proceed shortly in
the case of others.
A cost harmonisation exercise is being
undertaken across the programme to ensure
consistency in the reporting of capital
costs and inform investment decisions,
particularly from a cost transparency
perspective.
This is due to be completed in the coming
weeks.
The projects currently being developed at
full business case stage are spread across
the country and, combined, would deliver
more than 700 new places.
I intend to make an announcement in the
coming weeks regarding these specific
projects following the agreement of sale
prices.
In parallel, a further tranche of projects
has been prepared as preliminary business
cases to bring forward to the steering
group meeting later this month and I hope
further projects will be approved in
principle after that.
for the update.
It is important that we see that
substantial progress as we approach
October and come almost
the end of the year.
There are many eyes on where the
eight locations will be.
I appreciate I sound like a broken record
in County Roscommon.
The feasibility study about the need
in Boyle in north Roscommon is
20 childcare places per 1,043 households.
I have lost count of how many times I have
put that on the Dáil record, but the
Minister will be aware, or her Department
will be aware, of a former childcare
building that was available in the town
and was made known to the county childcare
committee and her Department,
the forward planning unit of which is
leading on this.
I want to make that case once again.
I appreciate and welcome that a decision
will be made in the coming weeks.
Deputy is right.
I appreciate that there are many eyes on
this and there is great interest in this
initiative, it being the first time that
the State is actually stepping in this
area with the State-led early learning and
childcare initiative.
I intend to
make the announcement in the coming weeks.
I am conscious of the case the Deputy
makes about her own area.
has made it eloquently and consistently.
councillors.
I am conscious of Deputy Kerrane's and
Deputy Martin Daly's interest
in this area.
We are continuing to take applications.
This is a long-term commitment by
Government.
It is time-consuming.
There is the initial business case, then
the full business case and then
commercial negotiations, which are
sensitive.
We are pleased with the progress that has
been made and look forward to the coming
weeks.
Minister
many times the matter of looking at other
ways that we can quickly build capacity.
The State-led approach is one for sure,
but
also the building blocks programme.
I again ask that consideration be given to
allowing building blocks capital to be
used to buy existing buildings.
In many towns, particularly in rural areas
like my own, across Roscommon and Galway,
there are buildings.
It is the quickest way to build
capacity in the early years sector.
point that is important to make is
we can forget about capacity if we
have the workforce.
Far too many early years educators
being lost.
They are leaving the sector.
Pay is a major issue that needs to be
resolved.
We will not have State-led services and
growing capacity to meet demand or come
anywhere close to meeting demand if we do
not respect and
the workforce.
That means paying them adequately and what
they deserve and respecting the
profession.
That needs to be looked at in this Dáil
term.
I agree with the Deputy on looking at
every possible mechanism that we have to
extend capacity.
The building blocks
is one.
In terms of it being State-led, the State
is stepping in, particularly
with the purchase of buildings.
There is also the building blocks scheme
for extensions.
We are looking at a suite of measures that
will, in the quickest timeframe possible,
deliver availability or additional
availability by supporting providers to do
that or through the State stepping in.
I agree with the
importance of the workforce.
There is no point in having buildings if
we
have the workforce.
We have a valuable and important workforce
currently working in the system and we
want more staff in the system.
The Deputy will be aware
over two years the Government has invested
over €90 million arising from an
employment regulation order.
The Deputy knows my views on wanting that
to be expedited and put in place as
quickly as possible.
the
Deputy and appreciate the question.
As Minister for Children, Disability and
Equality, I am always conscious of the
potential impacts of the work of the
Department and others on the rights of
children, women and girls.
Indeed, my work has a very strong focus on
improving conditions for women and
children across this country.
Equally, the Department of public
expenditure and reform leads on the
equality budgeting programme, which seeks
to identify the impacts of policies and
expenditure across a broad range of
equality grounds.
The European Institute for Gender
Equality,
undertakes an assessment of the impact of
actions by governments on gender equality.
It has found the Government's
on equality for women and
girls to have positive impacts and placed
Ireland sixth in the EU on its gender
equality index for 2025, up from ninth in
the EU in 2024.
Across government, there are established
mechanisms in place when formulating new
policies, including public consultation,
reviewing
appropriate, and stakeholder engagement.
As Minister,
I inform
colleagues
of proposals and, whenever appropriate,
seek their agreement.
Government approval is required for
significant new or revised policies or
strategies which must indicate any impacts
on equality.
Government approval is also required at
several points before the publication of
legislation.
As the Deputy is aware, the general
scheme, or draft heads, of a Bill
undergoes scrutiny by an Oireachtas
committee before the text of the Bill is
finalised.
The relevant Oireachtas committee will
usually invite stakeholders to participate
in
process.
A Bill must then pass through five Stages
in both the Dáil and Seanad before it can
be enacted.
In order to ensure a more inclusive and
fair society, policymakers need
to data related to equality.
Robust and comprehensive evidence allows
Government to design and evaluate policies
and services more effectively.
Disaggregated data, or data broken down by
characteristics such as age or gender,
That is why we published the National
Equality Data Strategy 2026-2031 earlier
this year.
The strategy provides a framework to
support the collection and use of equality
thank the Minister for her reply but, with
respect, it did not
the question I asked.
I did not ask whether she is committed to
equality.
I asked for the mechanisms.
When a policy or recommendation is made by
the Department in the name of equality,
what is the actual process for checking
whether it takes
the rights away from somebody else?
In my question, I named
women, children and girls.
I do not have to look very far for an
example of that.
We can go back before the summer recess.
I trust the Minister is rested and had
time to enjoy the summer.
In that time, I hope she finally took the
opportunity to read the book What's
the T?, which was recommended for
15-year-old girls by a State-funded body's
Pride reading list.
Last year, the Minister told the public
that
not familiar with it, yet
former
Minister, Charlie Flanagan, said he had
raised the issue with her and asked her to
read it back in 2023.
Her own office was emailed excerpts of the
book in March of this year.
The point is
if a sexually explicit book can be
recommended to children in the name of
inclusion and nobody in the Department can
tell me who checked whether it was safe
for those children,
the mechanism I am asking about does not
exist.
If it did, it would be in the Oireachtas
Library.
Does the assessment exist?
"Yes" or "No".
If so, could I have an example of that
assessment?
To reiterate, in terms of the book the
Deputy referenced, the Department has no
role in the oversight or recommendation of
any of the books referenced.
There is no role for the Department to do
that.
specific question on what exactly happens
regarding assessments that are made
of impacts on
children, women and girls from an equality
point of view, I have made very clear to
him that when any Department is bringing
forward any kind of policy or
strategy, there must be a robust
interrogation of it.
If anything new is being introduced, it
goes before a committee.
There is an interrogation at committee
level.
As I referenced, any policy introduced
is
analysed by EIGE, which placed Ireland
sixth in terms of equality for women
and girls
in 2025, up from ninth.
I also told the Deputy that the Department
of public expenditure leads an equality
rights budgeting programme.
That also seeks to analyse the impacts of
policies and expenditure across a broad
range of equality grounds.
I have been very clear on the mechanisms
that are
Minister did not answer my question on
whether she read the book or not, but she
made the statement,
that her Department has nothing to do with
it.
This may come as a surprise to her, but
the Minister for children and equality.
These are recommended books describing
sexual acts to 15-year-old children.
If the buck does not stop with her, as the
Minister, where does it stop?
Where is the mechanism that protects those
children?
That is what I am asking about today.
very disappointing.
Will she come clean to the House and tell
us whether she has read the book or the
excerpts?
Will she tell us who was telling the truth
and who
telling the truth?
Was it her or the former Minister, Charlie
Flanagan?
What is the story?
If the buck does not stop with her, who
does it stop with?
This is about the protection of children.
When explicit books
being recommended to children and
on a reading list for children, I would
think the Minister for children is surely
responsible.
To be very clear, the Department of
Children, Disability and Equality has no
role in the publication of books.
The Department
neither publishes the books,
That has nothing to do with the
Department.
to an account given by a former Deputy.
I have said
I do not share that account.
I have a different remembrance of the
engagement I had with the
Deputy, and it is completely at odds with
what he has suggested.
Notwithstanding that, Deputy O'Flynn asked
what mechanisms we employ in terms of
equality and ensuring that there are not
any disproportionate impacts.
That is specifically what is written in
question.
He asked what mechanisms are in place that
might
protect against unintended or
disproportionate impacts on the rights of
other groups, particularly children, women
and girls.
I have clearly outlined to the Deputy that
there are a number of mechanisms in place,
including in the Department of public
expenditure from
a budgetary point of view, the analysis
done by the European Institute for Gender
whatever policies or strategies
The Government's youth justice strategy
identifies family support, early
intervention and community-based diversion
programmes as key components in preventing
offending and promoting desistance.
Enhanced family engagement through Garda
youth diversion projects, Tusla services
and reintegration planning is regarded as
an essential element of effective youth
justice practice in Ireland.
important to note that Tusla's remit is
primarily focused on child protection
rather than on the prevention of crime.
That is important.
The prevention of crime is a matter for
the Department of justice while child
protection is a matter for Tusla.
Tusla works hand in hand with An Garda
Síochána as both State organisations work
together to help children and families who
need their combined assistance.
Officials from the Department are in
regular contact with officials in the
Department of justice in particular by way
of engagement through the youth justice
oversight and youth justice governance and
strategy groups.
These help to implement the youth justice
strategy 2021-2027, which is led by the
Minister for Justice, Home Affairs and
Migration.
Under this strategy the Government
committed to strengthening family support
interventions, including through the
Department of
youth diversion projects.
At the core of the Children Act 2001 is
the premise of detention as a last resort.
This is a critical factor to understand in
the youth justice system.
The Garda national youth diversion
bureau's role is to keep young people who
offend out of the formal criminal justice
system where appropriate and reduce the
risk of reoffending.
Although family support is a central
pillar of Irish
justice policy, I am advised by my
the Minister for Justice, Home Affairs and
Migration, that there remains a need for
more robust Irish outcome data
specifically measuring the extent to which
family support interventions reduce
reoffending among young people.
Current policy is informed largely by
international evidence and by broader
assessments of youth diversion and early
intervention
It is important to recognise that the
overwhelming majority of children in the
care system will never come into contact
with An Garda Síochána, let alone be in
conflict with the law.
It is important to say that.
The vast majority of children in care
never, ever come to the attention of An
Garda Síochána and it would be remiss of
us to suggest otherwise.
Of course, we all want to see the optimal
result.
We
want
any children to be involved in antisocial
and disruptive behaviour but unfortunately
there are.
The Minister gave a nice flowery answer
there that she is responsible for the
welfare of children
Does the Minister
have concern about the increasing number
of young people engaging in persistent
antisocial and offending behaviour?
What does she intend to do about the
situation and the cause of that trend?
Is she satisfied that Tusla, schools,
youth services and other State agencies
have the resources and supports necessary
to intervene effectively
with
children?
We also know
a lot of children in the
here is not really helpful.
We need to get to the bottom of this.
It is a growing trend and
worrying.
While the vast majority
and
delighted about that; it is great – we
need to have accountability.
I absolutely appreciate the Deputy’s
concern.
I think we all share the concern.
However, I must also speak to the fact and
the fact is the vast majority of children
Síochána.
In fact, I would say
thrive
with positive intervention and it is not
appropriate to suggest otherwise.
There is a close working relationship
between
the Department of justice and my
Department looking at it from a child
welfare point of view and with the
Department of justice looking at
from a crime prevention point of view.
There are more than 5,000 children in the
care of the State.
A very small number come from particularly
complex
and challenged backgrounds and it is for
that reason they are in the care of the
State but
a very small percentage.
In that respect, I want to acknowledge the
work that is done by Tusla in terms of
family support.
I can list some of the family supports
that are there.
For example, there are parenting supports,
overseen by Tusla and its partner
community and voluntary organisations.
These include parenting supports to help
parents feel confident and capable in
their parenting role, targeted outreach
programmes designed to reach specific
groups of families who may be at risk of
social exclusion-----
Minister about the vast majority,
thankfully, but it is the minority who are
involved in this behaviour.
It is also a sad minority who have gone
missing in State care under the watch of
Tusla.
A previous Minister said he
lose a wink of sleep.
Pat Rabbitte is a former chairman of the
board of Tusla.
I think Tusla is wholly unfit for purpose.
Goodness, accountability is not there.
Children can go missing.
We saw from the UCD report some time ago
how children were being trafficked in
hotels in Cork when they were under State
care.
This is a shocking vista.
You cannot just wish it away by saying the
vast majority of children are not involved
in antisocial behaviour.
Thankfully, they are not.
We all have responsibilities, including
parents, to ensure that.
However, the ones who fall through the
cracks and who do end up in State care
deserve to be minded, nurtured,
rehabilitated and
taken care of and, above all, the State
should know where they are.
If
not with their family and are in State
care,
are being trafficked or involved in other
horrible activities like that.
It is a shocking situation.
To reiterate, we are all concerned with
any young people who find themselves in
difficult situations.
I am mindful there is a percentage of
children, and not just children in State
care but children who are not in State
care, who find themselves involved with An
Garda Síochána or
find themselves involved with crime or
whatever.
That is not just exclusive to the
children-----
not exclusive to the very small minority
who are in State care who find themselves
in
similar circumstances.
Other children outside State care find
themselves in similar situations.
For that reason, there are significant
supports being made available from a
family point of view to support families
and young people so that they can readjust
their lives, whether
counselling and therapeutic supports, a
strengthening of the family resource
centres - the Deputy will be aware that
service has increased by 15 in the past
year and a half to 136 family resource
centres - services provided by the 12 area
based childhood programmes, ABC
programmes, which see parents, as the
first and most important carers and
educators in their children's lives, can
be supported.
There are also 121 Tusla child and family
support networks and 27 children and young
people’s service committees.
There are a number of support agencies
working to ensure that children get the
best possible opportunities and supports
in life.
the Minister make a statement on the
amount of money spent on litigating
in the necessary time since 2020?
There has been significant increase in
demand for assessment of need,
in recent years, reflecting both the
increase in population and the number of
families exploring all options to access
services for their child.
Unfortunately, demand has outpaced the
capacity of the system to respond,
resulting in long waiting lists for
children to receive their assessment of
need.
The Disability Act sets out grounds under
which applicants may make a complaint
regarding assessment of need, including
completion within statutory timeframes.
Over the past years, there has been an
increasing amount of litigation seeking
enforcement orders under the Act.
important to note that if AONs are not
provided within the statutory timeframe
applicants can use the statutory
complaints and redress system.
Therefore, they apply to the Circuit Court
for an enforcement order as opposed to the
High Court judicial review process.
The total legal spend for the period
2020 to 2025 is
€498,072.
These are the HSE's own fees and do not
include the legal spend of the parties who
bring claims against the HSE, which have
been paid by the HSE.
That is because these are discharged by
the State Claims Agency.
Inability to meet the rising demand for
AON is resulting in significant financial
cost to the State but, more importantly,
is causing delay and distress to children
and families who should have access to
supports as early as possible.
It is very clear that change is needed.
There has been progress over the past two
years with a
increase in the number of completed
applications.
Over 5,900 assessments of
were completed last year, which is a 43%
increase compared to the
year, and 3,043 assessment reports have
been completed in the
first six months of this year.
This improvement must continue and it must
continue at pace.
the AON process and reduce waiting times.
Last year, nationally, the State spent
€10.5
million defending approximately 1,000
cases of
assessment of
that were overdue.
This Government is
spending more money fighting families in
the courts than providing assessments of
for children who desperately need them.
Without the assessments of
those children cannot get the supports
they need in the services.
They also cannot get the supports they
need and the services they need when they
go to school.
This Government's decision is to fight it.
To give
another figure,
only 7% of assessments of need in Cork
were completed on time.
These children have rights, and this
Government just does not seem to give a
damn.
These figures speak for themselves.
We absolutely do care.
That is why this week, at Cabinet, the
Minister, Norma Foley, and I brought
forward legislation in this regard.
To be clear, the HSE has not contested
applications to the Circuit Court.
The figure that was provided to me today
in response to
question is
the HSE's own legal fees, as I have said.
They do not include the legal spend of
parties who bring claims against the HSE
that have been paid to the HSE.
I do not have the figure from the State
Claims Agency but I can absolutely request
that for
To be clear, significant legislative and
operational work is under way to improve
the AON process and reduce the waiting
times.
This includes continuation of the targeted
wait list initiative, improved training
and guidelines for assessment officers and
targeted amendment of the disability Bill,
which was brought to Cabinet this week, to
improve the efficiency and effectiveness
I agree
it is unacceptable how many children are
waiting on these assessments.
That is why we are bringing in these
reforms - to help change that situation
for people.
Minister of State says the HSE is not
contesting these cases, but
1,000 families had to bring cases against
the State
last year, and the State spent €10.5
million then.
What was it spending the money on?
Why was that €10.5 million not put into
assessments of need?
To give
from Cork, there are supposed to be 14.5
assessment of need posts in Cork; there
are only eight.
In August, 2,000 assessments of
were overdue.
The average waiting time is 27 months.
It is supposed to be six months, but
children are waiting over two years.
No disrespect to
and I do not doubt her sincerity, but I
come in here every year raising
assessments of need and children who need
supports and need this done, and
every year I fear what the Government will
do.
These figures speak for themselves.
Children are waiting
for vital assessments.
This Government has failed the children of
Ireland.
absolutely, and it is not good enough.
What has got us here is the increase in
demand.
That is due partly to changing
demographics, and
a good thing,
to more awareness within families and
among parents exercising their right.
Parents - I am sure
the same - do not want to know the why;
they want to know what we are doing.
The only way to fix this is to change
things, and that means reform.
We are bringing in legislative reform,
policy reform and budgetary reform.
From a legislative perspective, the
Minister, Norma Foley, and I brought
this week a Bill
will be debated in this House next week.
It is about making the approach more
efficient, more effective and more
standardised.
From a policy perspective, the HSE is
introducing a single point of access and
the new autism protocol and pathways
initiative.
From a budgetary reform perspective, as
well as building capacity within the
system, we are investing.
This year alone we invested €20 million in
the wait list initiative.
To be frank and honest about this,
however, it will take time.
These changes will make things better for
families and children in this situation
but it
happen overnight.
We need to invest in these reforms if we
are to change things, and
something
Minister and I are determined to do - to
change things for these families.
thank the Deputy for the question
on this important matter.
Since core funding was introduced in 2022,
it has been incrementally increased year
on year through funding secured in the
annual budget cycle.
When first introduced in 2022, core
funding had an annual allocation of €259
million, of which €210.8 million was
entirely new funding for
the sector.
is worth over €482 million.
That is an increase of over 86% in core
funding
over four years, bringing the total to
€1.7 billion since the scheme began -
an investment by the State
This unprecedented increase in year 5 of
the scheme includes €21 million in funding
dedicated to support partner services in
adhering to the core funding fee
management conditions from September 2026.
The annual budgetary increases to core
funding have ensured
the scheme remains responsive, balancing
the needs of providers while seeking to
meet a range of other objectives.
Core funding has been developed using the
various components associated with the
administrative staff
time, and non-staff overhead costs.
The base rate calculation also accounts
for the increases to the cost of
delivering services encountered by
providers.
These components have been factored into
the calculation of the budget for core
funding since the scheme began in
The core funding base rate has increased
year on year since the inception of core
funding, with a 20% increase in hourly
rates between years 1 and 5 of the scheme.
Accordingly, this has ensured that the
scheme has kept pace with inflation and,
thus, has reflected the dynamic costs
profile inherent to the sector over that
period.
In particular, the base rate was enhanced
this month to support all providers to
keep their fees more affordable for
families, through the core funding fee
freeze and maximum fee caps, in the face
of rising cost pressures.
The Department will explore further
developments to the allocation model as
part of the 2027 budgetary process.
the current fee arrangements have created
unintended inequality between service
providers.
Service providers that have been involved
in the core funding programme since its
introduction have had their fees tied to a
rate being charged in September 2021,
while new service providers are able to
establish their fees based on current
operating conditions, subject to
applicable fee caps, which puts
established childcare providers at a
disadvantage.
I want to be clear that I am absolutely
committed to continuing to engage with the
sector and all concerned to
continue to develop the scheme in order
that it can support providers to deliver
high-quality early learning and childcare
to children that is sustainable.
I think that is the rub of
question - sustainability.
including a flat rate for sessional-only
services and a minimum core funding
allocation were introduced in year 2 of
the scheme.
These were enhanced in year 4.
The Department also ran a fee increase
assessment process during programme
3 of core funding, whereby partner
services charging fees below the county
average were eligible to apply to be
assessed for a fee increase.
I have made the decision to launch a
revised version of this process for the
upcoming programme year, the
sustainability review process.
exactly what the Deputy has asked, in
terms of those who are having challenges
around sustainability.
I have made the decision to launch that
sustainability review process.
The eligibility criteria for the review
process have been refined to target
Without such a review, there is a risk
that these providers will be unable to
continue operating, which would reduce the
number of places for children available in
the sector.
That review is exactly as
asked,
to support providers.
happy to see this is progressing.
Several providers involved in core funding
since 2021 have contacted me and they have
experienced
considerable increase in their overheads.
I would also like to point out the fee
payment thresholds table.
Can I ask that County Wicklow be aligned
with Dublin?
At the moment it is in
mid-east bracket, and strangely for some
of the mid-east brackets the upper limit
on the threshold is lower than
some of the midlands.
There seems to be an anomaly there.
Another anomaly, which is slightly
related, is
if a child moves from senior infants into
first class they end up using a facility
That parent contacted me to say they are
being charged €93 extra per month.
That is because the childcare provider no
longer receives the subsidy for
that one hour per day.
Yet the parent, who is now putting their
child in for one hour less per day, ends
up being charged the higher fee.
These kinds of anomalies need to be looked
at.
I reiterate that there is unprecedented
investment by the State in
this sector.
I think €1.7 billion speaks to the
determination of the State to support
early learning and childcare provision.
That is in terms of supporting providers,
the workforce and
parents.
We are moving into budget 2027 where there
are negotiations, which I imagine will be
ongoing to the eleventh hour, to see how
we can advance in each of those areas.
in terms of this sector to speak even at
this point
in terms of €1.7 billion.
On the issues the Deputy raised around
sustainability, that sustainability review
is now open to providers to engage.
In terms of the specific issues he raised,
there are differences between
early learning and childcare provision and
school age childcare provision.
Notwithstanding that, the State is
committed to continue investing in the
early learning and childcare sector.
I return to
assessment of need, specifically in my
constituency, to ask for details of the
number of children currently on the
waiting list for an assessment of
and the numbers waiting
more than three, six and 12 months.
The Department and the HSE are working
intensively to address delays in the
to children and their families.
There has been significant increase in
demand for assessment of
in recent years.
Applications have risen from 4,700 in 2020
to over 13,000
in 2025.
That reflects both the increase in
population and the number of families
Unfortunately, demand has outpaced the
capacity of our system to respond.
While the HSE does not provide assessment
of need data by county, data is provided
by regional health area and local health
office, so I am able to give the
specifics for
Monaghan.
The most recent data for Cavan-Monaghan
LHO is
for
applications were overdue for completion
at the end of June.
Of these, 543 were overdue for more than
three months.
Up to June of this year, 123 assessment of
need applications were received in
Monaghan for 2026.
clear that change is needed, not just in
Cavan-Monaghan but across the country.
There has been progress over the past two
years with a notable increase in the
number of
Over 5,900 AON reports were completed in
2025, a 43%
increase compared with the year previous.
Some 3,043
assessment reports were completed in the
first six months of 2026.
This improvement must continue.
Significant legislative and operational
work continues to improve the AON process
and over time
This includes continuation of the targeted
waitlist initiative,
improved training and guidelines for
assessment officers and the targeted
amendment of the Disability (Amendment)
Bill, which was brought to Cabinet this
week, to improve the efficiency and
effectiveness of the AON process.
I hope the Minister of State's voice gets
better soon.
I know it is difficult when one is in this
position with a sore
throat.
However, I have to say that regardless of
the tone
able to deliver it, her answer is
incredibly worrying on a number of fronts.
First of all, there is now a backtracking.
I have a parliamentary question response
from the HSE in January where I was given
county-specific data.
Now,
telling me the HSE does not provide that.
Again, there are difficulties in the
response with the fact that this
Government is breaking the law by failing
to provide children with assessments of
need they are legally entitled to, within
the timeframe they are legally entitled
to.
Yet, the information the Minister of State
is providing in response to that is
becoming more limited and restricted.
In the first instance, I ask her to get a
handle on that.
Second, the numbers she has cited from
January
to now - the most recent figures - suggest
to me that there is an increase from
509 children who are waiting for a stage 2
assessment, to over 600.
Is that true?
Are there more children currently waiting
more than a year for assessment of
in Cavan and Monaghan than was the case at
the beginning of this year.
The information I
provided the Deputy is the Cavan and
Monaghan figures combined.
It shows that 634 applications were
overdue for completion at the end
That is the figure up to the end of June.
Of these, 543 were overdue for more than
three months.
That is the data the HSE has provided to
me.
Applications received in
and quarter 2 this year for Cavan and
Monaghan combined are 123.
Those 634 applications are the data up to
the end of June.
That includes the 123 applications
received this year
but if we are talking about those overdue
for completion at the end of June,
634.
That is the information.
It is provided by regional health area and
local health office area.
That is the Cavan-Monaghan combined
figure.
To be clear,
this is an important point.
I asked, through
parliamentary question, as is my
constitutional right, for the assessment
of need number in Cavan and Monaghan, by
county.
The Minister of State is telling me that
the HSE does not provide that.
I am telling her it did provide it, as
recently as January.
I am aware of
because I have a parliamentary question
response.
That is telling.
If it is not dealing with the Minister of
State and sending her into this Chamber
with a shortfall in the information she
has been asked
for, how can she trust it in respect of
what I contend is the much more serious
matter that
in Cavan and Monaghan,
634 children being failed?
They are not only being failed in a moral
sense but are being absolutely failed in a
legal sense.
The Government is breaking the law in
respect of these children, and despite the
assurances the Minister of State and
others have provided to us, this has
real-life implications.
Many of these 634 children are being
denied access to other services because
their assessment of need has not been
carried out.
This Government needs to get a grip on it.
I have been here since 2020.
I have been listening to the same rhetoric
from Ministers about all the measures that
are going to be taken to improve matters
but
going to take a little bit of time.
time passes, the situation gets worse.
asking the Minister
With all due respect to my predecessors
and the Minister's, while
may have heard what plans were coming down
the tracks, what he is hearing from us is
what plans are happening, what changes are
happening and what reforms we are
delivering.
This week the Minister,
Foley, and I brought to Cabinet
legislation that will make it more
efficient, more effective and will provide
standardised guidelines for the entire
assessment of
process.
That will be in this House for debate next
week.
From a policy perspective, the HSE has
developed, launched and is about to
implement two very significant changes.
One is the single point of access, which
means there will be no wrong door for any
child.
I hear this all the time from parents.
Someone is on a waiting list for primary
care or a CDNT, gets to the top of the
list and is told
the wrong list.
That will be no more.
That is a significant change for families.
Also, the autism protocol and pathways
initiative is being launched.
From a budgetary perspective, we are
building capacity within our teams.
The workforce in disability has increased
by 22% in five years and we are investing
in the wait list initiative to reduce the
number of children in Cavan-Monaghan and
across the country who are waiting on an
assessment of need.
These are real changes that will deliver
for children and families.
I appreciate it will not happen overnight
but these
are needed to change the situation for
those children and their
There have been significant developments
in entitlements for parents of working
families in recent years.
The combined durations of maternity,
paternity and parent's leave and benefit
now equate to 46 weeks
paid leave for a two-parent family,
supplemented by an entitlement to 16 weeks
of unpaid maternity leave and 26 weeks of
unpaid parental leave per parent.
Under the Parent’s Leave and Benefit Act
2019, working parents are entitled to nine
weeks of paid parent's leave,
to be taken
by the EU work-life balance directive.
The entitlement is for each parent in
their own right.
The leave is non-transferable to ensure
that fathers are also supported in their
caring roles and to promote women’s equal
labour market participation.
The principle of non-transferability is
also required by the EU work-life balance
directive.
Under the Parental Leave (Amendment) Act
2019, an employee who is a relevant parent
in respect of a child under the age of 12
is entitled to 26 weeks of unpaid parental
leave for each child.
Where a child has a disability or
long-term illness, the entitlement can
continue until the child is 16 years of
age.
The Work Life Balance and Miscellaneous
Provisions Act 2023 complements existing
family leave entitlements and introduces
additional flexibility for working parents
and carers.
Under this legislation, parents and carers
have a right to request flexible working
arrangements in line with Article 9 of
Directive 2019/1158.
An entitlement to five days of leave
annually for medical care purposes was
also introduced under this Act.
A key priority in First 5, the
whole-of-government strategy for babies,
young children and their families, is to
support parents to look after their babies
at home for the first year of their lives,
given the benefits of parental care in
that first year for children’s outcomes.
Family leave provisions are kept under
review to ensure they respond to the needs
Paternity leave is a fairly recent policy,
introduced in 2016.
In 2020, the uptake was 48.6%; in 2023,
that increased to 54%.
Of those who avail
paternity leave,
go on to parent's leave.
Ireland offers €299 per week.
For working families, this represents a
72% drop; that is the figure we have
been given,
on quarter 1 average incomes.
Other EU countries offer much more to
parents.
I
ask whether the Government is considering
extending parent's leave.
When will parents in this country see
an extension?
Programme for Government - Securing
Ireland's Future commits to examining the
extension of parent's leave and benefit
and additional flexibilities.
The first action plan under the new
national strategy for women and girls,
published in August, includes measures to
support working families in balancing work
and family responsibilities, including
extending parent's leave.
The Department is taking forward work to
implement that measure and to look
and examine it.
The programme for Government also commits
to introducing pay-related parent's
benefit
and exploring other payments where a
similar model could be applied.
The Department of Social Protection will
draw on the learnings from that scheme to
inform the development of options for
parent's benefit and other family leave
schemes.
There is a programme for Government
commitment to examining the extension of
parent's leave and benefit and additional
flexibilities.
Work on that is under way.
Work
the Department of Social Protection on
pay-related
parent's benefit.
Minister
fill us in on
This is a huge issue, as she and everyone
in this House knows, for many parents.
Nine weeks' parent's leave is simply not
good enough for those who have to look
after a newborn, particularly in cases
where a C-section was involved, which
parents have contacted me about.
Given the amount of work and care needed
to ensure the health of the mother and
child,
nine weeks does not help the situation.
What stage is the work in the Department
at?
Will the
Minister look
to a public consultation on this?
I am sure she will get plenty of feedback
from parents because that is what we have
received in our office in the weeks and
months since we started raising this
issue.
Will the Minister confirm her and the
Government's thinking on increasing
paternity leave to replicate
other EU countries, which offer a far
better scheme than is available in
Ireland?
Deputy has said about the nine weeks, it
is important to reiterate that up to 46
weeks
of paid leave is available to two-parent
families.
The programme for Government contains a
commitment to examining the extension of
parent's leave
and benefit and other flexibilities, as
does the national strategy for women and
girls.
My Department is in the very early stages
of looking at that.
There will be
engagement and consultation on that.
The pay-related model is also important.
That is to be undertaken by the Department
of Social Protection.
Between the programme for Government
commitment and the national strategy,
there is a commitment for this to be
looked at.
I thank the
Deputy.
I announced €135 million in capital
investment in buildings for high-quality,
accessible State-led early learning and
childcare up to 2030.
This is a ground-breaking initiative for
Government and it began this year.
Capital funding will be used to acquire
and fit out
buildings, depending on requirements.
The State-led initiative will provide
thousands of places up to 2030, with the
funding provided through the national
development plan.
The level of investment will ramp up over
the lifetime of
Government.
The programme was launched earlier this
year and has eight objectives, including
the delivery of additional supply in
suitable locations, cost-effectiveness and
timeliness, and supporting improved public
management of the sector.
A range of tools have been developed to
assess projects’ alignment with the
programme objectives, including a forward
planning model to analyse early learning
and childcare supply and demand.
The Department has received project
proposals from a number of sources since
These projects are in different stages of
development.
Some relate to existing buildings ready to
or fitted out, while others are longer
term prospects for future years.
Not all proposals align with the programme
objectives.
Some projects are proposed by an existing
early learning and childcare service
provider, while others relate to a
building or property only, where a
separate process to identify an operator
would be required.
The Department has a long list of projects
under consideration, including project
proposals received through preliminary
appraisal forms from city and county
childcare committees.
I am advised that no formal proposal has
been received from County Kildare via
a preliminary appraisal form.
The Department is aware that this
is not exhaustive
and I reiterate that the scheme remains
open.
There is an opportunity for people to make
proposals at any point and
very happy to do that.
the first point of contact is the local
city and county childcare committees.
thank the Minister for her reply.
It is disappointing to hear we have had no
proposal from County Kildare.
As
aware, I have discussed with her on
multiple occasions in the House the
deserts that exist in County Kildare,
particularly around towns such as
Kilcullen and Newbridge, where parents
come to me and say they cannot find
childcare.
The question I have as a result of the
Minister's reply is
can contact the childcare committees.
It seems to me that unless
a provider contacts the childcare
committees we will not get the facilities
we need in Kildare.
It is parents who are contacting me and it
is parents who are facing these problems.
I have previously given examples in the
House of people who have made a life in
Kilcullen having to move back to counties
such as Kilkenny because they do not have
childcare facilities in that town.
This is
happening on a weekly basis in my county.
Again, the question I ask is whether the
Department will get involved in
identifying these deserts that we and
have spoken about in the House previously
rather than relying on childcare
committees and proposals that childcare
committees might get from providers.
proposals to the city or county childcare
committees are not all from providers.
They can be from anyone.
Deputy Wall will appreciate that there has
to be some form of a process
and the first line
of the process has been identified to be
the local on-the-ground mechanism of the
county and childcare committees.
It is free to anybody to make a proposal.
In the first instance, this year we are
looking at provision of buildings and
primarily where a building might be
available.
I am aware
community groups have stepped forward, as
have individuals.
The proposals can come from anywhere and
there is an openness in the city and
county childcare committees to look at any
proposal that comes their way.
Of course we will look at other
opportunities as well.
There are opportunities through local
authorities.
We are very open to working with anybody
who has
a viable proposal.
In the first instance a preliminary
business case will be made and then a full
business case.
To assure the Deputy, the process remains
open.
If anybody wants to step forward we are
very happy for consideration to be given
be sending the Minister a number of
proposals from County Kildare because so
many families
asking me this question.
The problem I have with the Minister's
answer is that
still reliant on viable proposals.
Parents are hard-working, as we
just discussed with regard to parental
leave,
how are they to come up with premises?
I have contacted schools and local sports
clubs to try to get them involved in this
and
not forthcoming with the premises.
We still have these deserts, as I call
them, in Kildare and
again that
the Department receives these multiple
questions from parents it
looks at these deserts and works with the
parents, who are ordinary decent families
working each day but finding it more and
more difficult to get childcare places and
the time, energy or perhaps know-how to
identify places.
This is where I believe the Department and
the childcare committees come in.
I ask that when the Minister receives the
proposals from me later today she actively
looks at them and
providing childcare places in County
Kildare where they are needed.
I suggest, as
already outlined, that the first line of
contact is the local city and county
childcare committees.
That is the process.
I would be surprised at this point if
Deputy Wall has not engaged with them
because I know
very active on the ground and I imagine he
has already engaged with them.
If he has not, that is the first line of
contact.
Whatever proposal Deputy Wall has, it
should go to them first.
They are on the ground and can discuss
with him the potential possibilities or
the viability of a particular project he
might want to advance.
As it stands, this year we are looking at
buildings that might be available because
this is the quickest access.
If
opportunities present themselves we will
look at building facilities or whatever.
Let us be very clear that there is a
process
whereby a proposal, suggestion, idea or
vision
can be discussed on the ground with the
local facility, which is the
local city and county childcare committee.
I suggest that if Deputy Wall has a number
of proposals he engages with them first
and if
viable they will come to the Department
and we will do all we can to progress
In March 2025, a commitment was given that
section 39 workers would be brought into
future public sector pay agreements
automatically.
I accept that budget 2027 is not finalised
and that public sector pay
discussions have not started but I would
like confirmation from the Minister today
that the commitment given in 2025 will be
upheld for the people and organisations
behalf of the State.
The March 2025 pay funding agreement for
workers in community and voluntary health
and social care organisations, whom Deputy
Cooney has referenced, represents a
significant investment in the sector and
provides certainty for workers and their
employers on the application of future pay
adjustments in the public sector.
The agreement was negotiated between
Government Departments and unions, with
the involvement of relevant funding
agencies and employer representatives,
with, as always, the assistance of the
Workplace Relations Commission.
The agreement includes funding for a 9.25%
pay increase for workers directly employed
by these independently operated
organisations.
In funding terms, the deal amounts to an
increase of approximately €70 million per
annum for the organisations delivering
specialist disability services and
supports funded by the HSE.
Taken together with the earlier October
2023 agreement, which provides for an 8%
increase, this amounts to a 17.25%
increase in available pay funding over a
three-and-a-half year period.
The final increase provided for in the
agreement, a 2% general round increase, is
due to be applied on 1 October.
The level of funding increase for
individual service providers is assessed
and validated by the HSE with reference to
the service agreements in place.
This ensures the uplift takes account of
pay-related costs in each service
agreement.
In a landmark step by the Government the
arrangements also include
automatic linkage for these workers to
general round increases in any future
public sector pay agreement.
This treatment is an important step
forward for workers and has been a
landmark step forward by
Government and much sought after by
workers.
It is a huge assurance and reassurance to
them that there is
automatic linkage to any general round
increase, not only
in the upcoming public sector pay
agreement but public sector
agreements going forward also.
Section 39 workers have been left behind.
After the crash their pay was cut in line
with the public service but it has never
been restored in the same way.
It has taken over a decade, with
Labour Court and threatened strike action,
to begin to close the gap.
We are still not there.
Even the agreement reached in 2023 was not
fully honoured because the funding
employers, including pension and PRSI
contributions.
Small providers without reserves or
fundraising capacity could well be pushed
Funding levels for section 39
organisations must cover the full cost of
employees' salary increases as well as
their pensions and PRSI costs.
Has this been raised by the Minister and
the Department in the current budget
discussions?
I
reiterate that the agreements
reached in recent years, including the
9.25% increase and the 8% increase
in 2023, are a 17.25%
increase over a three-and-a-half year
period.
This is significant.
As always, the Government's priority is to
protect vital services for those who rely
on them while ensuring sustainable
employment for the dedicated workers who
provide quality supports and services.
The phased increases recognise that staff
should be fairly paid for the difficult
work they do.
Notably, the ability of organisations to
actively recruit and retain staff has also
improved as a result of these funding
agreements.
To
point, as part of the agreement a
comprehensive data-gathering exercise is
being conducted on pay and funding
arrangements in the sector.
This exercise is crucial in order to
create a shared understanding of the
sector.
The outcome of the exercise will inform
targeted measures on the low pay issues
that affect the long-term sustainability
of services and it is expected that this
work will be finalised shortly.
These arrangements relate to services
funded through statutory grant aid
arrangements, funding for services
commissioned through tendering
arrangements,
is not covered-----
The consequences of a failure to deliver a
fully funded package for section 39 staff
and organisations will, unfortunately,
fall on the vulnerable people who rely
on them.
These organisations operate on a tight
service level agreement with the HSE.
Pay parity for staff must be supported by
a ring-fenced, fully funded package
from Government that includes the full
cost to their employers, which is
important.
Anything less will move this crisis from
staff and organisations directly onto
families, unfortunately.
Organisations funded under section 39
already find it difficult to compete with
HSE and section 38 pay scales.
This will compound the existing
recruitment and retention difficulties
resulting in increased staffing shortages,
greater reliance on agency staff and
higher risk to service delivery.
Organisations may be unable to adequately
support their existing staff or meet the
needs of current service users and their
families.
We need to fix this issue properly, once
and for all.
reiterate that this is and has been
recognised by all concerned, including the
workers the Deputy referred to, as a
landmark step by Government
that ensures
these workers will be automatically
included for any general
round increases in any future public
sector pay agreements.
That is very significant in the first
instance.
In the second instance, regarding the
specific issues raised by the Deputy, an
exercise is currently under way, which was
agreed to at the time, to get a further,
and more
transparent insight into the issues within
the sector because there are a variety of
different issues in the sector.
That exercise is under way and nearing
completion.
It is a data-gathering exercise and the
outcome of that exercise can and will
inform targeted measures on the low pay
issues that affect the long-term
sustainability of services.
The arrangements relating to the workers
the Deputy referred to
are arrangements through statutory grant
aid arrangements.
Funding for services in those
circumstances is part
of that data-gathering exercise.
important to say as well that the
organisations funded under section 39,
while supported by the HSE, are
independent entities.
They are not public bodies and their staff
are not public servants.
The terms and conditions of employment for
staff in these organisations are
ultimately determined by the employer and
their employees, notwithstanding the body
of work that the State is doing and the
commitments that we have given regarding
the automatic linkage to public pay.
As
know, families in Ireland, especially in
rural communities, are continuing to face
childcare.
I know that she is concerned about it, as
am I, and I know we have many programme
for Government commitments, including the
creation of additional childcare places,
initiating State-led childcare, especially
in areas of unmet need, and getting to
that €200 per month.
With budget 2027 approaching, will the
Minister outline what measures she intends
to consider
supporting childcare provision in rural
Ireland?
the Deputy's sterling work in a personal
capacity as Chair of
committee, her leadership in that respect
and her personal commitment to the issues
in relation to early years in childcare.
The view shared by the committee that the
Deputy chairs excellently,
and across Government, is that we should
improve access to quality and affordable
early learning and childcare
opportunities.
Early learning and childcare capacity is
increasing.
Data from the annual early years sector
profile for 2024-25 shows that the
estimated number of enrolments increased
by approximately 25% from the 2021-22
programme year.
A 25% increase in those three years is
significant.
However, it appears, and I absolutely
accept, that demand for early learning and
childcare remains higher than available
supply in certain parts of the country,
particularly for younger children.
The Department supports the ongoing
development and resourcing of core
funding, which has given rise to
significant expansion of places since the
scheme was first introduced, and this will
continue to be the case in 2027.
Core funding, which is presently in its
fifth programme year, funds services based
on the number of places available.
This provides stability to services and
reduces the risk associated with opening a
new service or expanding an already
existing service.
Budget 27, as
aware, is currently being considered by
Government in the context of the annual
Estimates process, which officials are
actively engaging in.
I have also engaged directly with
Minister,
Jack Chambers.
The Deputy will
appreciate that it would not be
appropriate for me to comment further at
this stage other than to say openly that I
am pursuing an ambitious budget package
intended to reduce costs to parents, to
support providers in the workforce and to
increase the availability of places.
In addition to current funding to expand
capacity, the Government is also
supporting the expansion of early learning
and childcare capacity through capital
funding.
We are doing this through a number of
different mechanisms, including schemes
like building blocks and the State-led
initiative.
In terms of building blocks, capital
funding schemes have been in operation
since 2024.
The building blocks extension scheme is
currently operating and will deliver
quality, affordable, full daycare
for
under three across the country.
thank the Minister.
I welcome the increase in enrolments.
I am really thinking about my own county
of Mayo.
Even when we have increases in the
national childcare scheme, and I hear
about these great subsidies, I know many
parents in my county are not able to
access them.
The last data I got was that we only have
one registered private childminder in the
whole county.
There has been a bit of an uptake on the
pre-registration course, with the deadline
of September 2027 approaching, but after
that course there
been a
I am very concerned that right now we only
have one registered childminder.
People are
struggling to find a place with a private
childminder or within a centre,
and now we have this looming deadline
coming in September.
I am extremely concerned.
What I
want to see addressed is the potential
crisis with private childminders if they
do not start registering soon.
In relation to State-led childcare, in my
own area, because we are focusing more on
the voluntary boards of management and the
community-led element, we
have any proposals in that area yet
Just to be clear, significant work is
under way to encourage
more childminders into the registration
process.
A review is under way in terms of how that
is working and what we could do
differently in future, including what
further supports we could provide or
whatever the case might be.
I am very pleased to have brought that
review forward to give us a
clearer line of sight of what we need to
do to get more of the childminders
on board, recognising their invaluable
work
and the important contribution they make
to early learning and childcare.
Specifically, in terms of
building blocks and the scheme that is
there, a large proportion of the projects
supported through building blocks have
been in rural areas.
It is important to make that point.
The State-led process
was announced in January.
We are working at speed and I acknowledge
the work of everybody involved.
In the coming weeks,
to make announcements around the State-led
projects.
childcare will be a game-changer but we
cannot just rely on the community
voluntary boards.
In cities like Dublin and Cork, the boards
In rural Ireland, the same people who are
on their GAA board are also
on the board of the community childcare
facility, so we need to look at that.
I also really welcome that a review
ongoing in relation to how we can better
support private childminders to get
registered.
We need to reach out and allow people,
even in a confidential way, to come
forward.
Good representative organisations are
speaking for childminders but a lot of
childminders
not even registered with those
organisations.
I held a public meeting and childminders
were nearly afraid to come to it.
An anonymous survey where they can engage
in a confident way would be welcome.
If we
get
registration soon with this deadline
approaching, we could be in an even bigger
crisis by September than we are in right
now.
I reiterate that the process is an open
one.
It is open to anyone to get involved and
to engage in the process.
We would absolutely welcome
existing
childminders, including those who are
registered and those who are not
registered, all of them, coming forward to
share their thoughts and views on what
might be done to support it better going
forward.
I again reiterate that we hope in the
coming weeks to make the announcement
around eight proposals for State-led
childcare this year.
Including for rural Ireland, opportunities
remain open for any group, individual or
organisation that wants to reach out to
the city and county childcare committees
with proposals whether a proposed
building, a site,
a building that requires purchase or even
a building that simply requires
fit out.
The Department is very flexible in
offering any kind of support we can
to enhance the availability of the
provision of early years and childcare
facilities.
put the question and raise an issue with
the Minister.
I wanted to ask her about the measures she
is taking to increase residential places
for adults with intellectual disabilities
in County Meath and the number of new
residential places planned for 2026 and
2027.
Along with a number of colleagues,
including Deputy Guirke, I met
a number of residential providers,
including Clann Mór in Navan, County
Meath.
It has proposals at an advanced stage in
relation to providing additional
residential places.
It, among others, needs support to do
that.
I implore the Minister to make that happen
as quickly
When you put something at arm's length
from the political system, you need to
make sure it is operating effectively, as
it should be, while maintaining that
independence.
I
think any Minister for justice should have
a role in a protected disclosure.
No Minister for justice should be the
investigator in something that is brought
forward.
I
think anybody in this House believes
We
have an opportunity to review the
legislation.
I believe it has worked effectively.
Again, I commend
their families, have come forward to
highlight issues, not just in An Garda
Síochána but
in other workplaces.
That is the importance of the legislation.
It is not just about An Garda Síochána but
An Garda Síochána is quite literally
charged with protecting people in this
country
with the security and protection of this
State.
We need to make sure the structures within
An Garda Síochána are such that, if people
are not doing things correctly,
there are
in place.
As I have outlined, many such structures
and oversight mechanisms were introduced
when I was Minister for Justice and many
have been followed
Again, I did not ask the Minister whether
she was informed of the details of any
protected disclosure.
We know that section 41 of the Garda
Síochána Act requires that the
Commissioner inform the
Minister for justice if there are
incidents
that have the potential to undermine
public trust in the office.
Public trust has been
undermined by any number of
captured in last night's RTÉ documentary.
Those charged with looking after
whistleblowers, taking on their files and
investigating their claims had to become
whistleblowers
and were
removed from the
the information she was given was enough?
This goes to the heart of
ministerial accountability and
role of informing Parliament.
very clear that there was a gross failure
and that people were being penalised.
What exactly did Drew Harris
when he was making this change?
I know I sound like I am repeating myself
but it is important to say that the Act
very clearly states that, under the law,
it is not an option to comment on or
confirm the existence or details of any
specific protected disclosure.
What the Deputy is referencing, what was
highlighted last night
what was spoken of by individuals clearly
suggests that is what is being talked
about here.
I am not trying to be evasive.
I am trying to be very clear.
Legislation was enacted that very clearly
precludes
the office itself, I was not aware of how
the structure was changing
over.
That is not something that
brought to my attention because it is a
matter for An Garda Síochána.
The 2005 Act very clearly sets out the
roles and responsibilities of An Garda
My role as Minister for Justice at that
time was to make sure that
where we needed to.
specifically to Fiosrú, individuals made a
complaint, the complaint went to the
ombudsman that existed then and it then
went through a process of criminal
investigation that might have come to an
inconclusive answer.
then had to start at the beginning and
potentially go through a civil process.
It took a long
nobody was getting answers.
The process was protracted and was not
working effectively.
That is why Fiosrú was introduced.
to ensure we would have a quicker, more
efficient
more effective process.
That was my priority and focus as Minister
for Justice.
stress that, at all times, no matter what
was going on, I adhered to and followed
That was my responsibility as Minister.
I took it very seriously and
have always adhered to
We will look into that.
I want to be associated with the
Minister's comments about Deputy Michael
Healy-Rae.
I am thinking of him, his family
his supporters in south Kerry, many of
I know very well.
Deputy Doherty raised the question of when
the Minister first knew about the
issue.
I have the answer.
It took three attempts before the
Minister, Deputy O'Callaghan's Department
would tell me, but we
know it was August 2020.
It is shocking that it took three
attempts.
The whole country is talking about last
night.
This does not give me any pleasure.
Everyone in this House knows
been raising these issues for years.
It
give me any pleasure to stand here today
to say what I have to say.
Luke, Brian, Donal and Rose are incredible
people.
They are real
honest people.
Many of these revelations are not new, by
the way.
There is a man sitting up there
John Lee, who has written about this for
years.
So has Mick Clifford.
They deserve great credit.
There are so many layers to this programme
and so many issues that have not been
covered but
in this Chamber over the weeks, months and
years to come.
Minister,
will have to answer for how An Garda
Síochána and his Department acted.
The Minister, Deputy McEntee, will
need to outline to the House what she did.
I am not talking about the
individual protected disclosures.
I am interested in process and pathways.
Brian O'Reilly sent the Minister his
protected disclosure in September 2023 as
it impugned the
Commissioner.
That was the correct thing for him to do
because it was about the Commissioner.
The Minister sent it to the Office of the
Protected Disclosures Commissioner later
that month.
That was also the correct thing to do.
In October 2023, the OPDC sent its
statutory direction
that the Secretary General of the
Minister's Department be appointed to
investigate this.
The Secretary General made no objection to
this.
That is where it sits.
What happened next was detrimental to
Brian O'Reilly's life, his
career, his livelihood and
him, his wife, his children and his
family.
As Minister for Justice,
and redirected to An Garda Síochána,
thereby usurping the
OPDC's statutory direction.
Giving such direction is that office's
role.
We
know the legislation.
Deputy McEntee, as Minister for Justice,
was entitled to and exposing the nature of
his allegations.
In doing so, she acted without legal
authority and directly interfered with a
serious and significant protected
She did exactly what the Taoiseach spent
all day yesterday
lecturing us about, telling us that
would be completely and utterly
inappropriate.
How does the Minister explain this?
It was either done deliberately - to be
fair to her, I actually do not think it
was - or it was just incompetence or
a mistake.
Everybody in here is talking about this.
I told this Chamber
that the issue of the holsters, one
of which I am holding now, and how the
Minister handled protected disclosures
would haunt this Government, the Minister
herself and the previous Government.
Last night's programme absolutely
confirmed that to be the case.
I will start where I finished in answering
the last question.
In my role as Minister for Justice,
on any matter,
adhered to the law and the structures we
have to adhere to under
this Act and legislation.
The Deputy can look elsewhere, shake his
head at me or say that I was incompetent
or whatever it is he was trying to
suggest.
exactly what he has suggested.
I have adhered to the legislation at all
times.
ensured that
everything I did in the Department was to
ensure accountability and oversight, even
at times when that did not make me
popular, which happened quite a lot.
How did we make sure there
better structures in place?
It was by introducing new legislation,
putting
the audit committee had oversight of what
happened on protected disclosures and
introducing Fiosrú so
we
better protection for those who brought
forward protected disclosures.
We also amended the 2014 legislation
introduced
by Deputy
leader.
All of this was to make sure that, where
people brought forward protected
disclosures, procedures were adhered to
and that
were protected, encouraged to come forward
and supported, where possible.
I cannot be any clearer in saying that I
have always adhered to the rules and the
regulations as
set out to me.
I have always acted in accordance with the
law.
When it comes to protected disclosures and
matters relating to such disclosures that
are still before the courts or a tribunal
or inquiry, the Deputy will know
that this is not something that any of us
can talk about.
The Taoiseach was very clear about that
yesterday.
I have repeated that many times this
morning.
As I have already said, we have an
opportunity to review the legislation.
There is a legal requirement in the Act to
ensure that
by July of next year.
I am informed by the Department of public
expenditure and reform that this review
will start by the end of this year.
There is an onus on all stakeholders to
participate in that.
laid out the facts.
I have the documentation here in front of
me.
I am not interested in
the details of the actual disclosures, the
pathway and the process.
I know what happened here.
The Minister will have to explain it,
despite everything she has said
there, because
the way
was managed by the Minister simply was
not appropriate.
Most of all though, today, I am thinking
of the family of Colm Horkan.
I have met them several times, and I know
others here have
too.
They are broken.
They are devastated.
He should never have been wearing that
version of this holster
that night.
The State let him and his family down.
Someone has to stand up for them.
Collectively, as a Chamber -
Opposition or Government, it
really matter -
we all have to stand up for them.
Will the Government -
I mean this -
finally do the right thing and sanction an
independent investigation into
everything to do with how faulty holsters
like
this were given to our brave men and women
I know
that is what the family wants.
I know that is what they deserve.
I
too have met the family, and not just on
that occasion I mentioned.
It was the very first thing I did as
Minister.
I met them subsequently and I know how
difficult and traumatic this is for
them.
I know they never want anybody else to go
through that.
The death and the murder of any individual
is traumatic enough but for
somebody who is tasked with protecting
each and every one of us
is reprehensible.
We all agree on that.
I
think anything we can do will ever take
that away from the family.
is very clear that we have a number of
different investigations and processes
still under way.
That might not suit what people want to
say here today but that is a fact.
It is the case.
There is an obligation on each and every
one of us to make sure that any
independent investigation is adhered to.
Beyond that, and the Taoiseach asked this
question yesterday,
what do we want to do and how do we
respond.
We have an opportunity to review the
legislation to make sure it is acting in
accordance but we have to make sure any
independent process that is under way is
allowed to continue.
It might take longer
than any of us would like,
but we have an obligation to ensure any
process under way is allowed to conclude.
Every TD in this House knows Irish Water
is not fit for purpose.
Every day, an Opposition TD or a
Government TD raises an Irish Water issue
in this Chamber.
Every day, Government and Opposition TDs
are on local radio criticising Irish
Water.
It beggars belief that despite water
shortages, hosepipe bans and
future and continued scarcity of water due
to climate change, Irish Water would
decide to close down and decommission a
perfectly good water treatment system
plant and reservoir.
That is exactly what it proposes to do
with the Poulavanogue water treatment
plant, serving the town of Clonmel.
This is one of the plants currently
serving the town and has done so for the
best part of 100 years.
Irish Water also proposes to decommission
the Ragwell reservoir, a facility that can
hold up to two days water supply for the
town.
At the same time, it is bringing
very hard water into the town.
This supply already supplies part of the
northern part of the town and has
created huge financial problems and
pressures for families who are already
hard pressed.
It damages white goods, electric kettles,
dishwashers, washing machines and
showers, forcing families to replace these
on a regular basis.
Many families are being forced to install
water softeners at considerable cost and
pay for the
Now, Irish Water proposes to impose this
very hard water on homes and businesses in
the town.
Irish Water refuses to even consider
softening this hard water at source,
something which is done routinely
throughout Europe and in the United
States.
Irish Water has also refused to mix the
soft water supply at Poulavanogue
with the hard water supply from Monroe to
reduce the hardness.
South Tipperary TDs have asked for copies
of the various reports Irish Water have
relied on when making these decisions.
We have not received those reports.
Minister to immediately
intervene with Irish Water to stop the
closure and decommissioning
of the Poulavanogue water
supply for the town and for mixing with
the hard water from Monroe and make
available to TDs and public
representatives all reports pertaining to
the closure of the Poulavanogue supply and
Ragwell reservoir.
Irish Water must be made accountable on
these issues and others.
I ask the Minister today to make sure that
happens by intervening with Irish
Water on these issues.
thank the Deputy.
While I do not have the specific details
of the case
he outlined, I will bring this
directly back to the relevant Minister.
Unfortunately,
we still have a number of communities that
are impacted by water infrastructure, much
of which is decades old.
It is important that the Government
ensures that the significant amount of
funding we have put directly into Irish
Water is invested in communities and spent
as quickly as possible and
the upgrades to our water facilities,
treatment plants, piping and
infrastructure that is decades old happen
as quickly as possible.
From July of this year, Uisce Éireann
marked a commitment to invest in the
reimagined water infrastructure right
across Tipperary,
There was a €16 million upgrade in the
Rossadrehid water treatment plant, the
construction of which is now under way and
will provide
safer, more reliable water supply for
homes and businesses right across the
region, originating in the Galtee
Mountains.
It is obviously an important source of
water for the plant and it provides
This is about making sure every part of
the county has access to that type of
supply of water.
It is about making sure the investment and
significant funding that have been
provided by the Government, through the
national development plan and directly to
Uisce Éireann, is invested as quickly as
possible and people see the benefit.
One of the biggest challenges
and I see this in my county as well, is
that our population has grown
significantly in a short space of time.
It is about making sure we can keep up
with that growth, keep up with the
delivery of houses and make sure that, at
the same time,
not just investing in new infrastructure
but also replacing old and outdated
The specific issue the Deputy raised is
one that many people deal with in their
communities.
There is then the impact it has on their
appliances, which means they have to
change them or invest in softeners.
That is a frustration and something people
do not need to deal with.
That is why we are investing this
significant amount of funding overall.
On the specific cases the Deputy
mentioned, I am happy to bring them back
to the Minister to see
can be done to speed up the process and
address the concerns raised by the
Deputy's constituents.
Irish Water is an unaccountable quango.
It has absolutely no respect for TDs or
public representatives.
Every TD in this Dáil can speak directly
to every Government Department,
including every section in the Department
of Social Protection.
TDs can contact county council staff at
management, engineering and
administrative level.
They can speak with HSE staff at all
levels.
They can talk to
Garda officers at local and national
level.
In fact, every TD in this House can speak
directly to any organisation that deals
with the public.
Why is Irish Water
Why does Irish Water refuse to deal
directly with elected public
representatives?
That is the case.
There is no way Irish Water will speak
directly with Members of this House or
members of local authorities.
Why is Irish Water the only organisation
that does this?
elected democratically and
Irish Water should be available to every
TD in this House through
a nominated local official who can deal
with issues arising locally and
nationally.
I ask the Minister to intervene directly
with Irish Water
in relation to stopping the closure and
decommissioning of
the
treatment plant
I fully agree with the Deputy.
Irish Water should be and is accountable
to every single person in this House.
There
is a process in place and it should be the
case that
can access and can talk directly to
people.
I am not saying that
working
it is absolutely essential that an
organisation that has been provided with
€12 billion, as it has been in a revised
national development plan,
that has been provided with billions of
euro to support the delivery of homes and
to invest in our capital infrastructure is
accountable to every person in this House.
Deputy Healy, please allow the Minister to
conclude.
I understand that, but the Minister has
the floor.
I ask the Minister to respond.
agreeing with the Deputy.
I am saying very clearly it should be the
case.
Deputies should not be standing up here
saying that they cannot access or engage
with people.
I will again raise this directly with the
Minister.
We have spoken of it.
I have spoken of it.
My party colleagues have spoken of it.
Any organisation that receives billions of
from the Government should be and is
accountable to every Member in this House.
It is not acceptable if
not able to access, talk directly to or
get answers from people.
I fully agree with him.
I am very happy to raise the concerns he
has raised here today.
very happy to relay that back to the
Minister.
I expect that, as a public representative,
I should be able to speak to and engage
taxpayers' money and I am elected as a
people's representative to monitor where
that goes.
I fully agree with
and I will raise his concerns directly.
I wish to discuss one of the key
educational commitments of the programme
for Government, specifically
to reduce the
general pupil-teacher ratio in primary
schools to
19:1.
The opportunity afforded to Government to
contribute to fulfilling that commitment
should be utilised as part of
2027.
As I said, the commitment aims to bring
the general pupil-teacher ratio down to
19:1 over the lifetime of the Government
and it is time we started looking at that
given that we are now in the second budget
of five of this Government.
The primary staffing schedule furnished to
schools for this current academic year,
2026-27, advised schools that they will
operate on the basis
of a general average of one classroom
teacher for every 23 pupils.
We know that there are schools where there
are children in classes of greater size.
Yesterday I spoke to a parent of a child
in senior infants where
a class of 29.
While the trend is going in the right way,
Department of education statistics
highlight that in the last academic year
some 39,000 school children were in
classes of 30 or more.
there are local-based factors that
contribute to that and
not all simply down to the primary
teaching schedule.
However, in comparing 23:1, as it is for
the next academic year, and 19:1, where we
hope to get to, we have some distance to
travel in the fulfilment of the
commitment.
I think everyone can appreciate the
benefit to a pupil's learning
to be in a class of a smaller size.
My own professional experience was that
within the schools where I was privileged
to work, wherever we encountered a
challenge in the progression of a pupil,
be that an academic challenge, behavioural
challenge, social challenge or
communicator challenge, the best resource
that we could make available to try to
meet those challenges and to work with the
pupil was to increase discrete
pupil-teacher time.
That is at a premium and it is at even
more
premium when we consider the broadened
curriculum, the new curriculum framework
that is going to introduce new subjects.
This is an issue that is pressing and
pending.
Schools are inundated with people selling
online tools, schemes and programmes to
try to help with the issues that pupils
encounter.
However, without a shadow of a doubt, all
of those fall into insignificance when
compared with the progress that can be
made by providing additional discrete
pupil-teacher time.
Minister will be aware that more children
are undergoing NEPS and, indeed, non-NEPS
psychological assessment.
The outcomes of these assessments are
generally the formation of a report where
a number of recommendations
the benefit of a specific pupil.
It is simply impossible for a teacher to
do that when they are teaching a class of
25 or 26 pupils.
The issue is pressing.
It is a commitment of the programme for
Government and I hope that we will start
to try to fulfil that commitment in the
upcoming budget.
thank the Deputy for raising this matter.
At the outset,
schools do.
While I take the opportunity whenever I
can in my role, particularly last year as
Minister for education,
to travel right around the country to meet
with many teachers, SNAs, secretaries,
principals, caretakers and assistants -
everybody who plays a significant role in
the education of our children.
The work they do is absolutely phenomenal
and I want to acknowledge that here.
That is why Government is investing a
record €14.1 billion in education and the
intention very clearly is to continue that
investment.
We
look at the number of people employed in
our schools, which is important for the
question the Deputy has asked.
Teacher numbers at primary level increased
by almost 6,000 between 2019 and 2025.
We have seen a massive increase in the
number of teachers who have been employed.
During that time, we also saw a massive
increase in the number of SNAs and the
number of assistants who have been
employed.
Over 24,000 are now teaching in our
schools, supporting our teachers and most
importantly supporting our children as
well.
In terms of the overall staffing schedule
and the overall ratio,
based on that investment
down to 23:1 for the current school year.
When the number of SNAs and assistants
within a classroom is taken into account,
it brings the overall number down.
At the same time, I appreciate that for
some classrooms the numbers are much
higher.
I appreciate that for some schools, while
they might be around the average, some
classes are much higher and we want to try
to bring
down as quickly as possible or in the most
stable way possible.
a clear commitment within the programme
for Government that we would bring that 21
number down to 19 and it is a commitment
that we have said we will reach within the
lifetime of the Government.
The Minister for education will obviously
be engaging with the Minister for public
expenditure and reform.
How that is decided and what priorities
are set this year are matters for the
Minister, but I know that she will be
seeking to get as many resources
and to provide as much support
to our teachers and importantly to our
children as well.
we have more favourable ratios implemented
for the DEIS urban band 1 schools.
We have
seen the highest level of investment in
our DEIS schools, making sure that those
who need our help the
they are from or because of instances that
happened in their lives, are provided with
as much support as possible.
I fully agree with the Deputy.
My own little man went off to school this
year and I see the impact
that a
can have a long-lasting impact on a child,
whether they like school, whether they
want to go to school, the dynamic in the
classroom, but also how they learn and how
that then sets them up for later in life.
we can do to reduce the numbers to provide
as much class time
between students and their teachers, their
SNAs, their assistants.
That is our objective and our goal.
why the money
has increased
and why I hope in this year's budget we
will see a further increase again.
The last point the Minister made is
relevant today in particular.
This morning, we heard and read of a new
ESRI study produced in partnership with
Tulsa that highlights that school
attendance rates are dropping.
In recent years, we have seen a decline
and it is pertinent that there is concern
about that.
In schools with higher levels of
disadvantage, attendance rates are not as
good
in schools that do not have that same
level of disadvantage.
However, it is important to
out that there is a level of deprivation
in every school.
Certainly, in DEIS and DEIS plus schools,
there is a greater concentration of that
deprivation but all schools have pupils
whom staff will recognise as being
deprived.
As the Minister pointed out, one of the
things that increases the chance of that
child attending school is a good
relationship between the pupil and the
teacher.
That is easier to build when there are
fewer pupils with whom the teacher has to
work.
That is a very pertinent point the
Minister made.
Minister is right in saying that in recent
years the Government has significantly
increased the number of teachers.
They
all been applied in the mainstream
setting, and I am talking specifically
about the mainstream setting.
also seen an increase in the diversity of
pupil profiling and
increase in pupil needs.
It is important that we try to achieve
that 19:1 ratio and that we start to work
on that as soon as possible.
I fully agree there are lots of things we
need to focus on to make sure children are
going to, staying in and
progressing in school.
When I was Minister of the Department,
following on from
work of the previous Minister,
Foley, before me and work
now carrying on, there was an action plan
put in place specifically looking at
attendance and how we can ensure children
come to school, particularly where the
levels within DEIS bands and primary
schools were increasing at an astronomical
rate.
I think one in four was missing more than
20 days throughout the year, not including
weekends and bank holidays and everything
in between.
There is a huge amount of work we need to
focus on to ensure children are going to
school and that parents are supported.
In particular,
those who need that extra bit of help, the
hot school meals are essential to that.
making sure children have food and are
able to focus and concentrate in school.
The books we have introduced take an
additional cost
of parents when they start school or at
the beginning of any year.
We also provide funding and supports to
make sure uniforms can be bought, that the
resources can be provided and that schools
can get what they need.
I appreciate that is something else in the
budget that we need to keep increasing to
ensure schools have the resources they
need.
Again, I appreciate there is a lot of work
we want to be able to do, but we have
fantastic schools and teachers in this
country.
Our objective as a Government has to be
continue to invest in both.
People are being hammered by the rising
cost of fuel.
The price of petrol and diesel has
increased sharply in the last while.
In some forecourts
this morning - I
know if
seen it - people are being asked to pay
€2.20 for
a litre of diesel.
People have seen these prices go up day
after day.
They also know that when these prices go
up, the Government rakes it in with regard
to additional VAT it charges on these high
prices.
It is not just petrol and diesel; home
heating oil has skyrocketed.
The price of 1,000 litres of home heating
oil has gone up hundreds of
in the last two weeks alone and households
cannot take any more of this.
I am asking the Minister serious questions
here because people need action right now.
They do not need commentary; they want to
know what is going to happen.
Is the Government willing to
cut excise on petrol and diesel?
That is exactly what needs to be done to
help families and workers at this time.
Will the Minister implement the
legislation I am bringing before the House
need to keep their homes warm this winter?
The Government has not removed a single
cent of excise from it up until now.
Deputy is right; people need action, not
words.
That is exactly why, at this time and at
this moment in the year, €1.4 billion has
already been provided to people to try to
assist with what is a very challenging
time - I fully agree with the Deputy -
much of which has been caused by the
conflict in the Middle East, where we need
to focus our efforts as well.
While
a small country, we still have a voice and
we need to use it to ensure every effort
is made to end the conflict because that
is the first and quickest way in which we
can see a reduction.
the fuel allowance, and the tax reductions
on energy
the Deputy voted against in the Chamber,
so that we give people that bit of a break
and make sure there is certainty in the
time ahead.
On top of that
we have a budget coming up.
On
the
Taoiseach, the
and
Minister,
Chambers, have all said they want to do
something on home heating oil and will do
something in the budget to assist people
in
the short
term.
The Deputy can be assured of that.
Increasing the cost of using public
transport by an average of 15% is a
political decision.
It is happening because this Government
refuses to invest in the
NTA,
in the expansion of the network and
ultimately
in its passengers.
We now know this is only the start of
fare increases.
The Government intends to raise them again
and again.
While Government backbenchers love the
photo-op of opening a new bus stop, what
people who stand at those bus stops need
the Government to do right now is to
demand that these fare increases are
reversed and
they do not happen.
The Government is making this decision
during a climate emergency,
when we should be doing everything in our
power to incentivise the use of public
transport, not disincentivise it.
It is making this decision amid an
affordability crisis where 15% will become
30%, which will become 50%.
a very simple question: Will the Minister,
her Cabinet and their backbenchers reverse
this decision?
Deputy said, the National Transport
Authority made the decision to publish the
new fares on 3 September of this year,
with the revised fares taking effect from
January 2027.
This was a really important step in
standardising the national fares
structure.
It is in line with a strategy that was
published back in 2023.
Since 2022, we have seen inflation of
almost 21%, which has of course driven up
the cost of operating our public
transport.
The public transport network is not immune
in the same way that people getting into
their car
driving to work are not.
At the same time, in that period, we have
seen costs drop, specifically
20% in the cost-of-living fares reduction,
the young adult card discount of 50%
the extension of free travel to children
under nine, so we have seen reductions in
costs for all people outlined there.
It is about getting the balance right and
being able to invest in the network to
expand it so
more people can access it while also
taking into account the fact inflation is
impacting that sector.
At all times, and to reassure the Deputy
because we
all impacted by this and have significant
public transport in our constituencies, we
want to make sure it is affordable for
people.
All of this has to be kept under review
and we have to make sure we are doing
everything possible to ensure any of the
changes and the €1.4 billion I mentioned
are passed on to our public and private
transport operators.
The Labour Party
want to raise with
the compounding crisis year on year for
school transport.
It is impacting every constituency.
I represent a largely urban constituency,
yet I am dealing with ten families in
Swords who are unable to get school
transport up to Coláiste Ghlór na Mara in
Balbriggan.
This is happening every single year; kids
are being left at the side of the road.
My
colleague Deputy Wall is dealing with over
100 families across four routes in Kildare
South and Deputy Eoghan Kenny,
behind me,
dealing with over 100 families in his area
of Cork.
Leitrim County Council, Cavan County
Council, Galway
own
in Meath - everywhere - are saying school
transport is not working and kids are
being left at the side of the road.
Can we have a solution, not only for this
year but a proper plan for school
transport so
not back here next year with more kids
being left at the side of the road?
We do have a plan.
Every year, more and more children are
getting access to school transport.
I appreciate not everybody is getting
access and there is more work we need to
do.
I think the figure was 181,000 young
people
had access to school transport this year.
We have to acknowledge we only have so
many buses and drivers, but we also need
to make sure we have a system that works
effectively.
One of the most important things we will
work on in the time ahead is a new
ticketing system.
We know there are buses where not all of
the tickets are being used.
There are people who are taking up tickets
and then not using the bus.
We need to make sure that if that is the
case, the seats can then be provided to
somebody else who needs the bus more.
We can only do that if we have an
automatic ticketed system whereby people
can monitor who is getting on the bus and
who is not.
That will be one of the most important
things we do in addressing some of the
issues and challenges.
That work is under way and is happening
through the Department.
I appreciate it is a challenging issue.
We all deal with it in our constituencies,
but importantly,
for parents.
Again, I stress that more money
being spent - significant amounts,
hundreds of millions - every year on
school transport.
More children
accessing it,
we need to make sure we have the buses,
the drivers and the appropriate system in
place to monitor who is on it.
With huge numbers of households struggling
with the hikes in electricity and
energy costs, how does the Government
think it is okay for ordinary working
people and householders to pay twice as
much per unit of electricity
how can the Government honestly justify
not supporting
imposing a levy on those billionaire
owners of the data centres so that we can
give a serious break, €500, to every
household to help them with their energy
bills and to all those with disability,
yet oppose that and defend
the status quo?
Is that
the reason people will be marching again
this weekend on the Affordable Ireland
demonstration in advance of the budget,
because the Government is protecting the
interests of the billionaire owners of
data centres that are hoovering up our
electricity while ordinary working
families are being hammered with increased
energy and electricity bills?
sure
what we did in this House, the Deputy
would be encouraging people to protest
That is something we must protect, but he
cannot ignore the fact that as a
Government, this year alone, we have
introduced supports of €1.4 billion.
other parts of Europe and the world, very
few governments have been able to
introduce that type of funding and support
to assist people at what is a really
difficult time.
The debate will take place later this
evening-----
obviously the Deputy does not acknowledge
that data centres represent critical
infrastructure, that
central to our modern economy and that
was being done through
LEAP, which is the new strategy looking at
large energy users.
A main focus of that is how we can
introduce more renewable energy and how we
can reduce the energy
needs of those large data centres.
We do not have any other large industries
that are drawing on our grid but
we need to make sure that individual
homeowners are not paying for larger
businesses and their energy costs and
their needs.
a clear plan in place,
businesses put in place their own measures
to make sure they are focused on a
zero-sum approach and can produce their
own electricity and their own grid through
renewable sources.
That is where we need to get to and I
agree with
on that.
As we come to the beginning of this term
which will bring the Government to two
years in office,
are we finally going to see some joined-up
thinking?
The Government has asked councils to
rezone additional lands for housing in
unsustainable areas
when we do not have the infrastructure in
place
like Clonburris and Adamstown.
They are areas with no electric vehicle
charging infrastructure for a domestic
tariff and inadequate parking, where
people are fighting in Kilcarbery, Seven
Mills, Adamstown and Citywest for spaces.
The Government is saying this is to
encourage a greener society and get people
to use public transport but the public
transport does not exist.
There is an inadequate train network and
the buses keep being missed.
The P29 express service, for example, was
missed four times out of four two weeks
ago and twice today and yesterday.
There is No.
13 and the C-spine routes.
All over my constituency, the buses are
not turning up.
The National Transport Authority is not
accountable to anyone
not fit for purpose.
If the Government is also increasing the
fares, it is giving a big middle finger to
people in my constituency.
Where is the joined-up thinking that says
if
going to
put in, it will have facilities and
infrastructure alongside
and buses that actually exist?
Every local authority is probably
conducting the review of their own county
development plan at the moment.
It is important in that review that we are
all increasing our housing targets and the
allocations that we have been given, and
that
making sure land is zoned on land that is
appropriate, but also
land
can be opened up where it needs to be.
To support that,
a significant fund that has already been
provided.
More will be provided at a later date but
money has already been provided to local
authorities to open up lands to provide
infrastructure, whether roads, electricity
or water,
in the right place and where it is
appropriate.
Then our towns and our cities can grow and
expand because that is where we have a lot
communities, people can build homes on
their land, whether they live locally or
are born locally.
It is about getting that balance right.
We have a national development plan of
over €100 billion and much of that is to
make sure we are delivering houses in the
right places and the infrastructure is
there so that people can access them and
the local authorities can deliver them.
The programme for Government commits to
improving cancer care and access to
treatment in the regions.
Cork University Hospital stopped carrying
out stem cell
treatments in 2009.
Since then, blood cancer patients from
Cork and the south west have had to travel
James's or Galway at the most vulnerable
time of their lives.
I know a number of people who have had to
travel to Galway and recuperate there
A €27 million stem cell unit at CUH has
had a project team in place since 2024.
The HSE's own tender notice admits
CUH is not providing optimal treatment for
stem cell and CAR-T therapies.
Patients' advocates and clinicians will be
in Leinster House on
October in a meeting organised by
own
Senator, Eileen Lynch.
To be fair to Eileen, she has advocated
for this for a long time, as well as
others in Cork and Kerry.
I have written a number of letters to the
HSE about this
I get the same old gibberish responses.
We just want a definite answer.
Can
confirm the funding is there,
the timeline for its delivery, since, as I
said, the project team has been in place
a number of years, and if CAR-T therapies
would be part of that as well?
If
have a response today, she might provide
it in writing afterwards.
Unfortunately, I
be able to give
a direct response today.
I hope
agree that this Government, the previous
Government, and governments before that
have placed a huge emphasis on investment
in cancer care,
prevention and on identifying
investing in new therapies.
I know the CAR-T therapy that the
breakthrough, its significance, and making
sure that every patient across the country
going through.
While I cannot give
the exact answer today on timelines,
figures or funding, I will bring it
directly back to the Minister and ask her
to respond.
I have no doubt that she will engage with
and Eileen.
Last weekend, I happened to be out doing
some community events and
men's sheds.
They all came with the same story about
the threat to the funding model that they
had and the fear that maybe the funding
has ceased for this year.
I know that some works were done in the
interim but what I want to do, given the
outstanding commitment that they make to
the men's sheds and the community effort
that they are involved with in tackling
loneliness and promoting well-being, I
want us to be sure that the funding model
that we put in place is fit for purpose
and does not threaten those very schemes
into the future.
I met a number of members of men's sheds
at the
this week and they raised this matter with
me directly.
I have known and worked with men's sheds
locally and at a national level for many
years.
As the Deputy said, I can only commend the
position and role that they have in our
communities in addressing the well-being
of older men and health issues, and
bringing people together in a way that
simply
exist before they were put in place.
I commend the teams that operate, deliver,
expand and manage them.
I have no doubt
the commitment of the Department
responsible.
At this stage, it crosses over a number of
different Departments naturally.
That commitment to funding will remain but
we need to ensure that where they are
growing, which they are, and to open up in
different counties that the funding can
grow and expand with them.
I will raise this directly with the
relevant Ministers and bring back
Minister is familiar with this issue, and
I call on her to intervene personally and
urgently.
The fifth-class students in Gaelscoil na
Ríthe in Dunshaughlin are currently being
accommodated in a small library room in an
old prefab.
Support hours are being provided in the
staff room.
This is because a promised prefab that
should be in place is not in place and
they are being told that it will be the
end of quarter one 2027 when it is
delivered.
This was a positive news story with an
additional junior infants class and it
was welcomed.
The school has gone above and beyond to
facilitate additional students.
It is incredible to me, and to all of
Ireland, that it would take the guts of 12
months to deliver a prefabricated modular
unit to this school.
The Minister knows well as I do, the
factory is literally a couple of hundred
yards up the road.
I ask the Minister to please intervene
personally with the Minister and the
Department.
Get this done.
The problem is with the Department.
Get it resolved.
It is unacceptable that they have to wait
that long.
This should be delivered in the next
handful of weeks, in my firm opinion.
Deputy
outlined, this is actually a really
positive story.
We have all, the Deputy included,
worked closely with parents over the past
number of months to make sure that the
additional classroom that was needed to
ensure that children going from naíonraí
were able to go into a Gaelscoil in their
local community.
That happened.
I welcome the work by
Minister, Deputy Hildegarde Naughton, to
support us in making that happen.
My objective now,
is to make sure that the classroom, is
provided as quickly as possible.
A commitment
the Department, to make sure that we can
provide that as quickly as possible.
We
want any child to be
in a classroom or an environment that is
too small or that
necessarily as appropriate as it should
be.
We are doing everything that we can to
make sure that the classroom is provided
as quickly as possible.
Sligo University Hospital will shortly
submit its options appraisal for formal
capital approval for the replacements of
its orthopaedic theatres.
This project will provide two new
replacement orthopaedic
I appeal to the Minister for Health and
the Department to move swiftly in
approving this critical development.
The existing orthopaedic theatres are no
longer fit for purpose.
Over the past 18 months, numerous
operations have been cancelled due to
leaks from roofs, radiators and
humidifiers, resulting in breaches of
theatre sterility.
Six orthopaedic surgeons have been unable
to perform scheduled procedures while
patients face unacceptable delays and
prolonged suffering.
I urge the Minister and the Department to
please prioritise this capital project as
a matter of urgency.
the work that has been done to get to this
point in trying to make progress on this
capital investment.
I will raise this directly with the
Minister and highlight the Deputy's
representations on behalf of the local
community and those working in the
hospital in ensuring that these type of
services can be provided.
Again, while I cannot give
a commitment today, I will raise it
directly with the
Minister.
I will raise how badly newly qualified
student nurses have been treated by the
HSE in Cork.
In June, these students interviewed for
posts and were offered jobs in named
clinical areas in CUH.
In September, the HSE tried to
back on this decision in really shoddy
terms.
It organised two meetings with the
students that were cancelled and then, at
short notice of just five hours, it called
the students before it and said that
instead of getting jobs in named clinical
areas, they would be placed on the bank.
We accept and welcome the bank.
It will reduce the cost spent on agency
staff, but it is not appropriate for newly
qualified student nurses who want to be
part of a team, want to expand their
skills and want to expand their practice.
Ultimately, these students were offered
posts and accepted them.
They had offers and accepted them.
Does the Minister accept that the HSE is
in breach of contract to these newly
qualified student nurses by trying to
back on this?
Why have student nurses in other parts of
the country,
been
These are badly needed across the country,
We need to hire these students and offer
It is so badly needed.
Staff morale is on the floor and is
getting worse with the way the HSE is
treating its staff.
Without knowing the details of the
contract or what happened, I take what the
Deputy is saying.
I am not contradicting that, but without
knowing the details of what has happened,
the timelines and why it has happened, I
do not want to comment on something I
have information on.
The Deputy is right.
In any business, if somebody is offered a
contract and they have signed it, an
agreement is in place.
It is important that this is followed
through on.
We also want to make sure for anybody
entering into a workforce for the first
time that their first experience is a
positive one.
It is the role of the HSE to work with and
to support our newest staff, whether they
are nurses, doctors or people working in
specific fields.
Again, while I
know the details of what happened in this
specific hospital with these specific
nurses, I am happy to take it back to the
Minister and highlight the fact the Deputy
has raised it.
If she is not aware of
ask her to engage with
directly on
The decision
by
Minister, Deputy Calleary, to scrap the
men's shed grant for 2025-26 has shocked
The grant, small as it is, helps toward
basic things like rent,
insurance, ESB, heating and water.
The withdrawal of the grant will have
serious consequences for the sheds.
Many will have to cut opening hours or
reduce activities and some will face
closure.
As the Minister knows, men's sheds are at
the heart of local communities.
Of course, they are non-profit.
They are places where men can gather to
socialise, share skills, build
friendships, combat isolation and
loneliness and support each other in
mental and physical health.
The withdrawal of this small grant,
which does so much good, beggars belief.
It is not good enough.
I am asking the Minister, Deputy Calleary,
to restore this grant immediately.
It is a vital grant.
It is a small grant but it does
exceptionally good work.
It should be restored immediately.
I reiterate,
the importance of our men's sheds.
I acknowledge the significant contribution
they make within our communities,
particularly for the men who avail of the
services.
I
think they see it as services; it is a
place for them to go to engage,
address and talk about issues that are
important to them, as well as engaging in
activities.
I will raise the Deputy's concerns
directly with the Minister.
I have no doubt, as there are various
strands of funding that have been
allocated over the years, particularly in
the Department of Health as well as
rural affairs, directly to the men's
sheds, that we will continue to support
and fund men's
and support their growth.
How that is done and what funding stream
will be decided in the upcoming budget,
but I will raise the Deputy's concerns
directly with the Minister,
The
recently echoed his predecessor as leader
of Fine Gael, Leo Varadkar, in saying that
this Government will provide a budget for
people who get up early and go to work.
Was the Tánaiste thinking that this
includes the tens of thousands of workers
country five days a week, who are now
facing an average increase of 15% in their
costs to get to work?
Many of them
facing increases of up to 33%.
These planned fare hikes are an attack on
workers and people who get up early in
the morning.
This is a political decision.
This is a direct result of this Government
changing the 2:1 ratio of investment in
public transport to roads-----
which was trumpeted at the start of this
Administration.
The NTA does not have the money to do
things right because
not getting it from the Government.
The Government is throwing commuters under
the bus.
The Government was able to find almost
€1.2 billion behind the back of the couch
Why can we
look after commuters in the same way?
simply not the case.
I outlined in a response to a previous
Deputy that we have seen costs reduce.
We have a 20% cost discount in terms of
living discount.
The young adult
card is a 50% discount and
allowed children under nine to travel for
free.
We have tried to put in
over the years, while at the same time
recognising that the cost of fuel is
impacting our public transport sector in
the same way it is impacting everybody
else.
We also want to ensure there is investment
in our public transport, that more people
can access it, that
encouraging more people, whether it is
through buses, trains or cycleways,
that
able to provide that investment as well.
There is significant investment, through
the national development plan and the
Department of Transport, but we have to
get that balance right.
It is about making sure we have those
targeted measures for younger people and
students and discounted measures for
people who might need them most, while at
the same time trying to get that balance
right.
I appreciate
nobody wants to see their fares going up,
but
some of the rail lines, what we have
seen - even in my own constituency - is
that fares have gone down.
We
see fares go up and down depending on
where they are and what type of investment
is happening.
It is always about getting the balance
right and trying to make it as cheap as
possible for people.
While solar energy has an important role
to play in achieving Ireland's renewable
energy targets, there is growing concern
across Galway about the scale and location
of proposed solar farm developments.
Many constituents have raised concerns
about solar proposals, including the
projects being pursued on productive,
top-tier agricultural farmland and in
close proximity to rural homes and
communities.
The closest panels in the case of the
County Galway are within 50 m of some
homes and
100 m of other homes in a local estate.
Councillor David Collins held a meeting
last Tuesday regarding local concerns,
including the impact of construction
traffic on the local school, the proximity
of the proposal and the future expansion
of Lackagh village, which I attended.
In line with the commitment contained in
the programme for Government, will the
Minister provide an update on when the
solar energy guidelines will be published
Will we see guidelines this year, or will
they be
put on the long finger,
accept that clear planning guidance is
required urgently?
Will the Government consider a temporary
moratorium for large-scale solar
I agree with the Deputy on both fronts.
I think we all agree that we need to
invest more in renewable energies.
We need to invest more in offshore wind
and in solar of all types, not just on
land but on roofs and on our public sector
and service buildings.
We also need to engage with communities
and make sure that we get this right.
What the Deputy has outlined in his county
I have in my own county where a huge
number of solar farms have been
approved and more applications
coming in.
It is important that we get that balance
right.
We all support the expansion of renewable
energy.
We know we need more of it given all of
the discussion we have had this morning on
fuel prices, the increase in prices and
how we reduce our reliance on fossil fuels
but, at the same time, we need to make
sure that there is guidance.
I know the Minister, Deputy O'Brien, is
leading on this and he is working closely
with
Minister, Deputy Browne, and the
Department of housing.
The intention from the Department of
housing is to issue the national planning
statement specifically on this, akin to
guidance, and that work is under way.
I
have a direct timeline for the Deputy, but
I would like to see it happen as quickly
as possible.
I would like to see it to continue to
engage with communities so that any
expansion can be done in a managed and
appropriate way.
I raise the issue of trees that have been
planted by local authorities in roadside
pits in the 1970s and 1980s.
In many instances, they were very welcome
at the time, but a lot of the trees
planted at that time - over 50 years ago -
were clearly the wrong species.
Some of them have grown hugely and they
have huge root systems.
The root systems have uplifted footpaths
and private boundary walls.
They have invaded front gardens and done
damage to driveways on private properties.
When residents raise these issues with
their local authority, they are given a
claim form, told to fill it in and send it
to
then passed on to Irish public bodies.
Irish public bodies routinely denies
liability, saying "It has nothing to do
with us and there is no negligence to see
here".
I have a letter from IPB to a constituent,
saying that while it notes their
allegation that the damage was caused by
the roots of a nearby tree, the cause of
the cracking was yet to be established
definitively.
What else could
have uplifted a wall?
It is utterly ridiculous and dishonest.
Can the Government intervene in this?
It is not fair that elderly residents are
left to foot the bills for repairing
private property damaged by the State.
While I cannot point to something specific
to this at the moment, I do know a body of
work
being done, looking at trees planted along
our roadside.
That is specifically following Storm Éowyn
and some of the recent storms where the
trees have become a danger during the
storm, including taking down electricity
wires and by causing danger on our roads.
Unfortunately, we know a young man was
killed in one of the recent storms because
of a falling tree.
A body of work
being done through
Minister, Deputy O’Brien’s Department,
engaging with the ESB and local
authorities to assess where trees need to
be taken down
that they can be taken down and that that
body of work can start as quickly as
possible.
Whether what the Deputy raised can be
included in those discussions or
conversations is something I will bring
back to the Minister.
I think
all very conscious of the need for us to
be clear about where we are planting our
trees
as the Deputy outlined.
My question is on dereliction and how we
can get county councils to enforce current
Government policies.
Dereliction is a plague on most cities,
towns and villages in Ireland.
I commend the Government incentives to
bring properties back into use such as
vacant property refurbishment grant, and
the vacant above-the-shop initiative.
Local authorities have the tools to deal
with dereliction with the first step being
simply to register derelict properties but
I am simply astounded why some councils do
not see fit to embrace these policies.
If you look at the derelict site register
today, there are 154 sites registered in
Waterford and 367 sites registered in
County Limerick and only
four
sites registered in the whole of County
Wicklow.
Why should hard-working businesses and
communities in Carnew, Shillelagh and
especially Arklow have to accept less
dereliction enforcement than any other
county in Ireland to the detriment of
these town and villages?
thank the Deputy for raising this matter.
It is really important that we do
everything in our power to bring derelict
properties back into use,
that we use every lever available to us
and where local authorities are not
responding that we look at what other
levers are available.
It is a priority for this Government, and
a priority in the Government’s housing
The Derelict Site Act contains a number of
actions and powers that can be provided to
the local authorities.
There is a derelict site register,
statutory notices requiring remedial
works, annual levies and compulsory
acquisition powers.
However, as the Deputy said, we have seen
that some local authorities are much
better at this than others.
He rightly said the number of properties
in Wicklow on the derelict site register
is far too low at four so much more needs
to be done.
I understand the Department of housing has
recently met Wicklow County Council to
highlight this and to be clear that more
needs to be done on its part.
The Minister, Deputy Browne, the Minister
of State, Deputy Cummins, and
Minister for Finance are looking to bring
in a new derelict property tax.
That would be an incentive to make sure
that all parties move on this matter.
I recently met the parents of children
with disabilities where the children are
either on a list or attending the
Waterford south city children’s disability
network team.
I find these meetings very difficult
because the story is always the same,
out on developmental supports.
What they told me in relation to this team
is shocking.
We know there are staff shortages across
many CDNTs but this CDNT has no
psychologist, has had no nurse – or at
least the parents have not had access to a
nurse for over a year – no dietician and
the number of occupational therapists has
reduced from two to one.
Even the most basic supports like
incontinence pads were not being made
available to parents for those children.
It is truly shocking that parents have to
battle for the most basic services.
I ask
to look at what is going on in that
particular CDNT.
It is obviously a problem across all
CDNTs.
They are not fully staffed.
We have children across Waterford city
whose parents are battling.
Those children are missing out on
developmental supports because the staff
are not there.
It is not good enough and I ask the
Minister to raise it with the relevant
Minister.
happy to raise the specific cases and
specific area.
I know it has been a challenge over the
years to fill all the teams across the
country but there has been a huge focus
and a huge investment specifically in
disability funding to try to fill the
particular places the Deputy mentioned.
There has also been a look at
restructuring
how the teams work so that
not dependent on perhaps the senior
clinical officer to be able to sign off on
various different strands of support that
might need to be provided.
I will raise
directly with the
Minister.
Yesterday the Cabinet approved going to
tender
the largest investment in public transport
the State will ever see.
When I went to the pre-tender engagement
in DCU I saw the global nature of this
project with potential suppliers from
right across the world.
The reality is the global nature of the
project will hit the ground from next year
with enabling works and for the next ten
years, at the very least, my community
will face many of the challenges of Metro
as well as its benefits.
We absolutely welcome Metro - it is a
really important project - but we need to
get out now and start telling communities
what this will mean for them in terms of
construction, traffic disruption,
engagement with genuine concerns and so
on.
I urge the NTA and TII to start that work
now and engage with local residents'
associations.
They want to be part of the process and be
part of the success of this project.
Inevitably, they will have concerns and
questions as with any project.
I urge that we ensure that
is part of a project that will be with us
for a long time to come.
right.
One of the biggest barriers or things that
slows down projects is a lack of
engagement and at the earliest stage
possible.
I fully agree with the Deputy and support
the need for the NTA and TII to engage
directly.
I know
highlight what is happening and the
benefits and the challenges that will
arise as is the case with any development
of this size or significance.
This is a massive investment in the
Deputy’s community and
our communities in Dublin, in particular.
It is really important that we can move
this project along as quickly as possible.
It is really important that we bring
people with us and that
aware of everything that is happening.
I must say to
as Minister for foreign affairs it is an
appalling situation that on
one hand, Ireland goes into the EU Council
of Foreign Ministers to advocate for the
cause of
adopts a mean spirited and hypocritical
approach with regard to refusing so many
Palestinian students visas.
There is a 70% refusal rate this year.
was only 15% last year.
My specific question relates to the EU
Digital Omnibus package,
Ireland’s position and the Minister’s role
in that.
Effectively, the direction of travel is to
loosen the protections in the AI
Act.
Last week, alarm bells were sounded by the
developers of AI.
AI has enormous potential
positive impact, particularly in the area
of health, but we know for workers,
consumers, for our security and democracy
there are particularly terrifying
prospects.
What is the Minister doing to ensure that
we have much better AI regulation in the
European Union and that
not going to diminish the existing
standards and protections there already?
The Digital Omnibus package is one of
perhaps 12 pieces of legislation we are
bringing forward at the moment under the
simplification objective we have during
the Presidency.
I want to dispel the myth that might be
out there that changing legislation in
some way weakens or loosens it a bit.
The whole objective is to make it more
straightforward and simplify it where we
can while, at the same time, protecting
people’s rights and making
those
responsible and accountable for protecting
consumers
also
concerned at the pace and speed at which
AI is moving.
We need to make sure that in the EU, the
appropriate regulations and rules
in place but that we
stifle growth and innovation.
We need to make sure we are embracing and
enhancing our day-to-day lives with the
technology as it is evolving.
We also need to monitor and manage it.
What you will see during the Presidency is
Ireland taking a very
central approach and making sure we get
the balance right.
We are not trying to have fewer rules; we
are trying to make sure they are better
and that we can apply them better as well.
This Bill is very simple.
It is a response to the fact that people
right across this State feel as if
being fleeced in relation to the cost of
home heating oil, and why would they not?
The fact is the
home heating oil has gone through the
roof.
This has happened not just in the past
couple of weeks, which I will discuss.
The cost of home heating oil from last
year to the start of last summer increased
by
€500 for a fill.
This is the eighth occasion on which I
have brought forward either a financial
respond, demanding that it have ordinary
workers' and families' backs and demanding
to keep their homes warm.
The Minister, Deputy McEntee, along with
her Cabinet colleagues, those in Fianna
Fáil, the Independents and some in the
Opposition, like the Soc Dems, vote to
continue to place these taxes on home
heating oil and
When I say this is the eighth occasion,
the reason I keep bringing this back is
that I have stood in too many houses and
had too many conversations with people who
tell me they are pushed to the pin of
their collar just trying to keep their
homes warm.
I told them I would have their back and
would not give up.
This is why we introduce this legislation
now, demanding that the Government
respond, demanding that the Government see
sense and demanding that the Government
get rid of carbon tax on home heating oil
while these prices go through the roof,
and by God they are going through the
roof.
In the past three weeks alone, the price
of home heating oil, according to the
forecourts buying it, has gone up €300 for
a 1,000 litre fill.
That is on top of the fact that it already
went up €500 compared with where it was
last year.
Yet, the Government still argued and voted
two weeks ago not to reduce a single
cent of tax on home heating oil.
Worse than that, and you could not make
this up, the Government's plan is, on 14
October, to increase the cost of home
heating oil.
Lo and behold, Sinn Féin produces this
legislation and then Simon Harris has an
epiphany: "Oh, maybe we need to do
something in the Finance Bill and in the
budget."
As I said earlier, talk is cheap.
What people want is action.
What people want are results.
This legislation gives them the results
they are demanding: reduce the cost of
home heating oil and get rid of carbon tax
on it.
The Government can do that with the stroke
of a pen.
It does not need approval from the
European Union.
That is what a responsible government that
has the back of ordinary workers and
families would do.
not just home heating oil that tax needs
to be cut on.
The Government needs to cut the tax on
petrol and diesel.
What is happening out there is madness.
Right across this State, people are
driving up to their forecourts and seeing
prices of €2.14 and €2.15.
In places like Limerick we are seeing
prices of €2.21 for a litre
of diesel.
It has gone through the roof.
In the past three weeks alone, the price
of diesel being sold to our pump operators
has gone up 30 cent.
What is the plan from
Government?
Again, the law states
on 14 October it will put the price of
diesel up another 2 cent by increasing
carbon tax.
Hopefully, it will see sense and not
proceed with that madness, but that alone
is not enough.
The Government needs to reduce taxes on
petrol, diesel, home heating oil and green
diesel, and that can be done.
We have the resources to do it.
It is what needs to be done.
This legislation is the first step in
getting the Government to get its head out
of the sand, to understand the pressure
that ordinary Irish people are under every
single day of their lives and, instead of
making things harder, to make sure that it
lifts some of the burden.
It is not lost on anybody that when the
price of home heating oil goes up, more
money goes into the Government pockets in
the form of VAT.
When the price of diesel reaches €2.20, it
should be remembered that 23% of that
increase goes into the Government's
pockets in the form of VAT.
Hundreds of millions of euro is flowing
into the Government because of these price
increases.
It is time the Government gave it back to
the people, cut the taxes, abolished
carbon tax on home heating oil and removed
further taxes on petrol and diesel to get
these prices back down.
Is the Bill opposed?
I move: "That the Bill be
Before I start, I wish Deputy Michael
Healy-Rae a quick
recovery from the horrible attack
yesterday evening in Dublin.
I spoke to him last night.
He was in good form and on his way back
home.
He and his family
need time for him to recover.
It has been such a harrowing experience.
I am delighted to see that an arrest has
been made, and we
very concerning for everybody that
something like that could happen in broad
daylight in our capital city.
pleased to bring the National Vehicle and
Driver File, Road Traffic and Roads Bill
2026 before the House.
This is a practical Bill but its purpose
is significant.
It is about making sure that the law that
supports road safety, vehicle compliance,
enforcement and public administration is
modern, clear and fit for purpose.
The policy rationale is straightforward.
The State must be able to use accurate
vehicle and driver information lawfully
and responsibly.
Local authorities must have the collision
data they need to identify risks and
target action.
Enforcement systems must work efficiently.
The Bill also advances the Government's
digital agenda and improves the efficiency
The law on motor tax, vehicle records and
speed limits must reflect how services are
now delivered and how road safety
decisions are now made.
There is also a practical necessity.
Much of the legislation being amended was
designed for a paper-based system.
It assumed
display and surrender of discs.
does not fully reflect current systems for
vehicle licensing, compliance checking or
the use of road safety information.
The Bill updates that framework.
It also gives the public confidence that
the system is operating properly.
Above all, there is a road safety
imperative.
Better information supports better
decisions.
Better enforcement supports better
behaviour.
Easier verification supports better
compliance.
Road safety is not secured by one measure
alone.
It depends on safer behaviour, safer
infrastructure, effective enforcement,
reliable data and clear responsibilities.
In practical terms, the Bill does a number
of things.
It modernises the national vehicle and
driver file; underpins the Check My
Vehicle service; removes the need to
display a paper motor tax disc;
allows open-ended declarations for
non-use; supports more flexible and
evidence-based speed limit management;
provides a statutory basis for sharing
collision data with local authorities;
clarifies the operation of penalty points
in multi-offence incidents; and makes
targeted improvements to court and
enforcement procedures.
I will deal briefly with each Part of the
Bill.
Part 1 contains the preliminary and
general provisions.
It provides for the Short Title,
commencement, collective citation,
construction, definitions and repeals.
These are technical provisions but they
matter.
They give the Bill its legal structure.
They also remove provisions that are
obsolete, superseded or no longer
consistent with the policy changes being
made.
Part 1 repeals older provisions on the
display of vehicle licences, non-annual
payment of motor tax, obsolete
notification arrangements and the offence
of failing to display a motor tax disc.
It also amends a provision of the Road
Traffic Act 2024 so that the approach to
special speed limits can be adjusted later
in the Bill.
Part 2 deals with the national vehicle and
driver file,
and
Check My Vehicle service.
The NVDF is the State's central database
for vehicle and driver information.
It supports vehicle registration, driver
licensing, motor tax, enforcement and road
safety.
The current statutory framework is
pre-GDPR and general in nature.
Part 2 modernises that framework.
It sets out more clearly the records and
data held on the file.
It includes appropriate data protection
provisions for personal data.
Part 2 also places access to NVDF data on
a clearer footing.
Where bodies need information to carry out
their functions, access can be provided
in secondary legislation.
The legal basis and purpose can then be
set out clearly.
This includes bodies such as An
Síochána and the Revenue Commissioners.
The objective is simple:
access must be lawful, transparent,
proportionate and linked to the function
being performed.
This Part also underpins the Check My
Vehicle website.
A person will be able to enter a vehicle
registration number and check certain
information held on the NVDF.
That includes the status of motor tax and
roadworthiness tests.
It will not disclose the owner's name or
address.
As paper discs are removed, this service
will provide a clear way to verify
compliance.
That will be useful for car buyers, driver
testers, driving instructors
and others who have a practical need to
check relevant information.
Part 3 removes the requirement to display
a paper motor tax disc and makes the
related changes needed across older
legislation.
This measure forms part of the wider
paperless discs project, under which
physical insurance and roadworthiness
discs will also be abolished.
The requirement to display a disc belongs
to a paper-based system.
Compliance can now be verified through
electronic records.
The law should reflect that.
The Bill therefore repeals the offence of
failing to display a motor tax disc.
It does not remove the obligation to have
motor tax.
The offence of not having motor tax will
be capable of being dealt with as a
fixed-charge offence.
Part 3 also removes outdated references to
surrendering, taking back or displaying
paper discs.
This includes references to refunds,
bouncing cheques and driving tests.
A vehicle licence will be deemed to be
issued when the owner receives a receipt
for payment, either in a local authority
motor tax office or through the online
motor tax service.
Part 4 deals with declarations of non-use
of a motor vehicle.
At present, a vehicle can be declared off
the road for a period of between three and
12 months.
This can create unnecessary administration
where a vehicle remains off the road for
longer or where the period is uncertain.
Under this Bill, a declaration may be made
in the last month of motor tax and may
continue indefinitely until the vehicle is
brought back into use.
This will simplify the process for vehicle
owners and reduce avoidable renewals.
It will also prevent arrears arising
simply because there is a gap between the
end date of
declaration and the next taxing of the
vehicle.
The Bill makes clear that arrears will not
apply to the first application for motor
tax following an open-ended declaration of
non-use.
The
offence to use a vehicle while a
declaration of non-use is in effect.
The Bill also provides transitional
arrangements.
Declarations already in force will end on
the date specified in the
If the vehicle remains off the road after
that date, a new open-ended declaration
Part 5 concerns speed limits.
This Part makes targeted amendments to the
Road Traffic Act 2004.
The purpose is to make sure that road
authorities retain the flexibility they
need within the national speed limit
framework.
It allows local authorities to set a
special speed limit of 60 km/h on local
roads in built-up areas where that is
appropriate This is necessary because the
Road Traffic Act 2024 changes the default
speed limit position.
Without this amendment, local authorities
could lose the legal power to apply a 60
km/h special speed limit to certain local
roads in built-up areas, even
where road circumstances and traffic
planning justify it.
That was never the policy intention.
Part 5 also allows for a special speed
limit of 100 km/h on national secondary
roads, including national secondary
managed roads.
This supports the next phase of speed
limit reform.
Under that phase, the default speed limit
on national secondary roads is to be
reduced from 100 km/h to 80 km/h.
Where a road authority considers that a
particular national secondary road meets
the criteria in the speed limit
guidelines, it should be able to retain a
100 km/h limit through special speed limit
by-laws.
Speed limits are among the most visible
parts of road safety policy.
They influence behaviour.
They affect stopping distances and the
severity of collisions.
These amendments do not weaken speed limit
reform.
They help ensure reform can be implemented
sensibly, lawfully and consistently by the
authorities best placed to understand
local road conditions.
Part 6 contains a number of important road
traffic and roads amendments.
The first allows a jury to consider the
lesser charge of careless driving where a
defendant is acquitted of dangerous
driving.
This amendment arises from Mr.
Justice Haughton's report on the death of
Shane O'Farrell in 2011.
Where the evidence may not establish
dangerous driving to the required standard
but may establish careless driving, the
court process should be able to reflect
Part 6 also provides a legal basis for
local authorities to receive and process
The data may be used for specific
safety purposes.
These include identifying and assessing
safety risks on public roads, targeting
maintenance or construction, and
supporting the proper allocation of
resources.
This Part also provides for nominated
local authorities where two or more local
authorities agree that one authority
should perform a specified executive
function on their behalf.
This is
central road safety provision.
Local authorities require robust
information to identify collision-prone
locations,
assess emerging risks and target
engineering interventions.
Collision data helps them move from
reacting after incidents occur to
identifying patterns and intervening
earlier.
Part also clarifies the application of
penalty points in multi-offence incidents
where a driver is disqualified.
Recent legislation introduces the concept
of a multi-offence incident.
That means that where several penalty
point offences arise from the same
incident, more than one set of
may be endorsed.
A practical difficulty can arise where
fixed-charge notices from the same
incident are paid at different times and a
driver has already been disqualified
before a later, higher set of
is notified.
The Bill makes clear that the swapping-in
of penalty points will not apply where the
driver has already been disqualified.
This avoids having to dismantle and
reconstruct an existing disqualification.
There is no appropriate legal basis for
doing that.
It could also unfairly advantage or
disadvantage the driver, depending on the
sequence of notifications.
Part 6 also provides for operators of
mobile safety camera vans to give
certificate evidence in court where a
fixed-charge notice is not paid.
This means they will not have
to give testimony in every case.
It is a practical enforcement measure.
It supports the efficient presentation of
evidence and helps ensure road traffic
enforcement can operate effectively.
Taken together, the Parts of the Bill form
a coherent package.
Part 1 clears away obsolete provisions.
Part 2 modernises the NVDF and supports
public access to defined
information.
Part 3 removes the paper motor tax disc
requirement while maintaining the
obligation to have motor tax.
Part 4 simplifies declarations of non-use
and Part 6 strengthens court, enforcement
and evidence-led road safety functions.
The Bill is technical in places but its
public purpose is
It makes dangerous behaviour easier to
detect, it makes lawful compliance easier
to verify,
it gives local authorities better
information for road safety work and it
ensures that the legal framework keeps
pace with modern systems and modern
expectations.
It also supports the Government’s Road
Safety Strategy 2021-2030.
This strategy aims to reduce deaths and
serious injuries by 50% by 2030 and
move Ireland towards Vision Zero by 2050.
Strategies must be
by practical action and this Bill is one
such action.
Bill asks the House to support measures
that are reasonable, targeted and
necessary.
It allows data to be used lawfully and
responsibly where it can improve road
safety.
It modernises a motor tax system that
should reflect the digital age.
It gives local authorities the information
they need to make roads safer.
It supports speed limit reform and
strengthens the practical operation of
enforcement.
Above all, it asks us to recognise that
road safety is a shared responsibility.
Every death on our
is a life ended.
It is a family changed forever and it is a
community left to ask whether it could
have done more.
We cannot normalise poor road-user
behaviour and we cannot allow outdated
systems or avoidable legal uncertainty to
stand in the way of road safety.
The Bill is a necessary step in reversing
current trends, strengthening
accountability and building a more modern,
evidence-led and future-focused
road safety system.
I commend the Bill to the House.
I acknowledge the officials in the
Department who have worked tirelessly on
this.
I also acknowledge the work of
previous Ministers of State in this
position
who helped
formulate the Bill in their time at the
Department.
I thank everybody for their support.
Before I call Deputy Daly, there was a
request for copies of the Minister of
State's speech and I am not sure whether
they have arrived.
We have an agreement at the Business
Committee that speeches are provided.
first glance the Bill appears to be
technical and administrative, dealing with
databases, record keeping, data sharing
arrangements and, as
said, motor tax and various amendments.
I know that other amendments
to come on Committee Stage and we look
forward to hearing about them.
Following the M9 crash, the Minister of
State said legislation is being prepared,
following discussions, and we look forward
to seeing what the amendments
A lot of elements in the Bill are sensible
and long overdue.
It modernises the national vehicle and
driver file and introduces open-ended
non-use declarations.
The legislation finally delivers on a
commitment to introduce provisions to
facilitate the sharing of collision data
with local authorities and this is also
welcome.
While the Government asks us to focus on
the administrative reforms, there are
reality in the midst of the growing road
safety crisis.
Road
death numbers are going in the wrong
direction despite what is happening across
Europe, where deaths are
Dangerous driving is becoming increasingly
common.
Communities see less Garda traffic
enforcement and we know that since 2009
the numbers in the Garda road traffic unit
have decreased by about 600.
Last year, they went up by five or six but
clearly this is not enough.
No more than
dealing with public order on the streets,
we need visibility to deter people from
breaking
road traffic laws.
Too many families are suffering and, at a
time when people are deeply concerned
about safety on our roads, the legislative
priorities should be stronger enforcement,
policing resources and investing in black
spots and rural road safety.
This administrative Bill is focused
largely on databases and processes, and
motorists are entitled to ask the simple
question as to what problem it actually
solves.
That is why we look forward to seeing what
amendments will come on Committee Stage.
At the moment the Bill will not stop
reckless speeding or dangerous overtaking,
put more
on the roads or make junctions safer.
Some of the people who came before the
transport committee emphasised the
importance of proper design in towns and
villages, in particular to ensure road
safety.
They
emphasised
visibility of gardaí.
These are the ways in which we can save
lives on the road and make sure the trend
in road deaths starts to decrease or at
least halt.
Vision Zero by 2050 seems an awful long
way off.
The truth is that the Bill does little to
address the issues that are keeping
This year has been the deadliest year on
our roads since 2010, with 120 people
already
lost their lives.
This should set off alarm bells because
every road death, as
mentioned, is more than a statistic; it is
a son or daughter whose future is cut
short, a family grieving and a community
traumatised.
Road deaths are not inevitable.
They are not unfortunate accidents.
They are often the consequence of
lack of investment, policy failures,
enforcement failures and investment
failures.
For years road safety campaigners,
and Garda representatives have been
warning that
traffic enforcement is declining.
An awful lot of money
spent on a lot of road safety campaigns,
which some experts who have come before
the committee have said do not work.
Visible enforcement is one of the
strongest deterrents.
When drivers believe there is little
chance of being stopped, compliance
declines and risk-taking increases.
Communities throughout the country are
reporting growing levels of dangerous
behaviour on our roads.
When Sheila Gilheany of Alcohol Awareness
Ireland came before the committee, she
showed
statistics and compared the likelihood of
being stopped by the police in Australia
with the likelihood of being stopped in
Ireland.
The statistics showed that
people in Ireland go out to drive at
night, they do not think they will meet
a garda, whereas in Australia the opposite
is the case and there is a much
higher rate of
random stops by police.
If my memory serves me correctly, the
number
of people who die on our roads with
alcohol in their system is way higher than
it is in Australia because the deterrent
effect is there with far more random
stops.
The number of people stopped on
the non-display of road
I ask him to encourage the local
authorities and the Garda not to prosecute
disc on their car.
This
legislation is long overdue to address a
number of technical issues and, in
particular, to legislate for the sharing
of collision data.
Since late 2023, local authorities have
been unable to receive vital Garda
collision data.
While the Department did provide for the
partial sharing of this data, there is a
legitimate question to be asked as to why
it has taken nearly three years for the
issue to be resolved.
Without all of this data, local
authorities, which are responsible for
maintaining the majority of the State's
road network, face significant barriers in
implementing road safety measures.
This clearly should have been an urgent
priority for
Government, yet it has taken years to get
to this point and
has caused delays to many road safety
On the broader issue of road safety, the
latest road fatality statistics show that
2026 is likely to be the deadliest year on
Irish roads since 2010.
Road fatalities are up 17.8% so far in
2026 when compared with the same period
last year.
This demonstrates that Ireland's roads are
becoming more dangerous.
Each road fatality statistic represents a
life lost and a wider family devastated,
and
demonstrates the constant work needed to
make our roads safe for all who use them.
The Government's target of halving road
deaths by 2030 is moving further out of
reach.
Despite these trends, the Government has
ignored the overhaul that is needed in
road safety policy and governance, which
was recommended in the 2024 Indecon
report.
This failure in road safety
seen at a national level.
In my constituency, many towns and
villages across Galway have seen road
safety projects delayed and this is having
a significant impact on the people who
live in these areas.
One example I would like to raise is that
of Kilmeen Cross in County Galway, which
the Minister
will be familiar with.
This is an area where there have been a
number of serious accidents.
A road safety scheme was first proposed
there years ago, including lights and a
roundabout, but it has been left in limbo
for years.
It has been passed back and forth between
the council and TII, with no clarity as to
when it will be progressed and no funding
allocation to begin construction works.
That needs to be addressed as a matter of
urgency.
We also have the example of pedestrian
crossings and traffic calming on the
national road through Kinvara, which has
been held up for 20 years.
We have the example of Bridge Street in
Dunmore.
also a national road where there has been
a failure to progress the regeneration and
road widening project.
Residents have
been left waiting years for that
These are the basics that we need to get
right to prevent tragic incidents from
occurring on our roads.
It is not acceptable for crucial schemes,
like the ones I outlined, to be left stuck
in limbo for years.
The Government and TII need to get their
act together and get these schemes
progressed.
Another aspect I would like to raise is
the failure of the Government to
adequately resource the Garda roads
policing unit and the poor level of speed
limit enforcement.
I have raised many times
that there are only 58 speed camera vans
responsible for monitoring speed limits
across 1,900 camera zones.
Likewise, only a handful of fixed speed
cameras are operating across the State.
We cannot say that this is effective
enforcement, especially when we know that
speeding is one of the leading causes of
road collisions.
The Government cannot continue to treat
rising
fatalities on our roads as isolated
incidents.
The reality here is that rising
fatalities reflect fundamental failures
within the Government's approach to road
safety, including the failure to
adequately resource the Garda roads
policing unit, the failure to invest in
road safety measures and the failure to
reform wider road safety policy and
governance.
The time to act is now to save lives on
our roads and ensure that our roads are as
safe as possible for all who use them.
Go raibh maith agat.
Cuirim fáilte roimh an deis labhairt ar an
ábhar seo.
There are sensible provisions in this Bill
that Sinn Féin can support.
Giving local authorities access to
collision data from An Garda Síochána and
the RSA should help
identify dangerous locations and target
investment.
Allowing a jury to consider careless
driving where there has been an acquittal
on a charge of dangerous driving is also
reasonable.
Modernising the national vehicle and
driver file and removing unnecessary
bureaucracy
of course.
I have to say,
legislation alone will not make our roads
safer.
We can pass new laws, create databases and
introduce enforcement mechanisms, but none
of that will make a blind bit of
difference if there are not enough gardaí
in our communities and on our roads to
enforce
The justice committee, which I chair,
heard evidence
from Garda management and the Garda
representative bodies on Garda pursuits
and roads policing.
This followed some horrific incidents over
the summer, including the tragedy on the
M9.
What we heard should be of concern to
everyone in this House.
There are serious deficiencies in the
number of gardaí trained to undertake
vehicle pursuits, while roads policing
numbers have actually declined by 40%
since 2009.
How did we reach a situation where gardaí
encountering someone driving a stolen car
recklessly, potentially putting innocent
lives at risk, have not been given the
specialist training and resources needed
to respond?
We know that a pursuit will not always be
the safest response, and public safety
has to come first, but gardaí need to have
options.
They need the capacity to close roads
quickly, to deploy stinger devices where
appropriate, to co-ordinate air support
and, where necessary and proportionate,
conduct a properly managed pursuit.
That requires training and equipment, but
above all, it requires gardaí, and we
still do not have enough gardaí in our
communities.
Fianna Fáil and Fine Gael have absolutely
failed in that regard, and they are still
not going to reach their too-low targets.
Communities see the consequences of this.
There are restricted Garda station opening
hours, insufficient community gardaí and
reduced
visibility on our roads.
This all needs to be addressed.
I want to speak briefly about the whole
issue of speed vans.
I meet people daily who tell me that they
believe
speed camera vans are positioned not where
they will be most effective in
saving lives but
in revenue raising.
The perception exists that the vans are
located in places where the highest number
of fines will be raised.
That undermines confidence in road safety
enforcement.
Speed enforcement has to be about saving
lives, not raising revenue.
Camera deployment should be transparently
based on collision risk, road design,
speeding patterns and road safety
evidence.
If this Bill improves collision data
sharing with local authorities, then that
information should also guide enforcement
towards where it saves lives.
We also need to have confidence in the
NCT, system.
In 2025, the latest figures we have,
approximately 58.4% of vehicles
that were tested in Cavan failed their
NCT, which was the second highest
in the State.
In Monaghan, there was a failure
the fifth highest nationally.
Of course, there might be some legitimate
explanations, including maybe vehicle age
and mileage, but motorists and people in
my constituency deserve more than
assumption.
The principle has to be that the same car
should have the same prospect of passing
its NCT whether it is tested in Monaghan,
Cavan, Dublin or anywhere else.
I have asked the Minister for Transport to
investigate the disparities in the NCT
pass rates and to compare like with like
in respect of vehicles of similar age,
make, model and mileage, as well as the
defects recorded and outcomes at different
centres.
because in my constituency of
Cavan-Monaghan, like many rural
constituencies, a car is not a luxury.
It is essential for work, school,
healthcare and everyday life.
An NCT failure can have quite profound
impacts.
It means repair bills, retest costs and
serious inconvenience, and that
needs to be dealt with.
Many people would attribute any NCT
failure they have had to the state of the
roads they are forced to drive on daily.
I again put on the record that it is
inconceivable and inexcusable that the
Government has again this year
less money to Cavan and Monaghan to fix
local roads, at a time when costs are
increasing and when roads are in the most
deplorable state I have witnessed in all
my time in politics.
I am referring to local tertiary roads in
particular.
Let us modernise the national vehicle and
driver file and improve collision data
sharing, absolutely, but it has to be
recognised that legislation is only one
part of road safety.
We need an NCT system that people can
trust, roads that are fit for purpose,
speed enforcement targeted at dangerous
roads, and, arguably most important, we
need enough properly trained gardaí with
the equipment and resources necessary to
actually keep those roads safe.
No database, speed camera or new law can
replace trained gardaí on the ground and
the challenge that this Government must
finally address.
I welcome the opportunity to speak on road
safety.
It is an issue and concern for so many
people.
We have seen the recent horrific incidents
on the M50 and the M9.
since then of 75,000 fewer people taking
the motorways in recent weeks.
a member of the justice committee.
This week, we heard from members of An
Garda Síochána.
They confirmed to us that
not one garda in the State, as I speak
here today, who is trained in pursuit.
If I know this, and we all know this, we
had better believe that criminals out
there know this too.
It is 2026, and not one garda in the State
is trained to pursue a vehicle that
drives away at speed or refuses to stop.
This is absolutely shocking.
Any member of the public I have spoken to
during the last couple of weeks, since
this information got out, has found this
unbelievable.
People want to know, and it is a
legitimate question, how this has been
allowed to happen.
I spoke at another debate yesterday.
At that same meeting, a member of the
AGSI, brought out a document from 1988
that
were going to get pursuit training.
It has not happened.
That is 38 years ago.
I think I used the analogy of
Ray Houghton stuck the ball in the England
net,
and we still do not have a garda trained
to pursue any fleeing vehicle.
also the issue of e-scooters and
scramblers being used to terrorise
our streets.
The Government brought in legislation to
tackle the use
after the tragic death of Grace Lynch, yet
people in my community, and
communities across Dublin and across
Ireland, will tell you they have not seen
any change.
Gardaí need to be trained and resourced to
tackle this problem.
Gardaí cannot safely intervene if
a danger to the public, but
also a danger to the gardaí if they have
not received the proper training.
We have been telling
from this side of the House for years, for
decades, that there has been a problem
with scramblers, yet it took the death of
a beautiful young girl for the Government
being reactive again to a
regulations in relation to e-scooters to
deal with the number of young people
suffering from acquired brain injuries but
it was another reactive response.
We have been telling the Government for a
long time that this has been a problem in
our communities.
What we heard
in the justice committee was shocking,
coming from the Garda itself.
It told us we will see an increase in the
number of people having scramblers and
e-scooters taken off them or being
prosecuted for either not wearing high-vis
clothing or a helmet.
It told us they are the people probably
using them in a legitimate way,
going to work or
for legitimate business.
They are the people who will feel the full
weight of this law because they might have
forgotten their helmet or high-vis.
This is because,
these people are compliant and law abiding
so if a garda asks them to stop, they
will, but the lads running amok in my
community and
others across Dublin using e-scoters for
drug dealing or intimidation will not
stop; they
flee.
The
a priority to get gardaí trained.
We heard at the justice committee this
week -
that by the end of this year, despite the
urgency,
only six gardaí will have
proper training.
in the news this week involved a
high-profile English football player who
was arrested for dangerous driving and
possession of nitrous oxide.
I have raised this before.
I have heard anecdotally from people
contacting me that
this is an issue in our areas.
Young people have been seen driving around
with balloons, which contain nitrous
oxide.
It is a dangerous situation.
Anybody doing this is reckless and they
need to stop.
I said at the time we need to bring in
roadside testing for nitrous oxide
so if someone is under the influence of
nitrous oxide, a roadside test
That
might deter people from taking nitrous
oxide and driving.
a
situation where we name another law after
another fatality.
We have a chance to bring in this testing.
I
to have a look at that.
the opportunity
to debate this Bill on Second Stage.
I look forward to tabling amendments on
future Stages.
Any debate such as this is always
emotional because we often think of
somebody we know who has been hurt or
whose life has been prematurely lost
enforcement are in place to ensure our
safety on the roads.
This is a welcome step but as the Minister
of State accepted in his opening remarks,
no one law or
policy will be robust enough to ensure our
roads
I place no personal blame on anybody for
this but it is intriguing that while we
are, in comparison with our EU colleagues,
quite below
the average as regards road fatalities,
as a youth worker and a dad of young
people considering entering the roads
as drivers,
that
age cohort of 16 to 25
we are disproportionately represented in
fatalities.
Our policy,
training response and legislative response
need to be evidence based
that in mind.
Over the summer, I launched the idea of a
driver theory test
programme that would really look at that
evidence and robustly engage with the next
generation of road
users, whether drivers, cyclists,
e-scooter users or pedestrians.
For a very small sum of annual funding -
it is fully costed at
about €5.5 million -
50 development officers
the RSA and sent out to schools to give
a universal driver and road user training
programme that would culminate
in a fully funded driver theory test.
We all know in this Chamber that to take
control of a vehicle of any type
is to take control of a significant
weapon, yet what we have seen in
cultural norms and behaviours that have
evolved online or in person is
sometimes reality and perception are very
different in that generation.
This initiative would provide universal
training in transition year or fifth year,
in youth services or youth clubs to ensure
young people can see, feel
and learn the realities of what it is to
be a road user behind the wheel of a car,
as a pedestrian or
cyclist.
and his officials to consider that as part
of budget 2027.
It already happens ad hoc.
I accept the RSA has a training programme
but we are relying on
teachers and gardaí in the community who
are already overburdened
with work and cannot do it robustly and
universally across the State.
This is an attempt to offer that.
As part of the legislation, the Minister
of State spoke about removing the need for
physical tax discs in
vehicles.
I have had a bone to pick with this
Government since I was elected a couple of
years ago.
I have always felt irked that I pay 13%
more each year for
my road tax if I do not have the funds to
pay for it annually versus
paying for it every three months.
That is punitive.
The costs are
representative of that punitive damage of
13%.
It is certainly not 13% more in
administrative costs to produce
the discs, send a reminder email or post
it out every three months.
The Government now has an opportunity and
offering something of a political win for
the Minister
If there are no more hard copies of tax
discs, that negates the need for any
discrepancy between the cost of taxing
your car every three months and doing so
every 12 months.
Only a certain cohort can pay upfront for
12 months.
A lot of people cannot.
We want people to continue taxing their
cars and paying the tax.
Let us do away with the 13% difference
because all that does is punish people who
cannot afford it.
I was a councillor for a few years before
I was elected to the Dáil.
I could never understand how the body
responsible for designing our roads never
had access to collision data.
I welcome that
part of the legislation.
It has the potential to ensure real-time
engineering solutions are
provided in hotspots or
legislative route, will the Minister of
Will there be a live interactive map
updated consistently?
Will there be certain thresholds of
collisions?
I will give the example
the R403 in Kildare.
It is probably the longest stretch of
straight road in the country.
I have yet to find someone who disagrees
with me.
It is about 10 miles long, possibly even
more and it is
At certain times of day, people are
driving into stark sunshine at sunrise or
sunset.
It is also collision-heavy at crossroads.
There have been tragedies along that road
very recently
and throughout the past decades.
That the council did not have access to
that information in a timely way to
bring in engineering solutions does not
make sense.
I welcome this measure but I ask for
further information as to how that
communication will be conveyed between the
and the local authority.
The Government has missed a trick in some
ways.
I
over the summer.
The Social Democrats had a different
proposal, which was to register
e-scooters.
People would have had to register those
vehicles in the same way as
a car or anything else.
We could still go a way towards doing that
as part of this review.
If
considering that, he has my full support
because it is as dangerous a weapon as
many of the other weapons we ask be
registered in the State.
That is another consideration.
I do not want to repeat the points already
made but I attach
myself to the sentiment that
with the best will in the world of all of
us here, including the Minister of State's
officials in the Department who put
together this strong legislation, proper
enforcement and education are needed.
The legislation is only one part of that
jigsaw.
I have put some proposals
before the Minister of State that I ask
him to consider.
Equally,
to convey that message on enforcement to
his colleagues in
Cabinet.
The gardaí we have are doing what they
can, but we can all agree that the bodies
on the ground are not there, the training
is not there and ultimately the back-up
from society is not there to support them
that when they need to intervene, we will
back them as opposed to them being
prosecuted for trying to get involved in
these incidents.
I look forward to
to this discussion further on Committee
Stage and commend
the work so far.
I also welcome the Bill.
It is important, as my colleague said, we
empower local authorities and the
RSA, to enhance their data-sharing
arrangements.
There are also other welcome aspects to
up where my colleague left off and speak
about my constituency.
There is a serious crisis with the
lack of enforcement.
We have met and engaged with the parents
of Grace Lynch,
Martin and Siobhán, and I still engage
with them on
ongoing basis.
What is clear from
them and constituents who contact me,
and from speaking to people living in
Ballymun and Finglas this week,
is that despite the introduction of
Grace's law,
things are as bad as ever.
One resident from Finglas I spoke to today
said
every time they leave the house, they
encounter a scrambler or a scrambler-type
e-bike travelling dangerously on the
roads, paths, green areas and parks.
Last week, while
on their way back from
Valley Park on the
road in front of the traffic from
Deanstown Avenue and onto the green
opposite.
The resident said it is intimidating and
people in their cars look fed up.
It is
unacceptable that this is still the case.
I met one of the assistant commissioners
in An Garda Síochána last week
who confirmed
there is an issue around the EU Presidency
with Garda resources being diverted away,
that it does not have sufficient resources
to implement and enforce and that is
frustrating.
It is accepted
that communities such as Ballymun and
Finglas
need high-visibility policing to enforce
these rules to ensure
the communities are safe
They also need youth diversion programmes
and support in that.
It is frustrating that the
issues of road safety in relation to
e-scooters and scramblers
in the community are as bad as ever and it
is not right.
It is not acceptable.
The concern is, as has been said, that
this involves more promises without
delivery.
Injuries continue to happen.
We have seen the figures from the
hospitals.
Grace Lynch's parents plead with us and
the Minister
to avoid another tragic death
but
We
need to see more action and resourcing
and, as my colleague, Deputy Farrelly, put
forward, the idea of registering
e-scooters seems
a sensible proposal.
We need action on that and we need
enforcement because every
community
has the right to be safe.
Tá sé tuillte ag gach pobal a bheith
sábháilte agus tá gá acu leis sin.
agus Fionnghlas chun é sin a
We need more gardaí on the ground to
enforce but they need training.
It is absolutely scandalous that only six
gardaí will receive
training before the end of the year.
That is absolutely not acceptable.
I will continue to push on this to ensure
gardaí have sufficient resources and are
trained and that our communities are safe.
We know e-scooters and scramblers are
being actively used in drug
dealing and intimidation by drug
and the most vulnerable disadvantaged
communities are bearing the brunt of that.
They have
a right to be safe as everyone else in the
country so we need to see serious action
on that.
statistic is a person, family and
community whose lives have been changed
forever.
That is why we have a responsibility to
ensure our laws, enforcement
systems and road infrastructure are as
effective as possible in preventing
collisions and reducing harm.
That is why I welcome the Bill.
While much of it is technical in nature,
its purpose is
It is about making our roads safer,
ensuring public bodies have access to
better information, modernising how key
road traffic systems operate and
strengthening the legal framework that
underpins many aspects of our road safety
policy.
One of the most important aspects of this
Bill is the provision allowing collision
data collected by An Garda Síochána to be
shared more effectively with local
authorities.
Too often we hear concerns from local
communities about dangerous stretches of
road, recurring collisions or persistent
safety issues.
Residents know there is a problem but
decisions can be delayed because the
necessary data are not readily available.
That is why provisions relating to speed
limits are
important.
Speed limits are among the most important
tools available to improve road safety
data.
They influence
the likelihood of a collision occurring
and the severity of its consequences when
it occurs.
The flexibility provided under this
legislation in speed limit implementation
is sensible.
However, these decisions must remain
firmly evidence-based and factors such as
road design, collision history, traffic
volumes, nearby development and the
presence of vulnerable road users must
continue to guide
When we discuss road safety, we cannot
focus exclusively on motorists,
pedestrians and cyclists.
Children travelling to school, older
people and people with disabilities also
have a right to use our roads safely.
For those road users, even relatively
small reductions in vehicle speed can make
a significant difference and that is why
ensuring speed limits are applied
appropriately and consistently remains
such an important part of our broader
road strategy.
While I am speaking about speed limits,
Minister of State will be aware, our local
authorities have been tasked with
examining local roads and implementing 30
km per hour
where appropriate.
I would very much like
to give an update to the House on its
status in each of the local authorities
and if he does not have up-to-date
information on the status,
to engage directly with local authorities
as I am hearing that there are some
difficulties with local authorities moving
that process forward.
We all want our roads to be safer.
Speed is a huge driver in that and it is
important we see
that process concluded as soon as
possible.
I also welcome the provisions relating to
dangerous and careless driving offences.
At present the situation can arise that a
jury does not consider the threshold for
dangerous driving has been met, but cannot
consider whether the evidence supports
conviction for careless driving.
That means we get outcomes that do not
accurately reflect the facts of a case.
Allowing a jury to return a verdict of the
lesser offence of careless driving, where
appropriate, is a common-sense reform and
I welcome it.
It will help ensure that accountability
better reflects the evidence presented
while maintaining the rights and
protections that are fundamental to our
justice system.
I also welcome the measures relating to
mobile camera van operators.
Requiring operators to attend court in
very routine cases is not always the best
use of limited resources.
At the same time, efficiency must never
come at the expense of fairness.
Where a genuine dispute exists, defendants
must continue to have the opportunity to
challenge evidence and to seek the
attendance of a witness.
It is important that public confidence in
road traffic enforcement is maintained
alongside any efficiency gains.
The national vehicle and driver file sits
at the centre of many of
systems that people interact with every
day, whether renewing a driver's licence,
taxing a vehicle or complying with road
traffic regulations.
Maintaining the accuracy, effectiveness
and legal robustness of that system is
essential.
I welcome the decision to remove the
requirement for a paper motor tax disc.
It is a sensible modernisation of a system
that has changed very little despite the
widespread digitalisation of our public
services.
Most motorists now expect to access
information and complete transactions
online.
I welcome that our legislation will
reflect that.
The key requirement
now that the electronic systems
underpinning all of this are reliable,
accurate and easy to access.
Gardaí, local authorities and members of
the public must be able to verify a
vehicle's status quickly and with
confidence.
We must also ensure that people who are
less comfortable using digital services
are not left behind as these changes are
I very much welcome the statutory basis
being provided for the Check My Vehicle
service.
This service gives members of the public
access to important information and helps
support transparency, compliance and
consumer
Modernisation of systems does not always
attract headlines but it can save people
time, improve their experience of
interacting with the State and reduce the
State's administrative costs.
As services continue to expand and evolve,
privacy considerations must remain to the
fore.
Public confidence in the State's digital
services depends on people knowing their
information is protected and that
sensitive personal details cannot be
disclosed.
Communities across the country want to see
tangible improvements in road safety.
They want safer junctions, safer routes to
schools, safer town centres and faster
action where risks are identified.
The measures contained in the Bill may
appear technical but their purpose is
anything but.
Better data sharing, more effective
enforcement, appropriate speed limits and
modernised public services all contribute
to one common objective - preventing
collisions and saving lives.
I share my colleagues' concerns in
relation to enforcement.
That is also a huge piece, as is training
and education, where
there is scope for improvement.
Ultimately, the steps we take with this
legislation and with regard to enforcement
and awareness and education campaigns will
all be measured by one statistic.
Is the number of road deaths and
pedestrian injuries caused by vehicles
falling?
I very much hope this legislation passes
swiftly through the House and that the
various sections are commenced as quickly
as possible.
As we deal with a largely technical Bill
related to various areas of Road Traffic
Acts, websites, databases and day-to-day
administration relating to driving, I
want to touch on something else that is
viewed by many as a glaring omission in
the delivery of policy
that I would say is an error in policy.
For many years, members of the diaspora
have been pointing out the administrative
burden associated with returning home to
Ireland.
Given that we are crying out for
healthcare professionals and that the
Department of Foreign Affairs
is actually advertising in Australia to
lure Irish people, including
construction workers, home, one could be
forgiven for thinking that this could be
a moment and an opportunity to be seized
to actually progress long-standing
recommendations to address the challenges
faced by returning Irish immigrants.
Unfortunately, for this Government, that
does not seem to be the case.
The
progress in obtaining reciprocal
agreements for
recognition and exchange of driving
licences between Ireland and other
countries and US states has been far too
slow.
I
commend those who have long campaigned on
this and on other diaspora issues,
especially Safe Home Ireland and the
Irish-US Driver's License
campaign group, the latter of which last
year published a report on this very
matter.
It brought forward proposals to allow for
the simplification of the process.
These warrant serious consideration.
That is why there has been so much
frustration at what is reported in the
diaspora media as a slap in the face
The crux of the issue lies in respect and
prioritisation.
On respect, to use the words of one
campaigner, "No reason is given,
no explanation made to those affected and
their families, who have and continue to
be impacted emotionally and financially by
an unintended consequence of what we
believe is just poorly worded
legislation."
On prioritisation, we see what
the Government is capable of when it
prioritises a matter.
When it prioritised this matter, the
programme for Government committed to
working on reciprocal arrangements with
countries with large diaspora populations.
It committed to prioritising such
arrangements as would benefit the
commercial sector.
I welcome the progress made with regard to
the commercial sector early this year but
my simple ask of
Government is to ascribe equal priority to
Irish citizens who wish
to return home to Ireland.
This is clear-cut.
Deputy Canney can either be a Minister
Patrick's Day jollies or he can be a real
friend to our brothers, sisters, sons
and daughters who live abroad and who want
to come home.
within his power to help alleviate the
administrative burden of returning home
if that is their wish.
I ask him to commit to making this a
priority for his Department and to
getting it done.
The Labour Party absolutely supports the
main thrust of this Bill, which is to
improve data sharing between the State
bodies responsible for road safety, that
is, An Garda Síochána, the RSA and our
local authorities.
At present, the information exists but the
people who need that information to make
our roads safer do not necessarily have
access to it.
That situation has been allowed to persist
for too long.
Nevertheless, I welcome the Bill being
introduced at Second Stage today.
If a person is seriously injured on a
road, if there is a collision at a
dangerous junction, if gardaí repeatedly
attend the same stretch of road or if
local residents have been reporting a
danger for years, that information should
not disappear into the database of one
public body and become inaccessible to
another.
It should be shared across the competent
and relevant authorities to inform what
happens next.
The purpose of road safety data is not
just to produce statistics; it is to
prevent the next collision from happening.
My Labour Party colleagues and I are very
supportive of the provisions in this Bill
that allow road authorities to request and
process collision data to identify and
assess safety risks to plan for road
maintenance, junction redesign and so on
and know where the resources need to be
targeted.
The Bill specifically provides that An
Garda Síochána or another public authority
may disclose collision data to a road
authority or nominated local authority for
those purposes.
It also provides safeguards around the
processing of personal data.
all very welcome but we have to ask why it
has taken this long.
We have known for years that
a problem with the fragmentation of road
safety data.
Road safety campaigners have been banging
this drum for a long time.
In a previous debate on road safety in
this House, I spoke about the frustration
but who cannot always access the data
necessary to understand the full picture.
I know of several in my constituency and I
am sure my constituency colleagues would
point
to the exact same spots.
The issue is pretty straightforward.
A local authority cannot properly redesign
a dangerous road if it
have information about what is actually
happening on that road.
It cannot always accurately identify black
spots or junctions that are particularly
dangerous for vulnerable road users like
pedestrians or cyclists.
It basically cannot identify patterns
because the information is sitting in a
different organisation.
why this part of the
is really important.
We should be moving toward a system where
collision information is routinely used to
identify locations of interest, where
local authorities are able to intervene
Fatalities are the most visible part of
the road safety crisis but we also need to
look at serious injuries that are
happening on our roads.
My colleague and the Labour Party's health
spokesperson, Deputy Marie Sherlock, has
done some important work in this area.
There is a gap between Garda collision
statistics and hospital data.
Thousands of people are hospitalised
following road collisions whose injuries
are not necessarily reflected in the same
way in the national collision statistics.
What this means is that,
again, we risk making decisions based on
an incomplete picture.
This also needs to be addressed.
If a person is seriously injured because
of the way our road system is designed,
that information should be available to
help us make the system safer.
In May, the RSA published an interactive
map of road traffic injury collisions
covering fatal, serious and minor injury
collisions between 2016 and 2024.
This is a really useful step towards
transparency and evidence-based decision
making.
However, that information has to lead to
action.
We need local authorities to have the
power, the resources and the obligation to
act when the evidence tells us that a road
is dangerous.
brings me to the wider context of this
Bill.
Road traffic legislation is not merely an
administrative exercise.
Ireland is in the middle of a road safety
crisis and I do not think any of us are
being hyperbolic when we say that.
The RSA figures tell us that very clearly.
There has been enormous progress over the
longer term; we should acknowledge that.
Ireland has gone from hundreds of road
deaths a year to figures that, for a
period, were among the best in Europe.
That progress is not something we should
take for granted, but I fear that the eye
has been taken off the ball.
The RSA's long-term figures show a rise in
road deaths from 134 in 2018 to
185 in 2025.
The Garda figures report 190 deaths in
2025 as they include deaths in public
places such as car parks and private
roads.
The Bill does not address this but we also
need to clarify which are the more
accurate figures when it comes to deaths
as a result of cars.
I would argue that the Garda figures are
more complete in that regard but that is a
discussion for another day.
Tragically, regardless of whose figures we
use - those of the Garda or the RSA - the
trend of increasing fatalities shows no
signs of reversing this year.
At the end of July, 105 people had already
lost their lives on Irish roads, or 13
more than
the same point in 2025.
More than 40% of fatalities occurred on
Saturdays and Sundays.
The RSA reports that 57% of fatalities
occurred on roads
27% of those killed were aged between 16
and 25.
Every one of these road fatalities and
every life lost will have left devastation
in its wake for the thousands of people
grieving the loss of their loved one.
We have all seen the consequences in our
communities.
In February, a man in his 80s, Frank Daly,
was killed when a Bus Éireann
double-decker bus struck pedestrians not
far from here on North Earl Street.
Three other people were taken to hospital.
In June, a man in his 30s died following a
three-car collision on the M21 between
Abbeyfeale and Newcastle West.
His death brought the number of people
killed on Irish roads at that point in the
year to 75, six higher than
the previous year.
In July, three men were killed in separate
collisions in Donegal, Cork and Kildare in
the space of a single day.
In August, we witnessed an absolutely
devastating collision on the M9 in
Kildare, where five teenagers lost their
lives in a head-on collision after a car
Four other people, a family including a
child who were on their way to Dublin
Airport to go on holiday, were seriously
injured.
I am so glad to
an update from
three sisters yesterday to say they are
getting stronger each day, and I wish them
the very best as they continue their
recovery.
These sorts of devastating events stay
with communities.
They stay with the emergency workers who
respond to them - the gardaí and anyone
who happens to witness them - and above
all, they stay with the families who are
impacted by them.
The barometer against which we have to
measure every piece of road traffic
legislation, such as this one, is whether
it will make our roads safer.
On the data-sharing element of this, I am
confident this Bill will do that.
On the speed limits element, though, which
comes under Part 5 of the Bill, I cannot
say I am quite as convinced.
In fact, I find this part of the Bill a
little
Section 21 provides for local authorities
to be able to continue to set a special
speed limit of 60 km/h for local roads in
built-up areas.
The Minister will be aware there is a
long-standing campaign, with many
different advocacy groups calling for a
default urban speed limit of 30 km/h.
I support this campaign.
At the very least, the sensible approach
would be to standardise urban road speed
limits.
At present, a road
different area, it would be 50 km/h.
It creates ambiguity, and when it comes to
road safety and the rules of the road,
ambiguity poses a genuine danger.
It also sends the wrong message about
allowing higher speeds in built-up areas.
Drivers could legitimately ask why
okay for one road to
but another
in very similar areas.
They may be tempted to put the foot down a
little bit more as a result, seeing a sort
of unfairness there.
My clear position is that we should be
reducing urban speed limits to 30 km/h.
It is increasingly becoming the
international norm.
It is also the policy direction that this
State has already legislated for.
The Road Traffic Act 2024 provided for
a
was hardly dry on that Act,
before the Government started to roll back
on it.
I have tabled a number of parliamentary
questions to try to ascertain why the
Government was effectively moving away
from the national default approach and
instead instructing local authorities to
introduce 30 km/h speed limits through
special speed limit zones.
I have never really received a
satisfactory response.
Generally, all I get is that
too difficult.
Once again,
not good enough.
The question should not be about whether
moving from 50 km/h to 30 km/h speed
limits in built-up areas is difficult or
not.
It should be about whether it would save
lives and prevent serious injuries.
The relationship between speed and the
severity of pedestrian collisions is well
established.
Around 5% of pedestrians would be killed
at an impact speed of 30 km/h, compared
with approximately 50% at 60 km/h and 90%
at 80 km/h.
There is an extraordinary difference
there.
At 30 km/h, we give someone a fighting
chance.
At higher speeds, the consequences of a
mistake become drastically, dramatically
Speed limits are not about how we get
drivers from A to B most efficiently.
They are about what happens when something
goes wrong, like a child running out onto
a road, a cyclist falling off their bike
in the middle of traffic or a driver
We cannot build a road system around the
assumption that everyone will behave
Our road system should be designed so that
those mistakes do not automatically become
fatal or risk life-changing injuries for
those
The case for reducing urban speed limits
to 30 km/h is clear, based on the evidence
from places where this has been done.
Wales, for
built-up areas in September 2023.
Early evidence showed average speeds
falling by around 4 miles per hour on a
sample of main roads.
In 2024, casualties on roads in Wales with
20 miles per hour and 30 miles per hour
limits combined were almost 20% lower than
the year before.
It is a relatively short period of data
but the direction of travel is
encouraging.
It is certainly a lot better than the
direction we have been heading in for some
time now here.
The Welsh Government has also estimated
that the introduction of 20 miles per hour
limits could prevent deaths and serious
injuries while delivering wider economic
and public health benefits.
We can also look to Spain.
They introduced a nationwide urban 30 km/h
limit on streets with a single lane in
each direction in 2021.
Urban road deaths fell by 20% in 2021
compared with 2019.
Their directorate general for traffic
specifically linked the reduction to a
package of urban road safety measures,
including
30 km/h limit.
Pedestrian deaths fell by 26%, cyclist
deaths by 34% and deaths among people over
64 by 31%.
Five years on, Spain continues to see a
positive trend, with urban fatalities in
2024 5% below 2019 levels, while cyclist
fatalities in cities were almost 19%
lower and pedestrian fatalities more than
16% lower.
The case for reducing urban speed limits
as a default is not theoretical.
This is what happens when governments
decide that speed in urban areas should be
designed around the safety of humans
rather than the convenience of the fastest
possible journey.
I pay particular tribute to the Love 30
campaign group, which has been to the fore
particularly in town centres, residential
areas and around schools and places of
public assembly.
I had the pleasure of hosting Love 30 here
in Leinster House for an audiovisual room
briefing on the campaign, alongside other
organisations including the Dublin
the Irish Road Victims Association and
community groups from around the country,
Whether it is pedestrians, cyclists,
children on their way to school, older
people going to do their shopping, people
with disabilities navigating pavements and
crossings, commuters waiting for a bus or
teenagers hanging out with friends, we
have to design our roads and institute a
road safety system for all of these
people.
We also have to keep an eye on
enforcement.
the other side of this debate.
A speed limit that
enforced is just a number on a sign.
There was a 23% increase in motorists
caught speeding last year.
I
know if we have got better in terms of
enforcement or if just more people are
speeding; I suspect the latter.
We need to take a holistic approach to
enforcement.
The obvious place to look is the decline
in the number of gardaí involved in roads
We have the authorities, the strategies,
the targets, the awareness campaigns and
announcements but the gardaí tasked with
enforcing the law on our roads are being
asked to do more and more with too few
resources.
In May 2024, we were promised an
additional 150 gardaí specifically for
roads policing by 2025.
We got 15.
If we go back further, the picture is even
worse.
There are almost 400 fewer gardaí working
in roads policing today than in 2009,
while there are more than half a million
more cars on Irish roads.
I do not believe the roads policing
position will get any better this year
given the increased demands on our gardaí
due to the hosting of the EU Presidency
and the circus around Donald Trump at the
Irish Open last week.
Enforcement has become so much more
difficult as a result and the odds of
being caught for those who break the rules
of the road are increasingly in their
favour.
Driver behaviour naturally adapts to this
new reality.
We have also been incredibly slow at
rolling out stationary speed cameras and
traffic light cameras.
I was very pleased to see Deputy
Moynihan raising this with the Taoiseach
yesterday; maybe he listened to him.
It beggars belief that we still only have
nine fixed speed camera sites in the
country.
Road design should also form part of the
overall enforcement strategy from a
proactive preventative perspective.
I hope that the data-sharing element of
this Bill will have a positive impact in
that regard.
We need to redesign the dangerous
locations identified through collision
data and crucially we need to give local
authorities the resources to do so.
The Government's own road safety strategy
has a target of reducing road deaths and
serious injuries by 50% by 2030.
The baseline for that was 144 deaths per
year and a target of 72 or fewer and yet
we recorded 185 deaths on public roads
last year.
We cannot look at these figures and
conclude that the current approach is
working; much more needs to be done.
I want to briefly touch on the RSA given
its role as a competent authority when it
comes to road safety.
The Minister
will know that I have my concerns about
the apparent rollback in the Government's
commitment to reform the RSA and split it
into two separate bodies as recommended in
the 2024 Indecon report.
As I have said on many occasions, there is
an inherent conflict at the heart of the
RSA in that
both poacher and gamekeeper when it comes
to vehicles on our roads.
On the one hand it is tasked with making
our roads safer and sometimes that can
mean fewer cars on the road but on the
other it is incentivised to keep adding
more and more cars onto the road because
it administers and is funded through
driving tests and the NCT.
Those functions need to be split.
Let one body deal with driving tests and
another deal exclusively with road safety.
I support the concept of an independent
commission for safety with real powers to
intervene and to take politics out of our
decisions on road safety.
Whatever model it takes we need a much
more active authority in the road safety
space.
South Dublin County Council recently ran a
consultation on proposals to install large
digital advertising boards in various
locations around the county.
It was really welcome to see the RSA make
a submission detailing the potential
hazards that these huge electronic
billboards would cause in terms of driver
distraction.
At the same
South Dublin County Council and local
authorities all over the country
but the RSA has not given any comment to
my knowledge on any of those speed limit
reviews.
That is exactly an area where the RSA
should be using its expertise and
experience, and advocating for what it
thinks is the safest thing for
our roads.
We need a much more active authority, an
authority that will work with local
the Bill
represents a positive step.
I have spoken about the data-sharing piece
but the provision around multi-offence
incidents which were introduced in the
Road Traffic Act
is also a move in the right direction, as
is the provision concerning careless
driving which as the explanatory note to
the Bill states arose from the
report on the tragic death of Shane
O'Farrell.
However, the Bill could have gone further
particularly with respect to the speed
limit issue.
I want to see
evidence lead us
the right decision on this.
We should not use 60 km/h as a convenient
compromise simply because
already familiar.
If a road is genuinely a major arterial
route, we can assess it on its merits but
in built-up areas the starting point
should be 30 km/h.
That is what the evidence tells us will
prevent collisions and fatalities.
If an exceptional road needs to be treated
differently, there should be a process for
that exception.
That is a much better system than
beginning with a higher speed and asking
communities to fight their way down to
something safer.
The principle should be the opposite:
start with safety then justify any
departure from that.
We cannot legislate our way out of every
collision but we can design a system that
makes collisions less likely and makes the
inevitable human mistake less likely to
result in death or serious injury.
I welcome the Bill insofar as it finally
recognises that road safety depends on
information being shared between the
organisations responsible for our roads.
Local authorities, the Garda and the RSA
all
on the same page and working from the same
evidence in terms of black spots and what
needs attention.
I sincerely hope that will have a positive
effect.
on the speed limits.
We should start with a default 30 km/h
limit for
built-up areas.
We know that lower speed limits save lives
and prevent life-changing injuries.
The case has already been made by Wales
and Spain, and the Road Traffic Act has
already pointed us in that direction.
I urge the Minister
not to roll back
on what was legislated for in that Act.
I welcome the opportunity to speak on this
Bill.
Road safety is incredibly important and
too many of the important indicators are
going in the wrong direction.
In Meath, for example, people are telling
me the same thing again and again, and I
know it myself: you never see a roads
policing unit.
Motorists can go for months or more likely
years without encountering
a Garda checkpoint or traffic control.
That absence has consequences.
When there is no fear of getting caught,
dangerous driving becomes normalised.
Behaviours such as speeding, mobile phone
use, dangerous overtaking, and drink and
drug driving
thrive in the vacuum left by declining
enforcement.
The road safety experts are clear, as I
heard when I was a member of the
transport committee.
Visible enforcement is one of the most
effective deterrents we have and the
Government has failed to resource it.
the state of our roads.
Across Meath, motorists are navigating
broken and deteriorating surfaces,
dangerous junctions, inadequate signage
and long-standing black spots.
Rural communities in particular carry a
disproportionate burden of serious and
fatal collisions yet they are expected to
live with roads that are themselves a
hazard.
The road maintenance backlog is growing.
Local authority funding is stretched
beyond breaking point and this Bill does
not address any of it.
There is not one measure to fix a
dangerous junction and not one euro for
road repairs.
Where is the alternative?
For too many people in Meath there simply
is not one.
We have a complete lack of appropriate,
sufficient and working public transport.
Towns, including very large towns and
villages, are left without reliable bus or
rail connections, forcing people into cars
often on roads that are neither safe nor
fit for purpose.
We cannot talk to people about road safety
while offering them no viable
way to leave the car at home.
While I welcome a number of the sensible
and long-awaited provisions of this Bill,
we have to look at the issue of
enforcement.
We need more roads police and roads
policing.
We need greater funding for roads
maintenance and repair.
Systems, of course, should talk to each
other, and that is welcome.
Of course, personal responsibility is
hugely important in all of this.
Some of the issues I have mentioned do not
fall under
remit but I would ask him to work with
ministerial colleagues, particularly in
justice, on these areas.
Another area that
needs direct attention.
As my party's spokesperson on education, I
want to talk
at schools.
When I was my party's spokesperson on
transport, the safe routes to school
programme was introduced.
While it is excellent and very welcome, it
is too slow and it is underfunded.
Different schools have different
approaches.
Too many schools are left without
important, and I would say
Dealing with local authorities is
infuriating.
There appear to be huge discretion and
flexibility but
no rhyme or reason when going from school
to school.
One school has huge intervention, while
another school in a similar or even worse
setting has nothing at all.
The local authority, in my experience,
defends that position and contradiction.
It makes no sense to me.
We need guidelines and design handbooks
for traffic calming at schools and we need
a comprehensive plan for every single
school.
This, along with some of the measures
I will say at the outset that it is good
we finally have this Bill before the
House.
We have been waiting for it for a while
now.
A number of its provisions represent real
common-sense reforms.
They look at the modernisation of the
national vehicle and driver file, the
removal of outdated paper motor tax discs,
improvements to collision
data sharing, which
speak more about, and measures designed to
strengthen road safety enforcement and
planning.
These are all positive, but we have to
understand this Bill is coming forward in
the context of wider road safety issues
and
the real carnage that is taking place on
our roads at the moment.
190 people killed on our roads last year
and,
according to
Síochána, 134 already killed in 2026.
Many of these deaths
Everything we do in this Bill and
everything we do in the Oireachtas
transport committee has to be with a view
to getting us closer to the objective of
Vision Zero, which is eliminating
The Green Party
have continually highlighted the need for
stronger and more focused road safety
responses, including better enforcement,
safer road design and improved collision
analysis.
I might come back to enforcement at the
end.
One of the strongest elements in the Bill
the Minister of State has brought forward
today is the provision allowing local
authorities to access and process
For too long, local authorities have been
restricted in their ability to analyse
identify dangerous locations in their road
network.
The ability to access this information
will enable evidence-based interventions,
better targeting of safety investments and
earlier identification of high-risk
locations.
At the moment, when the RSA and An Garda
Síochána go through their analysis of
collisions in an area, let us say in my
home area, they might say there is a bad
bend
in Blanchardstown and there have been six
crashes there over the past three years,
but because of GDPR right now they cannot
convey that information to
the local
While the Bill creates the legal basis to
share collision data, it does not require
systematic collision analysis, a
publication of findings or safety action
plans arising from that data.
As this Bill goes through,
sharing being brought through, which is
valuable, being supplemented with regular
reporting on collision hot spots,
publication of anonymised datasets, and
the integration with the Vision Zero
targets and commitments that identified
high-risk locations receiving funding
priority.
There is no point in Fingal being able to
say, "Yes, there is a really dangerous
bend in Blanchardstown", if it does not
have the money to actually do something
about it.
We have to have joined-up thinking here.
We are solving one problem here but more
has to flow from that.
The Green Party has been a consistent
supporter of more appropriate speed limits
because we know, and we have heard this at
the transport committee from experts who
have come in, that speed remains one of
the principal factors determining both
collision risk and collision severity.
This Bill allows local authorities and
Transport Infrastructure Ireland to set 60
km/h limits on certain roads in built-up
areas and provides additional flexibility
regarding national roads.
There is a potential risk that the
legislation as it is currently drafted
could be interpreted as creating
opportunities for higher speeds in
urbanised areas at a time when national
policy is and should be moving us towards
lower speeds and a safe systems approach.
Will the Minister of State give an
assurance that these
will not undermine the intent of the 30 km
built-up area policy
and the wider speed review?
If that assurance cannot be given, I will
struggle to support this Bill,
notwithstanding the other positive
elements I see within it.
The abolition of the paper motor tax disc
is overdue
and is something I welcome.
As we know, the Garda is now relying on
automatic number plate recognition systems
and access to digital databases.
The paper disc requirement does not serve
any meaningful enforcement purpose any
more and removing unnecessary bureaucracy
while retaining enforcement capacity is
good public administration.
The expansion of the level of information
available through the check my vehicle
service for consumer protection is a
positive step.
Providing greater information on things
like tax status, roadworthiness
certification and vehicle characteristics
will assist buyers in the second-hand
market and may help combat vehicle fraud
and cloning.
However, I should emphasise the data
protection safeguards must remain robust
and GDPR compliance must be fully
maintained as the database functions
expand.
Beyond the items currently in the Bill, I
argue that the Government should move more
quickly on additional road safety
measures.
I will highlight a few of these.
The implementation of the national safety
camera strategy took a long time to be
published.
It is
published but when we asked
NTA and others about it at the transport
committee,
there was
real lack of clarity on when
were going to see outputs.
I think only one meeting of the oversight
body has taken place so far - maybe it is
two at this stage - but how are we going
to see this delivered?
How are we going to see in our local
authorities those red
cameras that would provide such benefit in
catching motorists who are breaking
red lights and are dangerous to cyclists,
pedestrians and other motorists?
Camera enforcement of mobile phone and
seat belt offences, stronger road safety
governance and the reform of the RSA have
also been spoken about before.
No doubt,
come back to our difference of opinion on
that again.
It is also about improving regulation of
dangerous vehicle use, including
scramblers and
The Bill to date contains a range of
practical reforms that will modernise
transport administration and strengthen
aspects of road safety policy, but we
should also recognise that legislation of
this kind must form part of a wider
commitment to Vision Zero.
Every death and serious injury on our
roads is preventable.
I passionately believe these deaths are
preventable.
The objective has to be not just the
removal of outdated, bureaucratic
processes or the simplification and
opening up of databases but actually
saving lives.
That is what we have to be about here.
In this regard, there is so much more to
do.
The issue of enforcement is not directly
within the Minister of State's remit but I
am sure he has seen the discussion about
the number of gardaí available for roads
policing.
This has been in the media in the past
week.
Commissioner Kelly came into the transport
committee in the last sitting at the end
There are 660 gardaí assigned to roads
policing right now.
The Commissioner emphasised it is the
largest stand-alone unit within An Garda
Síochána but it is also significantly
smaller than it was - 40% smaller
than it was 15 years ago.
We have a new Commissioner, whom I asked
if growing the number of gardaí in roads
policing
one of his objectives, to which he said it
was not.
In fairness to him, he made the point he
believes
there could be more efficiencies and more
done among the 660.
However, I want to put it on record that I
do not believe that 660 gardaí on roads
policing is enough, not when we had 190
people dead on our roads last year and
134 dead this year.
there were two pieces of agreement that
every organisation that came before the
transport committee in the past six months
on the topic of road safety outlined to
us.
The first was
the RSA was not fit for purpose, which we
have spoken about before.
The second was
enforcement was the key, but we are not
seeing adequate enforcement.
I understand in the Minister of State's
role of overseeing road safety that he has
regular engagement with his own senior
Minister and the Minister for justice.
I ask that he take the message of
enforcement back.
I welcome what the Commissioner said in
terms of his approach to road safety on a
general basis, but I do not believe we
have enough gardaí focused on this crucial
part of their role.
I call on
to be an advocate to the Department of
justice to get more gardaí on our roads
a
a lot in this.
It is a timely update of many of the rules
around
driver and vehicle licensing.
I might touch on a few points of the Bill.
The first relates to
check my vehicle facility
provided for in section 7 of Part 2.
to make that information available
publicly.
Somebody who works in my office bought a
second-hand car recently and used the
private vehicle checking websites, which
cleared the vehicle.
He subsequently found out there was a
problem with the vehicle.
If we make this information publicly
available, as is provided for in the Bill,
we avoid the possibility of private rogue
traders essentially circumventing the
information that consumers think
getting about a car they are buying, and
avoid the situation where they buy
something and do not realise there may be
a history that makes it questionable.
Things like that are steps forward and
progress that is necessary.
the paper disc, the Roads Act 1920
established the requirement to have a tax
disc on the car.
That is a long time ago.
It is over 100 years since 1920 when that
was put in place.
The reality is
we must be ready to move beyond paper
discs on windscreens to establish whether
car tax has been paid or not.
My understanding, and
open to contradiction in this regard, is
that gardaí already have the power to
check whether car tax is paid up to date
or not.
The slightly ridiculous thing is section
69 of the Road Traffic Act which provides
for the requirement to display the disc
and makes it an offence not to display the
disc.
It is preposterous that somebody could in
theory be prosecuted for failing to
display a disc when the car might be taxed
already.
Let us move with the times and move to a
stage where gardaí can check through their
automatic number plate recognition
systems, which they are already using in
relation to insurance and other things,
that include road tax.
I welcome the notion that we do not have
to go through the
putting the tax
on the window.
There are times when vehicle discs get
damaged, or maybe a window leaks,
and getting replacements for them is an
additional charge on consumers.
I welcome those provisions regarding road
traffic discs
As I said, this is a large Bill.
Part 5 deals with special speed limits.
I would like to sound a note of caution in
this regard.
We have on the M50 this rolling speed
limit, which changes according to the
weather conditions, the volume of traffic
and so
The standard speed limit on the M50 around
Dublin is 100 km/h.
It may increase when you get to the south
or onto the M1.
That 100 km/h speed limit is variable,
with signs sometimes telling people that
or 60 km/h.
In theory that sounds like a good idea.
If
a particularly cold day when there might
be black ice or frost, or a particularly
wet day or there could be substantial
traffic, I see the rationale behind it but
I will say two things.
Having a variable speed limit like that
which changes all the time creates a
difficulty for motorists.
They might be on a road they use all the
time
they might be familiar with the speed
limit, but now they have to keep an eye
out for what it is.
It can change from one part of the M50 to
another, which makes it difficult for
motorists.
Beyond that, there is a broader point.
Motorists need to take responsibility for
assessing themselves what the appropriate
speed to travel at is.
Of course we should have speed limits, but
we are allowing motorists to abdicate
responsibility for making the judgment
themselves that 80 km/h or 100 km/h on a
particular day or in particular
circumstances might be too fast.
I
think we need to do that.
We are much better off to trust people.
My experience with driving
weather or traffic conditions.
You will often find yourself on the M50
with an 80 km/h speed limit on a dry,
bright day when the traffic is relatively
light.
From everything I can see, there is no
need for it.
the special speed limits.
the broader issue regarding road tax, I
said I welcome the provisions relating to
the removal of the requirement for the
paper disc.
It is budget season.
I do not whether we will have a chance to
do it this year or not, but we should look
at the manner in which we tax cars
generally
because the system, again, has not changed
for a long time.
We put in place incentives for electric
vehicles.
That is as may be.
It is appropriate to incentivise that.
As we move more towards the more
cost-effective electric vehicles, and
while we move towards the target of having
more and more of them in the road, which
have benefits in a whole range of
different areas, is it the case that
going to create a taxation deficit
relating to road tax?
If every car on the road, for example,
benefits from a preferential tax rate, how
will we ring-fence money for the upkeep
and maintenance of roads and the safety
systems that go with roads?
The time has possibly come, even outside
the context of a budget, for a review of
how road tax is calculated and what the
appropriate amounts are to be.
In the context of the vehicle and
driver file, it would be remiss not to
mention the issue around driver testing
waiting lists.
This is an issue we have talked about in
and outside this House.
There remains an unacceptably long waiting
period for people who want to have
a driving test.
Young people going to college or getting a
new job that might require them to drive
now have to wait an unacceptably long time
to get their driving test to make them a
legitimate and fully qualified driver,
which means that progress
for young people, and there is a situation
where more and more people on the roads
are unqualified or not fully qualified to
drive.
They cannot use motorways, for example,
and there are other restrictions that
apply to them.
In my constituency, Dún Laoghaire, we have
the second-longest waiting list for
driving tests.
We waited a long time for the Sandyford
driving testing centre, which we were told
was going to be a pressure valve on those
waiting lists.
We now understand that is not going to
proceed because of some kind of
administrative difficulty I
need to go into.
Now the people of Dún Laoghaire are still
faced with long waiting lists.
Despite the Department having applied more
testers to that centre, there has not been
a commensurate decrease in the number of
people waiting or a commensurate increase
in the number of tests that are happening
on a weekly basis.
It is not okay for this to continue the
way it is.
We need to deal with this as a matter of
urgency.
We owe it to young people in particular,
and anybody who wants to get a
test, whether
a person who has come here to work and
needs to qualify to drive in this
jurisdiction or whoever it is.
They should not have to wait months and
years for driving tests.
That is unacceptable.
It needs to be addressed as a matter of
urgency.
I would be grateful
Minister of State were in a position to
address what pressure valve there might be
for
Laoghaire in the absence of the Sandyford
centre coming online.
What are the
answers to dealing with the waiting list
for driving tests?
Minister of State is well aware that
yesterday, Deputy Emer Currie and I
introduced a Private Members' Bill,
the road traffic (amendment) (Jax’s law)
Bill 2026.
Jax's law is a Bill that seeks to amend
sections 52 and 53 of the Road Traffic Act
1961, which are the provisions for
careless and dangerous driving.
At the moment,
careless and dangerous driving are dealt
with as minor road traffic matters in the
a
unless death or serious injury
caused as a result of that careless or
dangerous driving, in which case the
has the option to move that up in the rank
of offences and prosecute
the range of tariffs available to court to
penalise somebody for the consequences of
that careless or dangerous driving.
One of the things that is not recognised
by the Road Traffic Act, however, is a
serious harm that could be caused to
somebody by the loss of a pregnancy.
For example, Saoirse Aylward came to me
and Deputy Currie earlier this year.
She had been involved in a road traffic
accident in 2024 as a result of which her
baby, whose heartbeat she had heard and
who was to be named Jax, died essentially
in her womb.
She was seriously injured and the person
who was carelessly driving in that
instance was prosecuted in the Circuit
Court.
She suggested to us that if she had not
been seriously injured but was involved
in a road traffic accident, the impact of
which resulted in her losing the
pregnancy, there would have been no
recognition by the courts whatsoever.
One thing that Jax's law seeks to do is to
change that, so that the loss of a
pregnancy is recognised by the law as a
serious injury or as an injury significant
enough to escalate the offence from the
District Court to the Circuit Court.
I equally recognise the work that has been
done by Colleen Langan, whose aunt, Róisín
Connolly, née Langan, was killed in a car
accident in Monaghan in 2010.
I think she was 26 weeks pregnant; I may
have that wrong.
Her husband was driving.
They were hit by another driver.
She died as a result of that.
Her unborn child died as well.
From the time of her accident in 2010 to
the time of Saoirse Aylward's accident in
2024, nothing was done in this space.
We know that there is a lacuna in the law
there that needs to be repaired.
The Bill that we
brought forward will do that.
It does not change anything magnificent in
the law
it just creates a recognition of the fact
that a person involved in a road traffic
accident, whose pregnancy ends as a result
of that accident, has suffered a serious
injury.
It deserves recognition in the context of
how that offence is dealt with
subsequently in the court.
Colleen was here yesterday.
Saoirse and Nathan Murphy, Jax's parents,
were here as well.
They are hugely invested in this.
Also in the Bill is the idea that the Road
Safety Authority would begin to collect
accidents.
At the moment, inexplicably, they are not
recorded.
a pregnancy after a traffic accident.
That is a statistic we should have access
to.
Although they
enjoy personhood in the constitutional
sense, it does reflect a seriousness in
that accident that might not otherwise be
recorded.
The Bill also requires a provision that
the Road Safety Authority would collect
statistics in relation to lost pregnancies
as a result of road traffic accidents.
Why am I raising this?
This is a gold opportunity to
short-circuit the notion of our taking
that Bill through in Private Members'
time.
As a Government Member, I
have the same access to Private Members'
time that many TDs in this Chamber do.
We might ask it to be put into the lottery
on a Thursday.
The chances of it being reached for Second
Stage, Committee Stage and Report Stage
are very small.
A way we can circumvent that is for
to use this Bill as a vehicle to put Jax's
law on the Statute Book, to lift the
provisions, as we have drafted in that
Bill, and drop them into this section.
I will be presenting amendments on
Committee Stage to do that.
I note the Minister of State's supportive
nature in relation to the issues we have
raised.
I know he has spoken to the people
involved, Saoirse and Colleen.
I appreciate his engagement on the issue.
The best way to engage with it and to
deliver for those people is to allow this
Bill to be the vehicle to make Jax's law
real law.
fair to say that we all welcome any moves
in relation to
anything that streamlines or simplifies,
particularly when we talk about road
traffic,
whether it is from a point of view of
retention of information and sharing
information in relation to collisions or
anything that can lead to something that
is safer.
We have all seen the absolute slaughter on
our roads in recent times.
Unfortunately, we have had too many tragic
circumstances that are in the public
domain that we all unfortunately have to
comment on.
That does not compare to the families who
have been impacted,
beyond detrimentally, in many ways, never
to be put completely back together again.
Coming from Dundalk, it is no different
from anywhere else.
Everybody has seen the increase in
relation to the traffic.
We have seen all the issues,
anybody who has had to use the M1, M50 or
anything in recent times.
Even the port tunnel
at times
on the basis of the huge volume of traffic
and the fact that this leads
to, what
in most cases, minor collisions.
They are minor collisions that have an
impact in relation to the problem across
the board.
Yet we have all the issues in relation to
speeding.
We have the far worse issue in relation to
drug and drink driving.
Everybody can improve on the next issue,
myself included, in terms of ensuring
people are careful.
People spend far too long
playing with their phones, at times in
this Chamber
everywhere else in life, but it can be
far more detrimental when people are
paying far too much attention to phones in
cars where they can impact on themselves
and many others on the road.
That is something that we
have to look at.
I will follow up on what Deputy O'Rourke
said.
In fairness, I
know how many of us have been knocking on
doors and talking to many communities,
particularly those involved with schools.
We have not always seen a consistency in
relation to traffic calming.
I could probably name multiple places.
I think of the likes of Sheelagh in north
Louth.
I can also think of one that
hopefully, happening this year beside
Pearse Park in Dundalk.
We need to make sure
more of these
It makes sense that we would streamline
the process, that it would happen faster
and that we would see
a template of best practice operated
everywhere it possibly can.
We
Dundalk was stopped on one.
There was also the tragic case of Grace
Lynch and injuries to many others, both
locally and across the State.
There is an issue in relation to
scramblers.
We need to make sure that we have
fit-for-purpose legislation and whatever
requirements are needed.
We know the issue that An Garda Síochána
talks about in relation to training.
I know it is not always suitable
in relation to following and chasing in
dangerous circumstances.
We have also had the issue of those acting
illegally
and travelling the wrong way on motorways.
A community worker has come to me and I
would like to speak to the Minister of
State about it afterwards.
This would have happened in my own
locality.
Between
hard policing combined with youth workers
who would have engaged directly with young
people brought some of this happening to a
stop.
It is something he believes can be
delivered across the board.
I would like to raise another issue.
Paul Brady from Drive Virtual Driving
Academy has highlighted
the use of simulators.
The Minister of State spoke about it
himself.
He had engaged with the RSA, many
politicians and many Government
representatives.
A process
in play,
the possibility of using this.
It seems to have stalled.
He and
will be requesting some engagement from
the Minister of State in relation to it.
Those are two particular issues I will be
bringing up with the
Before I start, I want to mention two
young people who have been killed on the
roads in Meath in the past few months.
Mia Lily Keogh O'Keeffe was a wonderful
young girl.
In her short life, she brought enormous
happiness and love to her friends and
family.
She was gifted, creative and engaging with
all who knew her.
Her life was stolen from her.
She was struck while walking her dog on a
pedestrian crossing in Navan in February.
The driver fled the scene.
TJ McDonnell, from Bohermeen, County
Meath, was killed just a few weeks ago.
TJ was training for a cycling event with a
friend when he was hit by a van.
Here too, the driver fled the scene.
I
say anything more about the circumstances
of these accidents as
drivers are before the court but TJ was a
young man.
In his short life, he had done so much.
He touched the lives of so many people for
the better.
In both cases, their families, friends and
communities had been devastated.
The Minister of State knows this but a
parent burying a child is
a very difficult thing.
In both cases, those collisions should not
have happened.
Just two days ago, there was a fatal
collision on the M4 at Enfield, where a
man in his 30s was
Will the Minister of State consider
a minimum sentence for those involved in
hit and runs?
Sometimes this can be done to evade drink
or drugs being detected in the system.
I believe the penalty should be increased
so that
no incentive to do that.
Leaving a person dying on the side of a
road without treatment is despicable and
can also directly result in death.
There have been 134 deaths so far this
year on our roads and it is only
September.
In each of those cases, families are
Road deaths are nearly a fifth higher at
this point in 2026 than at the same period
last year.
Some experts are saying that
on course to surpass the 2010 high of 212
road deaths.
Statistics are saying that a
disproportionate number of young male
drivers are involved in road collisions,
on rural roads.
Young men in their 20s from Mayo and
Donegal are disproportionately
represented.
This is important because it also shows
that
is
leading to these deaths.
It gives me no pleasure to say that under
this
Government, road death figures are getting
worse.
We are an outlier in European terms
because
most of Europe, road deaths are falling.
The alarming trend whereby 27% of
deaths are among young people between the
ages of 16 and 25
is shocking.
important to remind people that road
safety is first and foremost a personal
responsibility.
Each one of us is directly responsible for
his or her behaviour on the roads and it
is important that people take that
responsibility in hand and drive in a safe
and controlled manner.
However, the truth is
roads are getting more dangerous and
not by accident that this is
Many towns and villages have little or no
traffic protections.
I can think of a dozen towns and villages
where cars and trucks rattle through at
speed on a daily basis.
In some communities, those protections are
only useful for those who
are already obeying the rules of the road.
This is important.
We need road protections
to protect
including people who are driving too fast
or under the influence.
Many towns and villages in Europe have
traffic calming measures at the entrance
of every single street or road entering
that town or village.
People are forced to slow down because of
ramps or chicanes.
That should be a
standard.
Every town and village should have a
default chicane or
ramp
point
is the absence of enforcement.
When Mia Lily Keogh O’Keeffe was born
there were 1,046 road traffic
gardaí on our roads.
When she was killed there were 638 road
traffic gardaí on the roads.
That action alone is the main reason
people are being killed in higher
numbers on the roads.
All the Bills the Minister of State or
anybody else brings through the House are
not worth a hill beans if there is not the
gardaí to enforce them.
I remember in the noughties people would
think twice about drinking and driving
because there was a reasonable chance of a
garda stopping them on the roads.
That behaviour changed radically because
people knew there was no reasonable chance
of their being stopped.
Without enforcement, people's
changes for the worse.
They break the rules of the road and
people get killed.
That 40% collapse in the number of gardaí
is the most important issue.
If it is not addressed, all the
Government's Bills will be meaningless.
That is
fact.
been breathalysed twice in the last 30
On both occasions, it occurred at 10.30
a.m.
on a Monday.
I know there are some people who
at weddings and late night events on a
Sunday night, etc., but a very small
cohort is still over the limit at 10.30
a.m.
compared with people travelling home late
at night on a Friday or Saturday.
It is easier to staff
checks at 10.30 on a Monday than it is in
the evening but it
is less effective and less useful for
saving lives.
the figures are incredible.
Even when gardaí catch people the courts
system is failing us.
a sevenfold increase in speeding
prosecutions in the nearest District
Court to me, Trim, but two thirds of those
did not proceed.
That is incredible.
I invite the Minister of State to guess
how many people
are not insured.
people driving
the roads today who are not insured or
registered.
When the Minister of State drives home to
Galway today he is likely to pass around
200 drivers coming in the other direction
who are not insured
situation whereby 20% of people put off
the roads do not have a driving
In 2024, 8,200 individuals who were to
receive penalty points did not
even have a licence and 23,000 people who
were disqualified never gave
their licence.
We are talking about the wild west in
terms of people ignoring
the rules of the road and the laws.
Unless we join the dots between
enforcement, deterrence and behavioural
change, we will never fix the end result,
namely, deaths on our roads.
We have light-touch enforcement in this
country.
I
address in his response.
He contacted the RSA in the week after the
M9 collision to convey his unhappiness
with the organisation due to its absence
in the aftermath of that accident.
A spokesperson for the RSA said it was not
in a position to give any information to
people about how to deal with people
driving down the wrong side of the road.
The Government's plan
to
the RSA but it has done a U-turn on that.
Why is that the case?
Another issue I have banged on about for
years in this Chamber is that gardaí do
not have the ability to pursue e-scooters,
scramblers and people driving down the
wrong side of the road.
When I
raised this it was like playing handball
against a haystack because no matter how
many times I raised it, nothing happened
on the Government side.
After the M9
the Government jumped into some level of
action but, believe it or not,
just six gardaí trained in pursuit
training by the end of this year.
If gardaí are unable to pursue people who
are breaking the law, we will not be able
to enforce the law.
If
take home today,
is enforcement.
However, to be honest, I believe there
will be fewer than 600 people policing our
roads in five years' time, unfortunately.
As an Opposition TD who tries to be
constructive, I broadly welcome the
National Vehicle and Driver File, Road
Traffic and Roads Bill 2026.
Many elements of it are welcome and will
bring driving regulations and monitoring
somewhat into the 21st century.
The decision to finally abolish the paper
motor tax discs is an important
measure.
For decades we forced motorists to have
this piece of paper on their windscreens
while the rest of society moved ahead with
digitalisation.
As such, moving to a digital system,
backed by an online verification portal,
makes a lot of sense, just as it did in
the UK perhaps 14 years ago.
I will mention the
issue of insurance discs in a while.
The introduction of open-ended non-use
declarations also makes sense, as it will
get rid of an unnecessary layer of
bureaucracy for thousands of vintage
people who fix cars and citizens who have
their car off the road for whatever
reason.
Removing some of the bureaucracy is very
welcome.
also welcome the legal framework to
finally resume the sharing of traffic
collision data between
Garda Síochána and local authorities.
This is crucial but has been unfortunately
delayed because councils cannot engineer
safer roads if they do not have full
information about where accidents are
occurring.
In this context, while the Bill is a
welcome step, this Government and its
predecessor have already failed the
broader test of dealing with the deadly
crisis unfolding on our roads.
As we all know, we are in the middle of a
devastating spike in road fatalities,
which are up significantly on
2025.
Depending on which figures
up 17% on last year and are rising at a
time when the European Union average is
falling.
That is shocking and concerning.
The crisis
the delay in delivering this Bill as an
example,
the previous Government allowed strict
GDPR limitations and interpretations to
legally block councils from getting
collision data since November 2023, even
though the Data Protection Commission
explicitly stated that GDPR should not
prevent proportionate publication of crash
location details, especially when the
technology exists to get rid of personal
identifiers by anonymising or
limiting the data.
The critics of this asked why the RSA
could not just itself strip
out names and addresses or pass on the
co-ordinates to council engineers.
I am wondering
It
meant that for three years local
authorities have been effectively
blindfolded.
I acknowledge there are patch jobs that
were put in, like the locations of
interest, so they got some statistics, but
one has to ask how many
accident black spots went unfixed while
this Bill was just dragging
this Bill brings in digital tracking
and makes things a lot easier, it is, as
other Deputies have said, very quiet on
the enforcement of the law.
It is great to have a database, but if we
have enough traffic corps members on the
roads to intercept dangerous drivers, it
will not work.
That is why, as I have said before, we
need a separate dedicated traffic police
whose members have specific powers in
relation to the roads and who do not even
have to be members of
Garda Síochána.
That is a model that works in other
countries.
The databases that we will improve on will
not breathalyse the drivers.
I take on board what Deputy Tóibín said
about being stopped and breathalysed at 10
in the morning.
I was breathalysed by a garda at 8 o'clock
I said, "You are on the ball."
He said that it was part of Drew's
measures and that they had to do that
before they clocked off.
To me, it makes more sense to try to catch
people when they are actually under the
influence.
We do not have new digital measures
stopping and seizing unroadworthy vehicles
when
actually on the road.
Yes, it can be traced back, but sometimes
you have to stop the people when
actually out there.
You nab them on the spot.
bugbear of mine is the person who drives
for a full kilometre in a bus lane.
The R136 in my constituency is a case in
point.
I have a lot of sympathy for people who,
if
turning towards a left lane, get into the
bus lane so as to avoid queuing.
They are not blocking any buses and not
blocking any traffic and are able to make
a turn, but how long is a piece of string?
I have seen people go along for the full
kilometre and then bump in front of
someone else.
That
irritates other drivers and is breaking
the law but it is increasing.
I have seen it anecdotally a lot more in
the past two or three years than I
in the previous ten.
I have had reports from constituents of
those idiots who break the pedestrian
lights in heavy traffic, not just when
going at speed but also when they are
going to work during school times, when
the traffic is busy.
They go through the lights and sometimes
push past the school traffic wardens as
well.
We need that physical element of policing.
We also have to look at the gaps that the
legislation fails to fill.
I again refer to Jax's law, which I was
happy to co-sign recently.
I
repeat everything Deputy Barry Ward, who
is proposing it along with Deputy Currie,
said earlier, but this legislation
highlights one of the important gaps in
our core road traffic framework, that
the law still fails to legally recognise
the loss of an unborn child caused by
dangerous driving.
If the Government is fully committed to
comprehensive reform, mechanisms to
address gaps like Jax's law could be
integrated into this legislation, as
The Department should do it rather than
waiting for Deputy Ward to put the
amendment in himself.
That would be better than having grieving
families campaigning on the margins,
hoping that
gets to Second Stage and other Stages
through other means.
If Jax's law could be added into the
wording, I would certainly support
amendments to that effect.
Earlier today, I mentioned the lack of
joined-up thinking in transport
and planning as regards buses, trains,
parking spaces and EV charging facilities
in new developments.
People are told they cannot have parking
spaces because they have this fantastic
public transport service,
so they have to drive but they have
nowhere to park.
People get frustrated because of this.
They get agitated.
They have been fighting with their
neighbour to try to get a parking space.
Now they are rushing out to get to a place
that you need to take three buses,
to get to.
We have to understand what is required in
new developments.
If
going forward, all speeds in new
developments should be 10 km/h - as
simple as that - not the 30 km/h and 10
km/h and then a crawl out of it allowing
people to move at normal speed, but
allowing people to actually park their
cars so their relatives can visit or they
can get to work.
At the moment we are just creating extra
aggression on the roads,
the last thing we need in terms of people
responding because if
someone does something untoward on the
road and
already agitated, you will get madder and
respond in a way that you would not
normally do.
We also need more work on graduated
penalties for repeat non-compliant
offenders
and issues like managing unregulated
e-scooters and e-bikes.
Again, that is about catching them rather
than some welcome legislation that we have
coming later this year in that regard.
Others have mentioned the quality of the
roads.
I second that.
Some of the roads are in very bad nick.
Again, I have a personal bugbear about
what seem to be very low speed limits
on dual carriageways.
I know traffic has to be managed,
including heavy traffic like
the M50, for example, where you cannot go
too fast or you will crash, especially in
the rain, but sometimes the speed limit on
good-quality roads seems to be quite low
and then
the regional roads it is way too high.
Some work, I have to acknowledge, has been
done on that, but we need more.
We need more in terms of training in
pursuit.
Deputy Tóibín mentioned the six gardaí who
will be trained by the end of this year.
That is too little too late in terms of
trying to catch people out and about
doing robberies and going up the wrong way
on dual carriageways, as we have
tragically seen recently.
On the insurance issue, I notice that the
Motor Insurers Bureau
of Ireland has information that can be
shared with the Garda in terms
of automatic numberplate recognition etc.,
but I would love to see insurance discs
gone as well as the motor tax discs on
cars.
There should be a way of working that,
maybe not in this legislation but soon.
Broadly, I welcome the Bill but we have to
put resourcing into enforcement as well.
thank the
Minister
for being here and introducing this Bill.
I will start by acknowledging the 134
deaths this year and the families
who have lost their loved ones.
I welcome the Bill.
There are a number of practical changes in
it that I support.
It removes the outdated requirement to
display a paper motor tax disc, reflecting
the fact that gardaí can now check tax
status electronically through automatic
numberplate recognition.
That is a great positive.
It strengthens Check My Vehicle, giving
people buying a second-hand car better
access to official information on a
vehicle's tax and roadworthiness status.
It allows local authorities to access
collision data so they can identify
dangerous locations and better target road
safety improvements.
This is critical to all our communities.
I think we have all been in positions
where we have flagged areas that are
potential black spots for accidents.
Anything we can do to join up all the
agencies involved in road safety
is a positive.
also allows mobile camera van operators to
provide certificate evidence rather than
routinely attending court.
I will speak about court efficiency later
but, obviously, that is
very much an improvement.
Importantly, it allows a jury to return a
verdict of careless driving where somebody
has been charged with dangerous driving
but the evidence supports the lesser
offence.
This reform arises from Mr.
Justice Haughton's report into the tragic
death of Shane
There is a significant gap in our road
traffic enforcement system that I want to
focus on today.
It will not be a surprise to
I thank him for his Department's
engagement with me on this issue.
It relates to court penalty points, which
I have raised with
before.
When a court imposes penalty points, we
should be able to say with certainty that
the sanction actually reaches that
driver's record, and at present we
cannot.
Today's debate is about the national
vehicle and driver file.
I know Deputies are coming to this debate
with road safety
in general
but I am trying to focus on the NVDF.
As the Minister of State knows, I have
been pushing the issue of recording court
penalty points since I started to engage
with Susan Gray of PARC Road Safety Group.
The figures for 2024 that the Department
worked on show that almost half of
court-issued penalty points were not fully
captured on the national vehicle and
driver file.
It is important to put those figures in
context.
They include Irish licence holders,
foreign licence holders and people who do
not hold a driving licence at all.
We know that
a certain number of court penalty points
are not going to get to the
NVDF.
At the same time, the Department's own
analysis found that 19%
of unmatched court penalty point offences
in 2024 and 2025 could have been matched
to an existing driver record and that
potentially represents about
1,500 penalty points per year.
This is particularly serious because the
NVDF is the database that
and motor insurers rely on to establish a
status.
The system works much better when an
offence is dealt with through fixed charge
notices because the driver number is
captured from the start.
The serious weakness arises when the cases
go through the courts.
and their driver number may not be
collected.
The Department and the RSA are
subsequently left with the task of trying
to match the driver numbers with the court
sanction,
to match it to the correct record.
This is particularly concerning because
penalty points are cumulative and a driver
I have had assurances from the Department
that those cases have been
identified and dealt with.
the fact that the Department's analysis
identified cases that could have been
matched in the area of penalty points
demonstrates why we need to fix the
underlying process.
This has to be about making the process as
effective and efficient as possible.
I raised this with the Minister at the
transport committee earlier in the year.
He also agreed that a fifth of potential
court penalty points not being applied was
unacceptable, and that the Department can
match cases after the event
and could continue to do so.
I would welcome the Minister of State's
feedback today as to whether that is
happening.
Susan Gray and I have also met with the
Courts Service and the Department of
Transport on this.
I welcome the commitment from the Courts
Service to work directly with An Garda
throughout the case.
I am looking for an update on that today
because this Bill gives us the opportunity
to clarify that process in court for
capturing driver numbers and ensure that
information follows the case to the NVDF.
First, we should capture the driver number
at the beginning of the process, carry it
through on the summons into court and then
onto the NVDF systems.
Second, if necessary, we should change the
law so that somebody
who has
been summonsed for a traffic offence must
produce their driving licence or learner
permit, and
that the courts staff have the authority
they need to capture that information.
Third, we should continue to examine
historical unmatched cases where the
information exists to identify the correct
driver.
There is another practical issue with the
NVDF that I want the Minister
Garda members carrying out roadside checks
should be able to access the driving
licence photograph held on the national
vehicle and driver file through their
Garda mobility devices.
This is something I have been raising for
quite a while, and we have
had feedback that it is being considered.
It would lead to more accuracy, which
is essential.
In the past there have been mismatches and
this would address that.
The NVDF contains an enormous of
information that can assist enforcement.
If a garda stops somebody at the roadside,
being able to verify not only the details
of the licence but also the photograph
associated with that licence would be
another useful tool in confirming the
person presenting themselves is the
I want to raise the future ownership of
the driver file itself.
There was a statement on 29 July
element of the NVDF will transfer from the
Department of Transport to the RSA.
The Department has said it is intended to
give the RSA end-to-end ownership
of driver-related systems and that it will
also include the new
offence management system being developed.
is not simply an administrative database.
It is a critical part of our road safety
enforcement infrastructure.
It is the brain of all the information we
retain on drivers, from
disqualifications to penalty points and
driver numbers.
Given the issues we have identified with
penalty points and the matching of
records, I am asking the Minister
to set out clearly why he is transferring
ownership to the RSA and why he believes
that is the right approach.
At the moment, I do not quite understand
the rationale.
We have to join the dots between An Garda
Síochána, the Courts Service, the
Department of Transport and the RSA.
Some information on that would be good.
In my remaining time I will speak to Jax's
law.
As the Minister
yesterday.
Saoirse Aylward was here, as were Jax's
father, Nathan, Colleen Langan, who
campaigns for her aunt Róisín,
and Susan Gray of PARC.
While Saoirse had been through a horrific
ordeal, she
said she had been retraumatised by the
justice system and felt that while she was
recognised as a victim, the loss of Jax
was not.
We are asking the Minister of State to
examine our legislation.
We think we have come up with a viable
solution.
as part of this Bill he could consider an
amendment
to address what we believe is a gap in the
law,
and
look at both recording and publishing the
data on
that loss of pregnancy in road victims
information.
I thank the Minister of State and know he
has put a lot of work into it.
It is about making the NVDF work harder,
better, more
effectively and more efficiently.
I hope
can take on board some of the ideas and
concerns I have presented
today.
One of the issues that constantly comes up
in my area and
across the State is the use of nitrous
oxide.
It is not a banned substance.
Residents ring in to say there is somebody
sitting in a car outside their house
taking nitrous oxide and driving off.
They contact the Garda and are told the
fact it is not a banned substance means
there is very little the Garda can do
about it.
This is happening on a regular basis.
The evidence
can
the side of the road, at parking spots, at
beauty spots and so on right across the
State.
Deputy Mark Ward and
I
have a Bill coming up.
We are hoping there might be something in
relation to that.
A couple of things are happening in the
community.
There are stolen cars.
I have been a victim myself.
My car was robbed
recently.
I was lying in bed when someone went
around using the fob.
It impacts on
communities.
I was away for a couple of days and got a
phone message from
a woman saying there was a stolen car in
her area.
It was 1.40 p.m.
For four days, there
stolen cars in that community.
I remember
trying to deal with this issue 20 or 25
years ago.
Many of us thought this was behind us but,
unfortunately, it is on the rise again.
Some of it is down to the new technology
as well.
Cars are
safe enough.
to
talk about scramblers.
I was driving along the quays opposite the
High Court and a guy
coming down with a balaclava on his head.
We had the incident of
this guy had a balaclava on and was on a
scrambler bike on one of the main
roads in Dublin
right across from the courts.
We are allowing this to happen in our
city.
That was on the quays but it is happening
in my area as well.
The
not doing enough.
We need to empower the gardaí.
It is probably a non-issue for the Bill
today but we all need to wake up in this
House to what is happening in our
communities.
Theft of cars is on the rise.
It is in many working-class communities
but not exclusively so.
They are robbing the cars from everywhere
and people have to deal with the financial
loss of that.
In many cases, it is older cars; it is the
car that brings the kids to school or the
car that brings people to shops.
We need to do more and look at new ways of
tackling these issues.
There are parts of this Bill I really
welcome, particularly moving towards
better digital records.
That is something I have continuously
pushed for in this House.
I congratulate the Minister of State and
the Department staff for all the work that
went into this.
However, it will be better if I say what I
like
and what I want to see improved - namely,
enforcement.
I spoke in this House yesterday about
supporting gardaí before they
become gardaí, while they are gardaí and
after they are gardaí.
We can do a lot better as a State.
I come from four generations of policemen:
my father, my grandad, my great-grandad
and the grandad before that were all
policemen,
before the foundation of the State, so I
have a long line of people who knew how to
deter
My dad was a sergeant in the traffic
department in Dublin city for 35 years
and I saw at first hand when he would come
home and be shook from seeing car
accidents.
It is probably the reason I
get a motorbike as a young lad.
I see and
listening to
nowadays that we are not giving them the
support they need in the job or
financially.
I have continuously asked for tax
incentives and tax breaks for critical
workers, be it gardaí, nurses or teachers,
in Dublin, Galway, Cork or any
of the cities where the rent is higher.
It is something we can do which will
incentivise more gardaí, nurses or
teachers, and give them financial support.
It will also help gardaí be better at the
job because they will not have the
small financial worries that they would
not have if they were in
a less expensive area, working the same
job
doing the same hours that city gardaí are
doing.
Focusing on the Bill, we need rules that
can actually be enforced.
I heard Deputy Gogarty speaking earlier
about enforcement that
creates a deterrent and the policies that
change behaviour.
I proudly represent Dublin Bay North and I
hear about the consequences of transport
policy every day on my commute if
taking public transport, with the 130 bus
being cancelled eight times yesterday,
with the roadworks being done and
being told these traffic jams are constant
and with allowing people to then use rat
runs, speeding through residential areas
in
Marino, putting people's children at risk.
I see it constantly.
When one road closes, then capacity
changes.
Having been on Dublin City Council, I find
the traffic plans
and the diversions really frustrating.
While I always want to see traffic policy
being data driven, we should know
what happens after we close a road or
alter a major junction.
a route or making a route one-way with an
outdated traffic plan, which I have seen
across north Dublin, is not acceptable.
Elected officials should have a greater
say.
People put their trust in elected
officials.
To have an unelected engineer determine
what happens to a road is not acceptable.
What is the point of holding an election
if an entire road or area can be changed
without the push-back of an elected
official?
measures I would like to see in the Bill.
We should have the same approach
consistently.
One of the strongest parts of the Bill,
and one which I commend, is the provision
to allow local authorities receive and
process collision data.
As has been mentioned by multiple
Deputies, it has long been needed.
I welcome it.
When councils can identify locations where
collisions are occurring, they can target
investment accordingly.
That is using data.
That is what this whole Bill is about but
that is the kind of evidence-led policy I
would like to see across Departments.
Be it energy or health, we need to put
resources where there are pinch points.
On speeding, there are some very practical
things we could do.
People need clearer,
frequent signs showing speed limits on the
stretches of road they are travelling on.
There are areas in my constituency where
there have been repeated accidents and
where a wall has been built six times
because people are speeding.
Since a camera showing the live speed
the wall is still intact.
People are seeing that flashing LED.
It changes driving and the data shows
that.
Also, the wall being there shows that.
We should make far greater use of
solar-powered speed feedback signs.
It is not being done.
They would tell a driver instantly that
they are doing 55
in a 50 km/h zone and must slow down.
It is simple, visible and immediate.
When somebody repeatedly ignores the limit
there has to be enforcement.
I have travelled to other countries where
seen instant tickets being given to people
who are repeatedly
speeding and it would definitely deter
people.
I would support this as that speeding
ticket could be the deterrent that stops
someone speeding again and saves someone's
life.
I heard a lot of Deputies talking about
the incident on the M7.
That is something we need to discuss but
the systems and what
doing need to be changed.
I welcome the proposal in the Bill that
will end the requirement to display the
paper motor task disk.
The State already holds vehicle
information electronically and the Bill
will modernise that and remove the paper
disc requirement.
I think that makes sense.
We should use digital records, rather than
maintaining paperwork for the sake of
tradition.
It would speed up the process and allow
for
stop points to have a quicker flow of
traffic.
We should examine how motor taxation works
and whether
it can be linked to fuel consumption, so
that when somebody
can drive less, there is an incentive to
do so.
The issue I want to spend more time on is
e-scooters, which were
mentioned by Deputy
We need to stop pretending that
e-scooters, electric bikes and scramblers
Outside this House people can get an
ordinary legal
e-bike.
When I was parking outside my house the
other day, I saw two young lads
going down the road faster than I can
drive, and they had no helmets.
By the time I
they were coming, they would have already
gone past it.
Powerful electric bikes can already fall
into a category with
registration and other legal requirements.
People in north Dublin are constantly onto
my office speaking about their child
nearly run over or having been hit and
this is something on which we need to
allow better enforcement by gardaí.
We need to have this serious discussion.
We should
examine whether some form of identifiable
registration should apply to e-scooters.
I do not think
acceptable that people with phones can be
jumped on O'Connell Street by someone on
an e-scooter and
no way to easily track who owns that
scooter.
If that vehicle was registered
clearly visible,
it would deter them being used for crime.
With
drug dealing across the inner city and my
constituency, at night we can see people
visibly
shifting drugs on these e-scooters because
they know they
will not be chased
if they go off road.
We need to support and
enforcement brings me back to An Garda
Síochána.
It is easy for us to pass another law in
the House and say the
will enforce it but gardaí need resources.
With regard to numbers, I have given one
suggestion on how we can increase
in Dublin by giving incentives and tax
breaks to gardaí and critical workers.
We also need more road policing units.
They need equipment to test the so-called
bikes.
I welcome
recent announcement by An Garda Síochána
of the seizures of these e-scooters.
It shows that when there is a will they
can get results.
When gardaí do their job lawfully
and proportionately within their training,
they should be supported for doing it.
This does not mean gardaí are above
scrutiny - far from it.
No one in this country should be.
However, accountability should not mean
leaving individual members afraid to
intervene against dangerous behaviour
because they fear that doing their job
will leave them exposed.
I welcome the better digital records
Minister of State is introducing and the
measures that will
help
save lives.
I hope
some of the other considerations I
them to do their jobs, and when they leave
the Garda they should be supported the
whole way through.
I thank all
the Deputies for their contributions to
this debate and for the careful
consideration they have given to the Bill.
I
acknowledge their concerns and the
practical issues raised on Second Stage.
I might take a little bit of time to refer
to some of
Deputy Farrelly spoke about education.
It is important to say the RSA
piloted a scheme during the academic year
2024-25
that delivered training to teachers in
almost
140 schools.
In 2026, the RSA aims to have completed a
national roll-out to transition year in
730 post-primary schools,
expanding the capacity for new learning
sessions in the first and
secondary schools and third level
institutions
and a lot of work is going on in this
regard.
I have come across children who have done
these programmes and I have asked them
what they
learned, especially with regard to
bicycles.
The first thing they told me was
they learned how to stop the bike, which
is, quite simply, the most important
thing.
other issues have come up.
In relation to
enforcement and
protection and training of gardaí, I met
the
Garda assistant commissioner with
responsibility for road policing,
Department of justice officials and my
officials to discuss what gardaí need
in terms of training, pursuit training and
legislation.
The Garda has given us a list of two or
three
issues on which it wants us to formulate
legislation to help gardaí
do their jobs properly.
These are being looked at by departmental
officials and we will bring forward
legislation as urgently as we can.
Whether we bring it in through this Bill
or in a separate Bill
on an emergency basis, we are working on
it.
I want to make sure
whatever we bring in will work and will
help gardaí.
We are in ongoing
forward, and other measures such as body
cameras, gardaí have more technical backup
and more resources to do the job they have
to do.
I would love to see 1,000 gardaí in the
road policing
Minister of State, Deputy Buttimer, to see
how best we can help gardaí and get
more
out there.
The message
with scramblers and
to e-scooters, we have brought in a
regulation on hi-vis vests, visibility
and helmets.
Next week I hope to sign more regulations
to change the
age from 16 to 18.
I hope to get it signed next week.
We have other
proposed legislation to redefine an
e-scooter to make it a mechanically
propelled vehicle.
We are going through how we can bring it
in
and how we can end up with registered
so we know who the owners are.
This is very simple and will be a help to
gardaí.
Somebody mentioned NCT waiting times.
The NCT service has seen an annual
increase of more than 30%
since 2020 in the number of tests being
done.
At the moment
721 vehicle inspectors in the NCT service.
The number of vehicles tested
in July was 159,000, so
a lot of testing going on.
Somebody mentioned that 60% or 50% fail
the test.
I would prefer to see a vehicle failing a
test if
not right than it being let out on the
road.
We
have to have a common-sense approach on
Somebody else mentioned driver licence
exchanges with the USA.
We have a licence agreement with Australia
and with seven of the ten Canadian
provinces.
We have another proposed agreement under
way with Nova Scotia.
In the programme for Government, the RSA
is dealing with New York state,
Massachusetts and New Jersey to exchange
technical details with
regard to how they do their driving tests
compared with ours, and whether they match
Each of the United States has different
rules, regulations and standards so we
cannot have an overall measure for the US
but have to look at each state
individually.
We are working on
80 km/h to 60 km/h.
These account for 80% of the road network.
The local authorities are now charged to
have the
urban areas in place by March of next year
and they are working on this.
With this legislation we will be able to
the remainder of the roads from 100 km/h
to 80 km/h.
We also say clearly that at the end of the
day
speed limits are not a licence to drive at
that speed.
People have to drive with total control of
their vehicle at all times.
Legitimate questions have been raised by
Deputies in the House
all in the interest of having safer roads,
reducing
deaths on the roads and reducing
collisions to make sure everybody can
feel safer on our roads.
The Minister, Deputy O'Brien, is sitting
behind me.
We are working very closely in the
Department and we discussed a lot of what
we are speaking about today at
management meeting
what we can
This Bill itself is not the entire answer.
There is a lot more we have to do in terms
of legislation.
We then have the challenge of making sure
that when we bring in legislation, it is
acted upon.
Deputy Currie raised the issue of court
services and licensing.
We are working on that at the moment to
see how we can
deal with it.
I intend to bring forward amendments to
the Bill.
We will be making additional improvements
on Committee Stage, and I look forward to
working with Deputies across the House to
make sure we get this Bill enacted as
quickly as possible with the amendments I
intend to bring in
that Stage.
I thank
for their time.
It has been a very interesting and
worthwhile debate.
It is important
to thank Deputies because all they have in
their heads is to try to reduce the number
of road deaths.
Everybody makes a personal choice when
they go out on the road, whether
they are a pedestrian, cyclist,
motorcyclist or the driver of a car or a
truck.
They
take personal responsibility, and that is
most important.
We can bring in the laws and the
legislation to help protect people, but we
have to start with education.
Speeding and failing to wear seat belts
are problems.
We all know that phone distraction is a
huge problem in cars.
I plead with every Deputy to make sure
when they are talking to young people in
their constituencies, they ask them not to
use their phones when they are
in
the Bill
pursuant to Standing Orders
sharing time with Deputy Coppinger.
The budget is coming up.
The
crisis impacting huge numbers of people is
on everybody's lips.
This is, of course,
People are asking if the Government is
going to help those who are struggling.
There are many aspects to the
cost of accommodation and housing, the
cost of
but a critical issue for hundreds
of thousands
Thanks to Donald Trump, everybody is
facing higher electricity, energy and fuel
bills.
By the way,
on Members in this
not many of them,
who ever thought
Donald Trump was going to do any good for
the world.
Not only has he has helped Israel
rain death and destruction on the people
of
different groups of people, now every
person in this country and across the
world is paying an economic price for his
policies.
There are going to be people
who will not be able to pay their
electricity and energy bills
because of his warmongering and misguided,
immoral
policies.
The Government is offering little
assistance to those people.
It offered the red carpet to Donald Trump
last weekend,
offering little assistance to the ordinary
people.
More than 300,000 of them
are in arrears
not just
electricity.
Our motion relates to electricity prices,
but our proposals
actually about trying to help people who
are struggling generally with the cost of
energy, whether that is gas or
electricity.
When
take the two
more than half a million households in
this country are in
arrears with either their gas or
electricity bills.
That is set to get worse because of Trump.
making a very simple proposal in this
motion.
It is to help people who are struggling,
not just those in arrears, but
every single household can get some help
by introducing
a €500 energy credit to help them with
their electricity bills.
We are also proposing to give an
additional €500 to every
household
with a registered disability.
We would pay for that by imposing a levy
on the
data centres.
This levy would
amount to making the data centres
pay the same price for electricity as
householders are paying.
I
know how many people know
we certainly want to alert people to
know
been trying to alert people to it.
Some people may know, while others
probably
know, that while ordinary people are
struggling to pay their electricity and
energy bills and the price hikes resulting
from the policies of Trump, data centres -
as we will go on to discuss -
are now using almost one quarter of the
electricity in this country but only
paying half the price per unit of
electricity that ordinary householders are
paying.
It is a shocking fact.
Data centres,
owned by the billionaire tech companies
that are making
obscene profits, pay half the price for
their electricity that ordinary
householders pay.
It is absolutely disgusting and completely
unjustifiable.
worth going through the profits of the
main owners of the data centres that are
proliferating across the country and
hoovering up one quarter of the
electricity in the country, and soon to be
one third of the electricity.
Almost 80% of electricity in the Dublin
area
being hoovered up by these data centres,
the proliferation of which is making a
mockery of any attempt to deal with
climate change.
They are also using significant volumes of
water.
billion.
Meta's profits were €2.9 billion.
These are their annual profits.
Amazon's profits were slightly less at €22
million, but still very significant.
These are some of the richest companies,
owned by some of the richest people in the
world,
are being subsidised by ordinary
householders who are struggling to pay
their bills, and who are going to be
struggling even more this winter.
suggesting a very simple idea: that the
data centres pay the same as the
ordinary householders.
That will raise €1.5 billion, which will
fund a serious
bit of support to help every household in
the country to deal with their bills.
The average electricity arrears is about
€500.
This could help wipe out the arrears being
endured by some of the poorest
families.
The average household is three or four
people so hundreds of thousands of people
are seriously struggling to pay their
bills
going to struggle more.
This could give them a real break.
Our policies do not stop at that.
Some might object that it is just more
money in the pockets of
energy companies.
It is true
the energy companies are cleaning up at
the moment, making
extraordinary profits.
I think
€975 million in profits in the most
recently available
figures.
We also want to cap prices.
In our wider policies, and we will propose
this for the budget, we want to cap the
prices they can charge ordinary
householders for electricity and the same
for gas, petrol, diesel and so on but that
is another day's work.
In case anybody objects that this is a
handout to the super rich and the
multimillionaires, believe me, People
Before Profit will be taking that money
back off the millionaires with a
multimillionaire tax.
We will propose and have proposed
taxes on the super wealthy
Setting that aside, people need help now.
The Government recognised this
in 2025 when it gave energy credits of
€250
but
then withdrew them.
In the most recent budget, people with
disabilities
why we have also stressed the need to give
additional help to people with
disabilities.
the most vulnerable - those with
disabilities and their carers.
We propose a fair
and justified way to give every household
some support and in particular
give additional support to those with
disabilities.
worth bearing in mind that we have the
highest electricity
prices in Europe,
confirmed by the European Union
statistical agency during the summer.
We were told by previous Fianna Fáil
Governments that we needed to
deregulate and liberalise the market and
change the mandate of the ESB,
the State-owned electricity company,
because if we introduced competition
into the market, it would
benefit the consumer.
The opposite happened.
Prior to the deregulation of the Irish
electricity market, we had the lowest
Now, we have the highest.
They are 40% higher than the EU average,
and that
was before Trump's wars and the impact
of data centres.
and
privatisation of the market have benefited
private companies and big energy providers
but have crucified ordinary
householders to the extent that hundreds
of thousands of people
on the data centres in imposing this levy
because
they are
hoovering up huge amounts of electricity
to the benefit of some of the richest
The Government defends the subsidy to
these people already making billions in
profits on the grounds that
critical infrastructure.
I wonder if the Government and the
Minister
the Government has decided it will
subsidise, allowing these data centres
that are linked substantially to the
development of AI
to proliferate.
Even the AI tech billionaires are now
saying that technology could destroy the
world and humanity.
I do not actually take that very seriously
because I think
just looking for more handouts but it
underlines the madness of a
policy of giving them €1 billion in
subsidies a year and continuing to allow
data centres to proliferate.
I will be interested to hear the Minster's
response.
People will be out on the streets this
Saturday at the Affordable Ireland
demonstration demanding a real break in
the cost of living.
They are absolutely right to do so.
A simple measure the Government could take
to alleviate some of this cost-of-living
misery is to support this motion.
Solidarity fully supports this motion.
Just before I came down to the Chamber, I
heard very positive news that a data
centre has been refused planning
permission in Mayo.
I
heard the full details but there were
concerns about where it would access
electricity and concerns about climate.
I hope we are now seeing the tide start to
turn against
carte blanche
this during questions to the Minister
previously.
He and another Minister sort of laughed in
my face when I said-----
-----the purpose of these
was mainly for AI, which is not useful to
the world or to humanity; in
fact,
very detrimental in many cases.
I hope the Minister is starting to
reconsider.
A lot of young people and a growing body
of people are extremely critical of AI.
I also want to mention
how intersectional an issue this is.
It intersects with the environment,
military technology, the cost of living,
which this motion
focuses on, and many other issues.
An estimated cumulative average of about
€360
has been laid at the door of data centres.
With households
paying twice as much as a data centre per
unit and with the highest electricity
prices in the EU,
why is the Government so uncaring about
the proliferation of
data centres?
Would
admit that maybe the Government has erred?
Ireland is now becoming the bogeyman
rather than the poster boy for what other
countries should not do.
These price rises hit low-income
households disproportionately and the
Government has taken away the supports.
How are people going to cope if that
continues to be the Government's stance?
Seven electricity suppliers have increased
their energy prices over the past few
months.
The CRU said there will be a €41 increase
per month from October, largely laying
at the door of data centre usage.
With over 322,000 in electricity arrears,
The Central Bank also came out with a
pressing concern that house building will
slow down, another issue I raised
previously, because of the lack of
electricity connections due to data
centres.
A levy on data centres is urgent.
It is not like they cannot afford to pay.
Microsoft
profits
€47 billion.
Is the Minister seriously suggesting it
could not pay a levy?
It is well able to pay.
Further than that, the ESB, which once was
a public utility, should be brought back
into State ownership and run for profit to
get bills down in the first place.
Bord Gáis announced it will increase its
bills
by €140 a year.
There is a huge level of gas arrears.
In recent days, the regulator
admitted that data centres are a threat to
the gas grid too and new data centres will
be offered lower prices but it may have to
cut them off if there is too much demand.
There is a proposal for 17 more data
centres.
They would have the same gas needs as 2.6
million homes.
We need to get a grip.
There should be a moratorium on data
centres.
They are now a threat to people's pockets,
the environment and our
resources, guzzling a quarter of our
electricity.
It is proposed to take water from the
Shannon to
Dublin.
Most of
are around Dublin, Meath and nearby
locations.
Dublin West,
seems to be a hot spot for data centres.
There are more than 20 data centres in
Dublin 15 and Clonee, which is
beside us.
According to a report our councillor John
Burtchaell put in,
the council is not aware of how much
energy
They are not required to indicate that on
planning applications.
It just seems to be a let-it-rip approach.
Another data centre has been approved for
Clonee.
These
are overwhelmingly
in areas of deprivation.
That has been pointed out by
interesting - and
this will spread to Ireland - that there
has been a movement against data centres
in the USA.
Even the Republican Party is having to
make talking points out of data centres
because of the impact they are having
drought.
This is combined with the heatwaves we
have been having.
In Monterey Park in California, for
example, there was an organised response
to a new data centre coming to the town.
It was a huge issue at the city council.
In Naas, 300 people turned out
to discuss this matter.
Therefore, consciousness of these data has
been raised in Irish society centres,
particularly over the summer when we could
not water our plants because data centres
were using so much water.
People are aware that there is a real
problem with these issues.
It
just an environmental issue; it is a
democratic issue as well
because it seems the big tech companies -
the tech bro billionaires -
are dictating, and they are completely
unaccountable.
For example, thejournal.ie had a report
that roughly half of these centres did not
even have to give details of the resources
they are using.
This motion should be supported by the
Minister.
We could eliminate the arrears of the more
than 300,000 households
and take the dread and stress off many
people.
How can the Minister continue to allow the
electricity companies
ESB
just made a 20% increase in its profits.
Airtricity also hugely increased its
profits.
The data centres are guzzling almost a
quarter of our electricity.
They are also guzzling our water.
To sit idly by while people go into debt
is absolutely
unforgivable.
These multinational companies should be
taxed more broadly.
We cannot continue to pretend that we can
have public services such
as a State childcare system, healthcare
and so on without taxing
wealth.
We cannot continue to allow these
companies
gives us an opportunity to discuss this
issue.
I reject the motion - I take some of the
points that
made in it -
why I brought forward the
To set the context of where we are, we all
understand that, in particular, the
conflicts in the Middle East and Ukraine,
which have not been mentioned - Deputy
Boyd Barrett mentioned the Middle East
briefly - have caused significant
disruption to global energy markets.
I
think anyone would disagree with that.
We
not just that.
It is also Russia's invasion of Ukraine
and the various disruptions we have
had in recent years
On the purchasing power index
through Eurostat, Ireland is approximately
eighth for energy prices.
not first, but
still very expensive for
people.
That is a matter we continue to grapple
with.
The acceleration of
renewables will be critical in that
but
turn to that in a moment.
I assure the House that
supply, which is critical for an
nation, is being monitored on a regular
basis.
Thankfully, approximately 50% of our
electricity is generated through renewable
sources.
We doubled our renewable capacity
and
that.
We need to get on with the grid investment
programme we have under price review, PR,
6 and make sure that
have
held up are built.
We understand that any price increase can
be a serious challenge for households
and small businesses.
As a result, we have been proactive.
We have introduced a series of measures to
reduce fuel prices, and further measures
are under consideration by the national
energy affordability task force, which
feeds into the budgetary task force.
I chair that task force, which will meet
again tomorrow.
Specifically on fuel,
the package of Government support measures
is to the tune of €1.4 billion.
This package is helping to reduce the cost
burden, particularly at the pump and for
productive sectors such as haulage
right the way across to agriculture.
That is important because it underpins our
supply chain and the tens of thousands of
jobs
remind Deputies that I made a few
significant changes in the budget for
2026.
I reduced the VAT rate on electricity and
gas to 9% right through to 2030.
I extended social welfare direct payments
to households, including fuel allowance
payments.
More than a quarter of households receive
those direct payments, and that is a
matter
budget.
I also retained the €400 income tax
disregard for households involved in
microgeneration.
I intend for that to be kept.
The best way to insulate our economy and
society from fuel price shocks is to
reduce our dependence on fossil fuels.
That is why we are investing record
amounts
in retrofitting through part- and
fully-funded schemes.
We provided €640 million
in last year's budget for this year to
carry out retrofitting in households and
businesses, targeting 73,000 households to
bring about reductions in energy use,
emissions and bills.
In January, I brought forward changes to
that.
We expanded the schemes
middle-income households.
We also expanded the warmer homes scheme,
which is the 100% grant aid scheme for
those at risk of fuel poverty and those in
receipt of social welfare payments.
We have done more than 35,000 houses under
that scheme and
have increased the number year on year.
We want to do
that because it is a protection against
future price shocks.
We brought forward
in respect of attic and cavity wall
insulation.
We doubled the grants for heat pumps,
electrifying homes and
reducing dependence on fossil fuels.
Full home retrofits can save up to €1,200
per annum on energy costs.
This year, since we made the changes, we
have had approximately 89,000 applications
to the end of August, so people are
responding.
I intend to bring forward further measures
in that regard because they ensure
that we can protect households against
future energy shocks.
More than €2 billion has been invested in
that area since 2019.
The 89,000 applications we have received
to the end of August compares with
41,100 in the same period last year.
A number of protections are in place for
customers experiencing difficulties with
paying their bills.
The arrears figures - particularly those
relating to 90-day arrears - are too high.
They have plateaued in recent months, but
they are a concern.
We are looking at that matter.
At my request,
have put in
hardship funds
and protections for customers against
disconnection.
Disconnection does not happen in any real
way.
It is percentage of a per cent.
It is a very small number, and
want to keep it that way.
already mentioned the changes we made on
social protection measures.
They all form part of the discussions we
are having now, in advance of
the budget
The Deputies' parties will be putting
forward alternative budgets, as they do
each year.
They are perfectly entitled to do so, and
we will feed it into the debate.
It is important to highlight that the
recent price increases are a matter for
the Commission for Regulation of
Utilities.
We have seen a number of increases.
Electric Ireland
not increase its prices and
indicated that it will not be
seeking an increase in tariffs over the
coming months.
I do not recall
laughing at Deputy Coppinger in the
Chamber.
That is not something I
do.
Her recollection of something might be
completely different from mine.
I take this debate seriously because we
have to be honest with people that
we are not a heavy industry nation.
not a
heavy industrial manufacturer.
ICT, not just data centres, forms a really
important part of our economy, employing
about 7% of our people.
There are about 2.8 million people working
in our country now.
Nearly 2.3 million
working on a full-time basis.
Just short of 190,000 people work in the
ICT sector.
Some 19,000 are directly employed in data
centres.
Data centres are a very important part of
our digital infrastructure and
of our offering as a country.
The largest and most important protection
against poverty and
price increases is for people
have good jobs.
As a Government, we have a responsibility
to maintain
and grow
jobs that are here.
I refer both to indigenous Irish firms and
foreign direct investment.
That is also critically important.
Neither Deputy mentioned
job creation and job retention.
That must be fundamental to the operation
of our society and our economy.
We had a good discussion earlier today
when we had oral questions on energy.
There was a lot of discussion of data
centres.
I mentioned the large energy user action
plan that I brought forward with
Minister,
Peter Burke, in January of this year.
That sets out a planned approach to any
additional data centres or
large energy users being given a
connection.
Any new ones will have to meet 80% of
their electricity demand through new
renewable sources.
I was going to wait for
to speak later on.
Anyway, that is a fact.
Deputy Stanley was
here for that debate, when I also said
that applications for connections are not
automatically granted.
If anything, many have been refused.
We have to balance this and
done independently through the planning
process and through
connection agreements that are in place.
demand,
the critical priority is to ensure we can
meet demand right
the way across our country.
That is why the PR6 grid investment is so
important.
That €18.9 billion of investment will
deliver
520 capital projects to allow for more
renewables on our system - we are
accelerating renewables - to allow more
storage in our system and to bring down
energy bills.
The fundamental way to do that is to
accelerate renewables by reducing our
dependence on fossil fuel.
That has to be done and that is what we
are doing.
In relation to
measures we will take, the Deputies are
perfectly entitled to put forward this
motion with their suggestions.
We are now preparing for
the budget.
I assure people that the budget will be a
cost-of-living budget.
It will be about protecting families,
workers, working families and
the most vulnerable in our society through
what is a global crisis.
We are not going to be able to protect
everyone from every single price increase
but we will do our level best to protect
them in a very sustainable way that
continues to protect jobs in our economy
and not by shutting down a whole sector.
defending the indefensible.
That is why he did not really engage with
it.
He is defending the fact that, when
300,000 people are in arrears on their
electricity bills,
data centres owned by the richest and most
powerful companies in the world are paying
half the price the poorest people in the
country are expected to pay.
He is defending the absolutely
indefensible.
He is saying that we cannot
possibly say that these, the richest
companies in the world, which provide very
few jobs
get onto in a second, should be asked to
pay the same as ordinary households, which
is a minimal ask.
The fact that this would generate €1.5
billion, enough money to give a
€500 energy credit to every family in the
country and an additional €500 to every
family with a disabled member,
speaks to how much electricity is being
used by these data centres.
They are now using almost as much
electricity as every single house
in this State put together.
to the nub of the issue, which is that
this Government is not representing the
people; it is representing the big tech
companies.
That is what
doing at an EU level.
If you read the priorities, you see that
they are about pushing a deregulation
agenda within Europe as part of the
digital omnibus
on behalf of US big tech corporations.
It is also what it is doing domestically.
On every single front, big tech's data
centres are being put
before ordinary people.
I really think that more and more people
are waking up to the costs of this policy.
There are huge costs on multiple fronts,
to be paid by ordinary people, as a result
of the Minister's prioritisation of these
data centres and their insatiable demand
for our electricity.
There is the actual cost in their pockets,
which Friends of the Earth
has highlighted very clearly.
Extensive research shows that, between
2021 and 2023, the average
household paid an extra €263 in their
bills because
of data centres' usage.
How does that work?
Data centres are pushing up the total
amount of electricity being used.
They are using about a quarter of our
total electricity.
They are thereby increasing the
of time we spend using gas rather than
just using renewables.
When you do that, gas sets the price for
all the electricity.
People are paying the cost of that.
That does not take into account the extra
money people are paying in network
charges.
in total, between 2015 and 2023,
the public paid €715 million extra because
of the Government's policy of
prioritising data centres.
That is just what happened in the past.
Let us look at what is going to happen in
the future.
Without a new energy shock,
the average household will pay €461 over
the next ten years.
However, we are in the middle of a new
energy shock
happening in the Middle East.
The report's predictions in respect of the
increase in the price
of oil are modest but, in that scenario,
the cost could be €726 million, €1.1
billion or €1.6 billion cumulatively for
households.
We are talking about the average household
in this country
as a result of the Minister's
prioritisation of data centres.
The public is going to pay big time as a
result of our failure to meet our climate
The Minister has thrown in the towel on
climate action.
He did so over Christmas, when he said we
were not
meet any of our targets.
still patiently waiting for the climate
action plan for
2026.
The year is almost over.
Why?
It is because we cannot meet any of our
targets.
We are going to
well under half of our targets, which are
supposed to be legally binding, because
the data centres have gobbled up all
the renewable energy.
Sometimes when the Minister talks about
this he gives the impression that, as long
as we keep adding renewable energy, it is
good for the climate.
The planet cares about the amount of
greenhouse gases.
If you are adding extra renewables but all
of that additional capacity is being
gobbled up by data centres, then it does
not matter.
That is precisely what has happened.
Since 2017, all of the extra renewable
capacity has been gobbled up by data
centres.
We are therefore also paying for it in
terms of climate.
also paying for it in terms of housing.
It was the Minister's own senior civil
servant who said that we need to make a
choice about our energy use
going to go to data centres or to housing.
Of course, the Minister dismissed that.
Why?
It was because he had made his choice.
It is going to go to data centres.
This has actually happened.
It happened in west Dublin.
A new substation
designed
to provide electricity for new housing but
a data centre
came in and took up that electricity.
We are paying for it in terms of public
transport.
I am convinced that this is a key factor
in the delay in the electrification
of our buses and other public transport
projects.
Data centres are coming first and for
what?
In a comment last week, which the Minister
kind of pointed
this is our equivalent to Germany's car
factories.
That is a joke.
In terms of direct jobs, German car
factories account for about 400,000
direct
the record - that there are 19,000
directly employed in data centres.
I
know if he would stand over that figure.
said that 19,000 are directly employed in
data centres.
Great, because he will have to correct the
record later as that is not what is in his
record.
The Minister knows he is fiddling the
figures because that 19,000 figure -
it is
coming from the KPMG report,
which
spent €105,000 of public money to get.
He told them we only want this outcome,
to say data centres are really important.
Most of those jobs are construction jobs.
There are not 19,000 people
working data centres directly in this
country.
The Minister knows that is not true.
Most of them are construction jobs.
They could be building houses.
the other way this is affecting the
housing crisis.
these workers who are spending their time
building data centres
purely temporary jobs.
The KPMG
instead be building housing.
What is the actual figure?
How many people actually work in data
centres?
The Minister's own report, which is a
report designed to support the case for
data centres, says 3,300 direct jobs.
The figure is 3,300, not 19,000, not
the 1 million KPMG was trying to point
towards.
The figure is 3,300 direct jobs.
Of course, every job is important.
If any of these data centres had to shut
down, we are in favour of a just
transition but 3,300 jobs for an industry
that is gobbling up
one quarter of our electricity
makes no sense.
defending the indefensible.
People across the world are waking up to
the reality that this is the toxic waste
of the 21st century.
They use up all your electricity.
They use up all your water.
They restrict other jobs being created
because of various industries not having
access to electricity.
They prevent the building of housing.
They interfere with the delivery of public
transport and they provide a tiny number
of jobs.
Nobody wants them.
People in America are rising up against
them and saying we
want them but the Government approach is
to say
this toxic waste nobody else wants.
I will underline the point.
When you are living in a country that has
this very unusual,
outsized nature of the data centres,
people probably do not get just how
unusual it is.
Ireland is a massive outlier.
There is no country like Ireland in terms
of
percentage of electricity usage or any
other metric you want to look at.
We are ten times the European average.
on the run on this issue.
An Coimisiún Pleanála's decision on the
Mayo data centre is extremely significant.
The turnout at the public meeting in
Kildare a couple of weeks ago is extremely
significant.
People are waking up to the Government's
agenda and the fact the Government is
putting data centres before the needs of
ordinary people in this country.
I really predict this will be an enormous
political issue over the course of the
coming months.
The Government's position is utterly
untenable.
It is why it makes all
the arguments it makes.
Let us take up one of them
only ten seconds left.
This idea that we should not worry
nonsense.
That is on an annualised basis over a
whole number of years whereas the whole
point is
data centre demand is pretty much
continuous, it barely changes whereas
renewables come and go.
That is the whole point.
It makes no sense to continue on this
line.
We need action on the cost-of-living
crisis.
We need people on the streets on Saturday.
I welcome the opportunity to speak in
favour of this motion.
This is a critical motion because Irish
households are paying roughly twice as
much for electricity as data centres.
Ordinary workers, families and pensioners
are paying significantly more for their
electricity than these large energy users.
It is grossly unfair.
It is the direct consequence of the
Government's reckless failure to plan.
At a time when ordinary people are being
squeezed from every direction, Government
policy has prioritised the interests of
ever increasingly monstrous data centres
over the interests of households,
communities and families.
For years, Ministers have ignored Sinn
Féin's repeated warnings about the impact
that unchecked data centre expansion would
have on our electricity grid.
Fianna Fáil and Fine Gael ignored warnings
about pressure on grid capacity, despite
data centre demand having exploded by over
400% over the last ten
years.
They ignored warnings about the fact that
data centres are preventing houses from
being built.
Just yesterday, the Central Bank report
detailed that a lack of access to the grid
is one of the key reasons why housing is
not being provided.
While Fianna Fáil and Fine Gael fight for
this status quo, Sinn Féin is absolutely
clear that data centres must pay their
fair share.
In my constituency of
North, the building of the Herbata data
centre has been a source of massive
anxiety for my constituents.
Nearby, Jigginstown in
has been rezoned for another data centre
and this has also caused massive concern.
I attended that meeting in Naas, which was
attended by several hundred people.
It really has ignited people.
This new site is twice the size of the
Herbata complex, with its borders a mere
130 m away from homes and schools in the
area.
Having attended that meeting two weeks
ago, it is clear there are serious
concerns and the Government has to address
them.
We have seen the reports from Clondalkin
on the impact on locals from noise but a
hyper data centre right beside Herbata
could cause havoc for residents in
and Kildare.
Ireland has done more than its fair share
in respect of data centres.
This summer, the United Nations cited
Ireland as a cautionary tale on the
environmental impact of runaway artificial
intelligence growth and data centre
We already have enough data centres to
store the important data we need on health
and banking, etc.
and we have certainly done our bit.
This is not a Luddite reaction to
technology and innovation.
This explosion in data centre demand is
all around AI.
When the CEOs of these companies are
urging caution, surely legislators should
listen.
I absolutely believe a lot of this is hype
and I suspect there could be bit
of corporate capture involved in it but we
have to take a pause and listen
to these people when they are urging
caution.
Why, then, is this Government doubling
down and insisting on building more and
more data centres when our electricity
infrastructure is creaking during a
housing
Just today, An Coimisiún Pleanála
overturned Mayo County Council's decision
to build a data centre as the applicants
had failed to show there was sufficient
electricity locally to serve the centre
and for climate reasons.
This is to be welcomed.
I really hope that Kildare County Council
is paying attention to this development
because this logic must be applied across
the State.
Look at the Scottish Parliament, which
just this week voted to pause any new data
centre builds until proper guidance is in
place.
Our housing supply is being massively
affected by these new sites and the Irish
Congress of Trade Unions mentioned that as
well when it was before the climate
committee recently.
The Government still has no legislative
requirement that housing developments be
prioritised over data centres for grid
capacity.
This is why Sinn Féin has also brought
forward legislation that would require
Government and the regulator to prioritise
housing ahead of data centres for
electricity connections because the
national grid should, first and foremost,
If capacity is available, homes must come
first.
If there is a choice between powering a
new housing development and another large
scale data centre, the homes must come
first.
This is what the people of my constituency
want.
their kids to be able to afford to buy a
house in Naas, live locally and see their
grandchildren growing up.
They
want them having to work an hour and half
down the road.
This is why Sinn Féin believes a data
centre levy should be seriously
Simply put, those who place the greatest
demands on our electricity infrastructure
should make a fair contribution towards
the cost they impose on the system.
This levy would help ensure the burden
does not continue to fall
disproportionately on ordinary consumers,
while sending a clear signal that
strategic national infrastructure must be
in the public interest.
The Government's priorities have been
clear.
They have put corporate demand ahead of
strategic planning and they have failed to
ensure that housing and ordinary consumers
are protected.
Sinn Féin's priorities are different.
We believe housing must come first.
We believe workers and families must come
first.
Week after week, workers and families are
being hit with soaring energy bills.
We hear it every single day.
Unfortunately, we have had company after
company in the past two weeks telling us
they are putting up their prices again.
There are double digit increases.
That is another blow to families who are
already stretched to the limit.
The people out there are being told they
have to find hundreds more euro every
year.
They simply do not have that type of
money.
That is the reality.
I
know
hearing it in his constituency but I am
definitely hearing it in my constituency
The reality is stark.
Ireland already has the highest
electricity prices in Europe.
We now have more than 320,000 households
in arrears on their electricity bills.
One in four households in the State cannot
pay their gas bill because they have
fallen behind.
The statistics that
seeing now are staggering.
These are real people who do not have the
money to pay their bills when they fall
due.
These figures should be setting off alarm
bells in Government Buildings.
The Minister should be standing up and
asking what
can do here.
Instead, he waltzes in here as if there is
nothing to see.
Those figures reveal the reality that
these families are facing every single day
and the scale of the crisis that ordinary
people have to meet.
That is before we even talk about the
hundreds of thousands of other families
who are able to pay their bills but are
stretching themselves doing it.
Life has become so unaffordable.
People who expected to be able to enjoy
the odd luxury here and there simply
cannot do it any more.
Families, workers and pensioners are all
fighting to stay afloat and to avoid
Those
quietly rationing their heat, cutting back
on electricity and leaving their
home-heating oil tank empty because they
simply cannot afford another fill.
It is baffling that time and again
Government opposes energy credits on the
grounds that
not targeted.
The truth is that the existing supports,
important as they are, are not reaching
enough people.
That is a problem affecting not just a
small minority but it is affecting
households right across the State.
That is why Sinn Féin has been very clear
in this.
We are calling for a return of energy
credits as an emergency measure to provide
immediate relief.
Energy credits were always supposed to be
an emergency response while the Government
However, those reforms never came.
The Government never came with a single
idea.
Instead, the Government repeatedly voted
down the ideas that we in Sinn Féin
We all see
every single day.
Irish households remain entrapped with the
highest electricity prices in Europe while
record numbers fall into arrears.
Government failure has been allowed to
become the new normal.
This crisis did not happen overnight nor
can it be blamed solely on a war or global
Every country has faced those pressures.
The real question here is: why does
Ireland still have the highest prices in
Europe?
People know the answer to that question.
The Government has pursued a reckless
expansion of data centres without ensuring
the necessary grid infrastructure was in
place first.
It can commission all the reports it likes
and can hire all the consultants to tell
it what it wants to hear but none of that
changes that reality.
Officials within the Department of energy
have acknowledged that data centres are
driving up prices for everyone else.
They pay a fraction of what ordinary
households and small business pay.
This is the system that Fianna Fáil
created and that Fine Gael has presided
over for years.
To make matters worse, data centres are
now being prioritised ahead of housing
Sinn Féin is having none of that.
That is why we introduced legislation to
ensure housing comes first.
We have consistently put forward proposals
and practical measures to reduce energy
costs to strengthen our electricity system
and to support struggling households.
Time and again Fine Gael, Fianna Fáil and
their supporters have voted against those
reforms.
Time and again they have chosen not to
act.
Workers and families deserve better.
They deserve a government that understands
the scale of the crisis and is prepared to
take the action to address the causes
the high energy costs and not simply
manage the consequences.
The message from households across the
State is clear: enough is enough.
It is time to put ordinary Irish people
first.
People cannot afford more excuses, more
delays or more inaction.
The Government needs to stop putting data
centres first and put people first.
They need relief, they need it now and it
is time to deliver for them.
and Solidarity for bringing forward this
really important motion.
The reality is the people are in crisis.
There is absolutely no doubt in my mind
that ordinary people need
energy credits and that we need to start
putting ordinary communities ahead of
data centres.
I am actually beginning to think that this
Government is making life harder for
people on purpose because if this was not
on purpose, I do not see how it would be
getting it so terribly wrong.
This is the
first week back and
people are worried out of their minds
because of the winter they are facing.
They are telling all of us
everybody is aware of that.
They are seeing that oil prices are
rising.
People living in the west of Ireland are
reliant on oil.
The Minister of State, Deputy McConalogue,
is aware of that as somebody who resides
Oil prices are rising and Government is
silent.
Electricity prices are rising and
Government is silent but Government is not
silent on public transport fares.
In fact, instead of being silent on it, it
has decided to increase them.
Instead of assisting struggling households
it has decided to make it even more
difficult for struggling households.
Tonight's motion
would assist ordinary families and workers
by actually
by putting money back into their pockets
to make it just that little bit easier
for them to be able to make ends meet.
However, of course as always, these things
fall on deaf ears when it comes to
Government.
There is a clear message that I want to
give to the Minister for Transport who has
disappointingly just left the Chamber.
Public transport fare price increases have
had a devastating impact on Galway
families.
A number of
in Galway have contacted me to say that
they are unable to meet this
extra demand on their resources.
What this will mean, and the NTA has
confirmed it, is that
be able to use public transport instead of
more people.
Not only that, but the Government has
doubled down when it comes to Oranmore
train station where
now have to pay for parking in order to be
able to use the train station,
which is ridiculous.
They will not be able to access Oranmore
train station with public transport until
at least 2028.
I am unsure how the Government is
expecting people to use that train unless
it specifically does not want it to be
used.
We
a huge increase in the Dublin MetroLink
cost.
There are serious concerns in the west of
Ireland about the impact this will have on
people across the west of Ireland,
specifically on capacity on the 424 bus.
Far too many people all summer have been
waiting at the side of the road, unable to
access that bus and it continues
to worsen in these months during the
academic year.
We urgently need the Minister for
Transport to intervene.
and for giving me the opportunity to
highlight the disaster that is the
Jigginstown Herbata data centres in Naas.
The people in Kildare have serious
concerns about the development of these
data centres.
Profits of corporations are being put
before the liveability of the town as well
as the livelihoods and well-being of its
residents.
The scale of the proposed project in
Jigginstown is terrifying.
If built, the Herbata complex would span
an area seven times the size of Croke
Park, reportedly consume three times as
much electricity as the whole of Kildare
annually, as well as 18,000 litres of
water a day.
This would jeopardise urgently needed
future housing in the county by placing
additional pressure on stretched
infrastructure.
The massive drain on energy resources by
data centres will also lead to spikes in
bills for families and small businesses
who are already struggling to keep the
heating and the lights on.
The Government is wilfully and recklessly
allowing the situation to deteriorate.
The environmental impact is equally
alarming.
The data centres proposed for Jigginstown
will rely on gas and emit up to 1.6
million tonnes of CO2 per year.
That is equivalent to the emissions of
half a million cars.
If allowed to go ahead, this project will
spell disaster, worsening the already dire
cost of living, housing and climate
crisis.
The hyperscale facility would create
further problems in terms of noise
pollution and property valuation due to
being planned mere metres away from an
established residential area.
We are not against data centres wholesale
but there has to be a balancing of
interests.
At the moment, Government is neglecting
the public good in favour of wooing
multinational investment.
In terms of cost and benefit, the number
of jobs created would be minimal and does
not justify the harm the development would
inflict on the environment and the quality
of life of the community.
The project simply must not go ahead.
The land must be rezoned before the
Jigginstown application is submitted.
Sinn Féin Councillor Noel Connolly will
bring a motion to Kildare County Council
that would oblige the chief executive to
initiate the rezoning process.
There will be a protest outside Áras Cill
Dara at 1.30 p.m.
on 28 September when this motion is being
discussed.
tonight is consistent with that objective
and represents an important step towards
restoring balance and protecting
communities.
For too long, companies have been drawing
on Ireland's natural resources while our
citizens bear the cost.
The Government needs to finally show
leadership, stand up to tech and say,
"Enough is enough".
Teastaíonn cothromaíocht inár gcur chuige
i
an
supporting this motion calling for the
introduction of a €500 energy credit for
households funded through a fair levy on
data centres.
As the Minister of State will know,
ordinary workers and families continue to
struggle with soaring bills while data
centres
consume almost a quarter of Ireland's
electricity.
They are driving up household energy bills
while paying much lower relative rates
than householders.
This is shocking and something over which
every Fianna Fáil and Fine Gael TD, many
of whom are fanatical about data centres
and AI, should be shouting their heads
off.
It is really shocking.
According to Eurostat figures published
earlier this year, data centres in Ireland
36.8 cent per KW paid by households.
The company Echelon Data Centres Ireland,
which is building two huge data centres in
my own backyard, just outside Arklow, had
a massive €2.5 billion valuation last
year.
All these data centres should be paying at
least the same price as the rest of us for
that is hard-pressed households in Arklow
or elsewhere in Ireland suffering from the
cost-of-living crisis.
We need to see an end to the discounted
energy rates for data centres and a
moratorium on the building of any more of
these new facilities to protect the
national grid and to meet our climate
targets.
The Government may claim there
a cost-of-living crisis anymore but
families know differently.
Every week, people are paying more for
groceries, more for fuel, more for rent
and more for energy.
Household budgets are stretched to
breaking point.
Many people are working harder than ever,
yet they are finding it increasingly
difficult to make ends meet.
We in Sinn Féin have consistently pointed
out that the cost-of-living crisis has not
gone away and that households still need
support with rising energy bills which are
among the highest in Europe, as Teachta
Doherty mentioned.
Many people are now questioning why large
energy users are not making a greater
contribution through a data centre levy
fund towards supporting the grid and
helping households with rising costs.
The revenue generated could then be
ringfenced to provide a €500 energy credit
for struggling households.
The message is very simple: ordinary
people deserve a fair deal.
Those who consume the most energy, that
is, big multinational data centres, should
make a fair contribution and that
contribution should be used to help
struggling Irish households with the
cost-of-living crisis.
thank
Deputy Boyd Barrett and colleagues for
bringing forward this motion.
The Social Democrats are very proud to
support it.
I want to make three key points in my
comments.
First, data centres are affecting our
communities and we have a duty and
responsibility as representatives to
simply reset the scales.
We have all seen research that shows the
very people who contact us worried about
how to heat their homes are facing higher
prices due to the sheer volume of data
centres in Ireland.
When an industry that has not been kept in
check has this kind of impact on ordinary
people's lives, it is our job as
policymakers to step in and do something
about it.
We know they provide little direct
employment.
We know they are part of an immensely
profitable and influential sector that can
afford to contribute a small portion of
those immense profits to mitigate these
adverse impacts on ordinary citizens.
We know that the public see an unfair
system where they are expected to scrape
national electricity, and which is
forecast to rise to one third in the next
four years, benefits from a system of
mates rates.
Ní féidir linn glacadh leis go mbeidh ar
an
seo, gan rud éigin a dhéanamh
We need a genuinely honest conversation on
data centres.
We see it time and again when reasonable
concerns and issues are raised that there
is no common sense behind the assertion
put forward by both Government and the
tech sector that if you do not support
unrestricted data centre growth, that
means you
want anyone to have internet, online
archives or technology.
There is a difference between having a
coffee in the morning and having 50
coffees.
There is a difference between having some
data centres and having so many that they
threaten our grid, disrupt our communities
and make us a "cautionary tale" according
to the United Nations.
It is also not acceptable to fudge the
numbers around the number of jobs based in
data centres to suit their narrative,
throwing out reports with outlandish
employment claims, like figures of 20,000,
that do not acknowledge the majority of
those are temporary roles for the people
building the data centres.
This undermines trust and, frankly,
indicates the cold hard facts do not
justify data centres being allowed to
operate at the scale they do in Ireland.
My final point is that data centres are a
tool that have been managed poorly.
Many useful or productive things may
require data centres but the narrative we
need to change is that because a good and
useful thing may need a data centre that
all data centres are
good and useful.
This fable means they get lower
electricity rates, the same grade
connection priority as a hospital or
school, they get to emit noise at night
which is waking up people in nearby homes,
and this happens regardless of whether
they are storing a university repository
or powering the generation of AI slop.
We have a responsibility to balance what
they want and what is good for our society
and that is a responsibility that has been
neglected for far too long.
thank People
for bringing forward this motion which we
are supporting.
I want to thank Friends of the Earth,
which has done incredible work on this in
recent months.
I highlight the report it has done which
shows how much Irish households have been
paying for the expansion of data centres.
There was €715 million more in electricity
bills between 2015 and 2023,
and it has identified that Irish
households will pay an additional almost
€1.5 billion in electricity bills due to
data centre growth.
While the Government blames war and the
Middle East for rising energy costs, on
the other hand it is sanctioning the
massive increase in data centres which is
adding to it.
What we are actually seeing here in
Ireland - and we have become a poster
child for this across the world - is the
grim reality of the AI-driven dystopian
future that the big tech trillionaires
have for us: data centres expanding across
our country at an exponential rate by
Meta, Google, Amazon, now consuming more
energy than all urban households in the
country.
What have ordinary people seen as a
result?
Higher energy costs for families who
cannot afford to put food on the table,
the guzzling of our water when we had
water shortages, eating up our renewable
energy and the gobbling up
our infrastructure resulting in delays of
much-needed housing delivery in the middle
of a housing catastrophe.
What does our Government do?
The very same thing it did with the
vulture funds - roll them in, bow down to
them and give them whatever they want and
facilitate them
cheaper electricity subsidised by the
Irish public.
It lifted the moratorium on data centres
despite being warned that data centre
expansion would make it difficult to meet
electricity demand during extreme cold
weather.
Will we see
in this country freeze
as to keep data centres running?
This is utterly dystopian.
Electricity bills have increased by 70% in
the past five years and they are going to
increase more because of data centres.
The Social Democrats believe there needs
to be a moratorium on data centres.
We believe we need to pause and look at
the impact they are having and put people,
our resources, nature and our communities
ahead of what these big tech corporations
are pushing.
We have to question
the benefits of AI.
We know people are losing their jobs.
We have the creation of AI slop so that
these data centres expand.
colleagues for tabling the motion this
evening.
It is interesting that we have set the
context that much
of the war in Ukraine and the war in the
Middle East.
You would think the energy suppliers would
start to feel that struggle as well, yet
what we are seeing is record levels of
profits among the energy suppliers.
It is impossible to defend when you do not
know where the attack is
coming from.
I am sure the Minister
this side that everything is going up.
Literally everything is going up and we
cannot understand why.
When colleagues across the House explain
why this is happening, it is blatantly
ignored to the extent that the Minister,
I thank
for being here.
I was at that public meeting in
Minister of State was last in Naas, but
is unique for many reasons.
One that it is probably not so proud of
right now is the fact that it has land
zoning specifically for data centre use.
I am not aware of any other town in this
country where lands are zoned specifically
and only for data centres to build on.
There is something significantly wrong
with that.
If nothing else comes from my input today,
I ask
to convey to the Minister a request to
issue a circular to all local authorities
to stop zoning land specifically for data
centre use.
We do not have the infrastructure, we do
not have the resources and we are having
to deny the fact that we are interfering
with economic reports because apparently
that is what happened with the Department
over the summer.
We have significant problems here.
In Naas, that is one part of it, and
a significant worry.
We have done our bit in Ireland, and we
are far in excess of holding the door open
to invite people in, while trying to keep
everybody quiet who is suffering at
the hands of it.
Some 24% of our energy use going to data
centres is wrong when we are paying
exorbitant fees.
I welcome this timely motion and its call
for a moratorium
electricity credits for families paid for
by a tax on corporations.
The other week, the energy Minister, as he
did today, made the outrageous
a fallacious argument with no merit
whatsoever.
Instead of creating hundreds of thousands
of high-paying jobs like the automotive
industry, data centres create a tiny
number, as Deputy Murphy outlined.
Instead of developing products for export,
data centres leach water and energy from
all around them.
Instead of providing economic activity,
data centres merely host electronic
transactions captured economically
elsewhere.
Data centres represent a severe economic
threat to the State,
and they are cannibalising the economy.
Every kilowatt hour spent on a data centre
is a kilowatt hour not available to a
household or
a productive part of the economy like a
pharmaceutical plant creating medicines,
or a semiconductor factory.
Data centres from one part of the economy,
in big tech, are putting critical and
important jobs in other productive sectors
of the economy, even other foreign direct
investment multinationals, at risk by
inflating costs and threatening our
ability to provide energy to our people
and businesses.
I spoke to one businessman in my
constituency this morning.
He told me his electricity bill has surged
26% and it is now putting his entire
business at risk.
Data centres now guzzle nearly half of our
renewable energy production.
Meanwhile, we are, right now,
decommissioning our only offshore wind
farm, the greatest renewable energy
resource that we have.
This Government is fuelling its own
climate and energy disaster and putting an
existential economic, environmental and
social risk at the heart of Government
policymaking.
That should change and it should
especially change in light of the climate
Anything less is negligence in the
extreme.
welcome An Coimisiún Pleanála's decision
to refuse planning for a data centre in
Mayo on climate grounds, so all hope is
not lost.
I thank People Before Profit Deputies for
tabling this really important motion.
On behalf of the Labour Party, I brought a
relatively similar motion to the House
as well as the introduction of a
moratorium on the new construction of data
centres.
I did so and I imagine that the Deputies
who are bringing forward this motion today
did so as well because we recognise that
Ireland has a growing problem with the way
our energy system is being managed.
There is a fundamental question here about
who our energy system is being built for,
who is paying for it and whether ordinary
households and small businesses are
getting a fair deal.
Ireland has some of the highest
electricity costs in Europe.
Hundreds of thousands of households are
struggling to keep up with their energy
bills.
We know that more than half a million
electricity and gas accounts are in
arrears.
Yet, at precisely the same time, we see
enormous growth in electricity demand from
one particular sector, data centres.
As is stated in the motion, they accounted
for 88% of the increase in demand
for electricity since 2015.
That is staggering.
As I have said before, I accept that data
centres, to a degree, are a part of modern
society and our industrial society.
They play a part in the digital economy
and so on.
Whenever any of us raise these concerns
about the Government's approach to data
centres and the seemingly boundless
expansion, we get these kind of strawmen
arguments saying that people use phones,
social media, and all that kind of
rubbish.
The Labour
has never argued that data centres should
not exist.
We acknowledge their place in modern
society, but we have concerns about what
is driving the current proliferation of
data centres that we are seeing, not just
in Ireland but elsewhere too, and the role
that the AI race is playing in this.
We have to question what data centres are
being used for and if we want to support
these purposes.
We spend a lot of time in this house
talking about the dangers of AI, reining
in AI and regulating the use of social
media so that it does not harm our
children.
Why, on the one hand, are we doing that,
and on the other hand, are we
facilitating and actively encouraging the
infrastructure that facilitates all of
this?
The use to which data centres are being
put has to be part of the discussion about
whether we want to continue to facilitate
them.
We have not had that discussion yet.
It is not credible for this Government to
continue to allow the expansion of data
centres without properly considering the
consequences for our society, as well as
for our electricity system, for
energy prices, for investment elsewhere in
our economy, and for our decarbonisation
efforts elsewhere in the country.
There is a simple principle here.
If a particular group of users is creating
significant additional costs for the
energy system, they should shoulder the
burden of those costs - some 88% of the
costs, you might say.
That principle is particularly important
at a time when households are struggling
The Government cannot ask families to
absorb higher energy costs while
simultaneously providing an energy system
that gives very large energy users
preferential treatment.
Recent figures show that data centres
accounted for 23% of energy consumed in
Ireland last year.
It is around 50% of the energy consumed in
Dublin.
This is an extraordinary level of demand
from a single sector and it
show any signs of slowing down.
Even when comparisons are made to
Germany's heavy industry
and the fact that we
have one, in Germany heavy industry
accounts for about 25% of energy use.
Data centres are
at that level here and all the
trajectories are that in a few years'
time, it will be a third.
When is that too much?
We are going to scale up significantly
because the de facto moratorium on new
connections for data centres
was got rid of last year.
We know the impact that this has already
had on household bills.
A Friends of the Earth report has shown us
that data centre energy demand added
hundreds of millions of euro to household
electricity bills between 2015 and 2023,
with a further €1.5 billion potentially
being added over the coming decade.
That amounts to about a week's wages for a
low-paid worker being added to
every household in the country.
We also have the extraordinary situation
where households can be paying
substantially more for their electricity
per unit than large data centres.
Fundamentally, if large energy users are
placing additional demands on the
electricity network, they should be making
a contribution that reflects those
demands.
We should be placing a levy on their
energy consumption.
It is some form of punishment or some
anti-technology or anti-business measure.
It is just about basic fairness.
It is a fact that data centre demand is
contributing to higher system costs and
higher electricity prices, so the
companies benefiting from that demand
should contribute towards the cost.
The money raised through such a levy, as
the motion here calls for, should be used
to help
address the costs being experienced
elsewhere in the system, including
supports for households struggling with
their energy bills.
I might have suggested a more targeted
approach for the energy credits than is
put forward in this motion, but we are
arguing over minutiae here.
The principle is the same, and we need to
make sure that those who
are forcing the country to have these
costs are paying their fair share.
Hundreds of thousands of households are
struggling to keep up with their
electricity and gas bills.
Their wages are being swallowed up by
rent, mortgages, food and transport; take
your pick.
Energy is just the latest one of those.
No one is presenting energy credits as a
substitute for fixing Ireland's energy
system.
That is the other thing to say.
Such is the extent of the energy crisis
that immediate assistance is desperately
needed for households up and down the
country while we deal with the underlying
problem.
We need to address why our energy is so
expensive in the first place.
Everyone in the House knows what we need
to do, that is, rapidly scale up renewable
generation.
We are miles and miles off target for our
offshore wind generation.
We are doing well on solar, but we have to
do better on offshore wind.
That is where the real gains can be.
Electricity demand is skyrocketing
precisely because of all the data centres
that are being
If renewable electricity is absorbed
almost entirely by the new demand from
data centres, then that renewable
electricity cannot simultaneously help us
electrify transport, decarbonise industry
or move households away from fossil fuels.
Almost all new renewable energy that is
being generated onshore in this country
through wind and solar is being gobbled up
by data centres.
It is affecting our efforts to decarbonise
elsewhere in our economy.
We cannot ignore that.
While this motion is primarily about
energy and affordability, there is an
important climate dimension to it as well.
We cannot separate the two.
A secure energy system has to be a cleaner
energy system, and a cleaner energy system
has to work for households.
The Labour Party supports calls for a
moratorium on further data centre
expansion until and unless we have
sufficient renewable generation and grid
capacity to accommodate new demand without
putting upward pressure on household bills
or undermining our climate objectives.
We need to get the fundamentals of our
energy system right before we can allow
for unfettered increases in demand.
Data centres need to make their fair
contribution toward both supporting
needed to support a
cleaner, more secure energy system for
everyone.
That is how we build a system that works
for the whole country.
It
have to be a choice between economic
development and climate action, but we
have to carefully manage scarce energy
resources and ensure that economic
development does not come at the expense
of households or our climate.
support this motion in principle.
I have a couple of queries about what is
implementable and what is not, but the
hard-pressed people of Ireland, faced with
rising costs, need a little bit more help
in terms of energy prices at the moment
while also trying to move toward a
more sustainable future.
For many years, people in Ireland have
been told that our electricity bills,
which
are now the third highest in the European
Union, are simply the result of
international factors beyond our control.
In some ways, that is true.
Looking at gas, which
about to get on to, global gas prices have
risen internationally and conflict has
contributed to that.
The reason we are dependent on gas is
because the electricity market operates on
the system of marginal pricing, which
means that the most expensive form of
power needed to meet demand at any given
time sets the price for 100% of the
Right now, we are dependent on fossil gas
for that.
In the future, it could be
If I have time,
outline a couple of suggestions, which may
already be in the Government mindset, but
it is the pace I am worried about.
Why are we burning so much gas when we
have all this existing wind potential?
I have mentioned wave and tidal before.
The answer right now lies in the
uninhibited growth of data centres, which
are consuming nearly a quarter of our
metered electricity in this State, which
matches the usage of every single
residential home in Ireland.
These data centres are operating 365
basically.
The demand is completely inflexible, so
when the wind stops blowing, that baseload
does not end up dropping.
Instead, we are forced to fire up the gas
generators -
and has cost implications, has been
referenced as well -
to keep the data centre servers cool.
Under the market rules, the gas does not
just price electricity for the tech
giants.
Rather, it prices electricity for the
family trying to heat their home in
Clondalkin, Saggart, Rathcoole, Lucan,
Adamstown, Brittas, Palmerstown or
elsewhere throughout the country.
Data centre demand has inflated wholesale
electricity prices by up to 8.5%, maybe
more, which
the average household
in recent years as part of a rise in
energy and household
prices.
We cannot look at data centre policy on
its own and energy policy
separately.
They are together.
The current trajectory is placing an
unfair tax, for want of a better term, on
Irish families to subsidise what is still
an unsustainable demand on our grid.
If the data centres were not there in the
first place, a lot more of our supply
would be provided by renewables and we
have the same dependence on gas.
We need to review the data centre grid
connections.
There is already another application in my
constituency
for a licence to the
EPA.
The message has not gone out to these
companies yet, and I
think
Government policy to say that it is an
unwelcome place for data centres.
I have mentioned before the brave new
future where we could be producing so much
excess capacity that we could afford to
operate data centres and be the data
centre hub of Europe as one of the major
energy producers.
There is huge revenue potential,
irrespective of the fairly
minuscule job creation element associated
with them.
As of now, we are going to have to work
within Europe to reform the marginal
pricing system that is penalising
consumers for the corporate energy demands
of multinationals.
It is penalising the producers of
renewable energy, basically.
The figures are staggering.
When a single sector consumes nearly a
quarter of our national electricity and
ordinary families face a crushing
cost-of-living crisis, it beggars
belief.
I am kind of lost for words in terms of
how to put it, but if you ask an ordinary
constituent whether they feel
been fleeced by data centres, they would
say, "Absolutely".
They feel
not getting the support.
The Government supports for electricity
pricing over the last couple of years were
very welcome.
The
fuel allowances are very welcome.
One half of me says
I do not like subsidising fossil fuels to
keep
cars and buses going.
Another part of me acknowledges that some
of the electricity produced is from fossil
fuel as well.
We need to reduce our dependence on these
supplies and reduce our carbon
emissions.
When you look at what is actually
impacting on people in their bottom
pocket, you have to take a two-pronged
approach.
Even if we need to borrow strategically to
create that energy self-sufficiency, it
I have a couple of queries about the
specific mechanisms in this motion in
terms of legal hurdles, which give the
Government an excuse to do nothing.
From the research I have done, a
legislative ban would violate Article
49 of the EU treaty on the freedom of
establishment.
That would leave the State vulnerable to
court action and multibillion
euro damages claims.
This electricity levy to raise the €500
would also violate EU
Regulation 2019/943 on non-discriminatory
grid access.
In terms of ring-fencing money directly
for
household credit, that would clash with
our own Constitution in terms of where
taxes are collected and how they are
distributed.
However, that does not mean that the
sentiment of this motion is not 100%
right.
We have to find a work-around so that we
do not have legalese blocking Government
action.
To achieve the goals through legally
enforceable pathways, there might be a
couple of other approaches, such as
legally codifying the strictest possible
version of the CRU's large energy users
policy and mandating that no data centre
can connect to the grid unless it has its
own off-grid supply of battery storage
and is relying 100% on renewables.
Personally, I do not think any new data
centre should be built for the next ten
years until we get to a point where we are
more comfortable in our energy
generation.
We could still levy some corporation tax
off these companies, as it stands, to
make sure that Irish families get some
sort of a subsidy.
We are at a critical juncture in terms of
our energy self-sufficiency and our
potential.
What would get rid of our dependence on
gas as the baseline?
If we put the investment in, mass battery
storage would be one
element to store all the daytime wind,
solar,
tidal and wave, which
not even properly investing in, and
replace the gas plants during evening
peaks.
The creation of new interconnectors would
create further links to France
and the UK.
If we have to import cheap nuclear or
solar power from Spain when the domestic
wind is low, so be it.
Until we get to the point where we are
producing three or four times our actual
needs, it will be a quid pro quo and we
will benefit from that.
That means we have to overbuild our own
capacity for wind as well as for tidal
and wave so that the grid is always
renewable no matter what.
Even on low-wind days when
taking the solar from Spain, the pricing
will be fixed in such a way that
not dependent on fossils to set it.
We could look at fixed-price contracts to
have steady lower rates
of renewable developers for decades.
That could be done at EU level, bypassing
the market price on a day-to-day basis
for fossil fuels.
While it would be more expensive to
implement now, green hydrogen is also a
solution.
Once you get to the point where you have
built your hydrogen infrastructure and it
is produced from excess renewables
then
hydrogen can also replace gas to make sure
we do not have any kind of winter
blackouts.
I am foreseeing that will be a
2030s and as we move into the 2040s, if we
put the
investment in.
As Deputy Heneghan has so eloquently said
so often, we have to get the grid right
and allow the private generators and home
generators to
access and share the energy and have a
more sustainable
individual, local grid as well as having
one big national one that is upscaled
for renewable generation off the west
coast which is not the case now.
If we put in all that work, which will
cost tens of billions,
that will reap rewards.
We will be the energy Arabs of Europe in
the 2040s at a time when
other countries will need access to that
energy, not only for heating
and transport but also for cooling
depending on how the climate change
situation goes.
It will all
have lowered our carbon emissions to
virtually nothing.
We have the potential if
have the vision.
Profit for bringing this issue before the
Dáil.
Electricity and electricity affordability
is probably my favourite topic to discuss.
I studied
DCU for five years and my thesis
on waste heat utilisation from data
centres.
Sometimes I hear people in this House
speaking about data centres and the water
they use.
They are not looking at the statistics.
I am not defending that they do use a lot
of water
but I note the recent
report
With my politics, I am always talking
about the current problem we face and what
solutions we can bring.
In the case of data centres,
we can use waste heat from
data centres for a district heating system
using a central pump to
supply heat at a reduced cost to nearby
buildings.
I would love to see
at a faster rate.
I commend everyone at district heating
Ireland on the work they are doing.
I support 100% the
parts of the motion on electricity
affordability especially those referring
to disabled
to protecting jobs, the next budget needs
to
support businesses in retrofitting,
transitioning and installing renewables.
This is particularly
SMEs and local businesses as rising energy
costs have affected a lot of businesses.
I will continue to push for
For households, electricity is often
essential for
medical equipment.
That equipment cannot simply be switched
off and is often life-saving.
However, I will not support the motion.
It is not that I
share the concerns about
data
I am not persuaded that the proposed levy
provides a sound basis for recurring
household support but am reminded of the
old saying:
“Give a man a fish, feed him for a day;
teach him how to fish, feed him for life”.
Rather than
a once-off €500 electricity credit, for
the same price you could provide nearly
every household
a plug-in solar system.
In conjunction with a battery, that would
have a ten-year lifespan and
constantly reduce a household’s energy
bill.
This would be in circuit, built in.
I agree hardship does not require us to
agree on this, but while what is outlined
in the motion and the €500 credit would
provide immediate relief, what we should
do is invest in all reliefs for what will
come in the future.
We need immediate protection and also
lasting change.
green hydrogen, as Deputy Gogarty said,
would do.
Ireland is in a unique position because of
our seabed and the potential of ORE.
If another country such as Germany, which
was mentioned
multiple times, had the potential we have
it would seize it.
From looking at records, I understand we
had a lot of plans for our ORE.
Sadly, the crash occurred and many of
those fell through.
We did have the only successful sale of an
ORE system in the EU last year
off the
I do not agree with a current one-off
payment.
I would like to see multiple payments for
plug-in solar, batteries and smarter
grids.
We could give a €400 electrical readiness
credit towards assessments.
I
want that to be used as a gazumping method
by electricians as we have seen with BER
ratings and solar installations.
I am thinking of a €400 electrical
readiness credit by an electrical
protective devices in the fuse-box for a
plug-in solar system, or maybe change one
breaker to make every house compatible or
make apartment buildings compatible.
We might change the laws to
that every single apartment dwelling be
allowed to use plug-in solar or have solar
systems on the rooftops.
If
not allow people who are renting to have
access to renewable energy that is not a
fair society.
We
see what Germany has done very
successfully with plug-in solar systems.
There were witnesses on this before the
climate and energy committee before
recess.
If
going to do a pilot scheme of these
systems,
priority as well as elderly people and
those with a disability and there
should be a workable arrangement for
renters.
battery storage
in the House.
Before recess, I invited Energy Storage
Ireland
the audiovisual room.
We had a great discussion on the potential
of batteries to act
as storage systems for the curtailment and
dispatch down that we see constantly.
That needs to be addressed.
A panel can generate electricity when the
sun shines and a wind turbine
when the wind blows but a battery can help
a household
If used smartly batteries can be used when
the cost is higher.
If they are
needed, smartly and with new systems being
used with these batteries, it can really
help people who are struggling.
The headline warnings I saw recently
regarding electricity underline how solar
export payments need
a clearer policy.
If people have invested thousands of euro
in solar systems in the
belief that they will be able to sell back
to the grid at a certain price, but other
EU countries are warning that the price
for selling it back to the grid will be
reduced, that
needs to look at now.
Those reports have
been brought to the climate and energy
committee and I look forward to discussing
I
brought forward a Bill on data centres and
what I would like to see
being done at a faster rate.
If data centres
or any
LEU, across the country had an easier
route to use solar, renewables or
hydrotreated vegetable oil, HVO, to supply
on-site generation at an easier rate, it
would be very beneficial
public.
anyone who is struggling at the moment
to hear about solar farms or wind farms
waiting months for
connection.
The CRU needs to examine this.
It also needs to examine the tariffs
that
reflect the value of exported electricity
and where customers can benefit from
choosing their input and export providers
separately like in any market.
to professors
I refer to data centres,
the Government-commissioned study and the
jobs associated with construction that
have been referred to.
Some of my friends work in that industry,
including
the supply chain of development,
construction and the wider spending
effects.
Some of those jobs in data centres
but they do represent a significant
economic activity.
Ireland's wider multinational economy
has supported this
but not every single project is justified.
Looking at the programme for Government,
one of the things I was very happy to have
helped negotiate was that data centres
should be encouraged to use renewable
energy.
I favour and will continue to favour
I do not think a blanket ban can
distinguish between projects on that
basis.
Likewise,
the 20% levy, while a levy should be
examined,
this one should
immediately be examined without a
discussion that ultimately speaks to
investment and the tax revenue of this
my
Bill for the last minute
I have.
I believe that it will help connect
additional renewable energy to the nearby
demand, not only for data centres but also
for energy sharing for a school that has
solar panels and in the
nearby nursing home or GAA club.
We have one DSO.
We need multiple DSOs, like other
countries, because an energy monopoly is
not good.
I welcome the Government's emphasis on
permanent supports; now I want delivery.
Those proposals need
to face measurable results.
I favour the immediate help and I hope
that in the coming months we see
plug-in solar rolled out, like the UK
Government did on 27 August.
Also, I would like clarity from the
Department on
if someone is to order a plug-in solar
system and plug it in now, that makes them
a criminal for wanting to reduce their
electricity bills.
I commend and welcome the discussion on
I
always love to debate energy in this
House.
the
many
Deputies across the House for their
contribution to this debate and for the
welcome opportunity, through the motion
put forward by Deputy Boyd Barrett, to
discuss the pressures households are
facing as a result of very high energy
costs.
The Government is deeply aware
and concerned about the pressures placed
on households and businesses by high
energy costs.
Providing supports to alleviate this
pressure has
and will continue to be a priority.
The Government is taking action to help
households and businesses with the cost of
fuel and energy and has been proactive in
introducing support measures on fuel costs
and supports for the transport, farming
and fisheries sectors.
This is in addition to the range of
measures in budget 2026 aiming to help
households with energy costs, which
included extending the reduced VAT rate on
gas and electricity, enhanced social
protection payments and record funding for
Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland
retrofit schemes.
The Minister, Deputy O'Brien, earlier
outlined the significant funding made
available for retrofit schemes and the
increased number of applications.
The benefit of even simple upgrades like
adding insulation, cavity wall or external
wall insulation, cannot be dismissed.
It can improve the warmth and comfort of
the home while reducing energy costs.
The
Minister has engaged with energy suppliers
and the energy regulator to ensure that
consumers, particularly vulnerable
customers, are protected.
The CRU has a wide range of protections in
place for
customers experiencing difficulties in
paying their bills.
Each year, it carries out a review on the
effectiveness
of customer protection measures over the
past winter as well as deciding the
measures to be retained for the
forthcoming winter.
Some of the key measures that remained in
place over recent years included a
disconnection moratorium, reduced debt
repayments and discounted tariffs for
customers on financial hardship meters.
The CRU will publish measures in the
coming weeks, ahead of this winter.
Anyone who is struggling with their bill
is strongly encouraged to engage with
their supplier.
Suppliers will not disconnect customers
who engage.
It is also important to note that
switching supplier or plan could save the
average electricity customer hundreds of
euro on an annual electricity bill.
I strongly encourage consumers to seek out
the best prices available.
With regard to high energy prices, there
are
structural factors.
Ireland is import dependent for energy,
making it particularly vulnerable to price
volatility in the wholesale gas market.
Ireland's isolated island location, low
levels of interconnection, widely
dispersed low-density population and
reliance on fossil fuels are also
important price determinants.
Energy is central to every social and
economic activity in Ireland, but we
remain too dependent on imported fossil
fuels.
The energy crisis caused by the conflict
in the Middle East highlights why we must
reduce our reliance on imported fossil
fuels and develop our own energy through
our security and strength.
As an island nation with limited fossil
fuel reserves, this means developing our
own abundant renewable energy resources
and deepening our interconnection with
trusted European peers.
The national energy affordability task
force has been established by
Government to identify, assess and
implement measures that will enhance
energy affordability for households and
businesses while delivering key renewable
commitments and protecting security of
supply and economic stability.
The first report of the task force,
published last November, set out measures
for consideration in the budget 2026
process.
The task force is working intensively on
an energy affordability action plan, which
will be submitted to
Government in the coming weeks.
Data centres are a critical component of
Ireland's economic and digital present and
future and a key part of our value
proposition for foreign direct investment.
Data centres strengthen Ireland's position
as a strategic knowledge-intensive
regional hub for the ICT sector and
support broader retention and expansion of
existing investment that supports billions
in annual economic value for Ireland via
high-wage employment, tax receipts and
supplier ecosystems.
Ireland's industrial electricity demand is
primarily concentrated in our digital
economy.
This is our core energy-intensive industry
and should be regarded as such.
It is evident that future economic
opportunities will be underpinned by
energy-intensive digitalisation.
The Government believes that these
opportunities should be capitalised on in
a planned and sustainable manner in line
with Ireland's decarbonisation, energy
security and affordability objectives.
The Government's large energy user action
plan, LEAP, published in January
this year, supports this.
It sets out a plan-led approach for very
large and energy-intensive investments,
which, due to scale and energy
consumption, will benefit from
co-ordinated national infrastructure
planning.
LEAP represents a key strategic industrial
policy in support of the Government's
objective to accelerate renewable
deployment, expedite grid investment and
streamline planning for the next wave of
industrial development.
Alongside LEAP, the CRU large energy user
connection policy establishes a pathway
for new data centres to seek connection to
the electricity system that addresses
security-of-supply risks and system
constraints and promotes renewable energy
targets.
Electricity network tariffs are set every
year by the CRU to recover the cost of
developing, operating and maintaining the
electricity grid.
They fund a grid that is more resilient to
storms and supplies electricity to a
growing population, new housing and
expanding businesses.
Extra-large energy users like data centres
have in recent years seen large increases
in network costs, with an average increase
of 175% compared with a 45%
increase for domestic customers
between 2020 and 2026.
The Government remains committed to
delivering a balanced approach to
facilitate data centre demand while also
ensuring overall energy security and
affordability for consumers and
businesses.
The Government will continue to actively
monitor the current geopolitical situation
and the impact on energy markets and
remains ready to respond as circumstances
evolve.
Again, I thank Deputies from across the
House for their contributions today.
However,
do not accept the motion before the House
and present the Government's countermotion
in its place.
The debate we are having here is a very
important one.
It is probably the most important one that
is in the Dáil this week for the simple
fact that energy, how it is charged for,
how it is priced, who
has access to it and who generates it will
be a key issue as we move forward.
By any standard, we are in an
extraordinary situation because of the
extraordinary number of data centres we
have compared with other EU countries -
ten times more, on average.
We must take into account that a lot of
American states
now resisting the location of data centres
in them.
Ireland is becoming the favoured home for
them and now we have 120.
I am not saying that data centres are a
bad thing
but this is a really extraordinary
situation, and it is going
to become worse.
The Government will highlight the jobs,
and there are some jobs, but
a few thousand
It is not the tens of thousands of jobs
the Minister is outlining as permanent
jobs in these data centres.
That is the reality.
If you look at the usage of electricity,
almost a quarter of
electricity
publicly available on the grid
due to rise to over 30% in the coming four
to five years.
Data centres are using the same amount of
electricity as over 2 million households
in the State.
It is putting huge pressure on the grid
and
Government knows that.
It is creating pressure for demand and
putting huge pressure for investment.
The grid is simply not able to take what
is there.
Who is footing the bill for the upgrade?
Householders are shouldering the heaviest
burden because they are paying the highest
They are paying a grid improvement levy as
well.
A recent Friends of the Earth report
estimates
that households forked out
€263
from 2021 to 2023 to pay for the
additional costs
of the load being put on the grid and
usage by data centres.
On the costs, we are told by successive
Government analyses that creating
so-called competition in the electricity
market would lower prices.
This is what we were told back in the
and nineties.
We have the competition now, but we have
highest prices.
We
have one of the lowest.
We had the third or fourth lowest in the
European Union.
We were almost at the bottom at one stage.
Now we are at the top of it.
When
was the sole supplier we had the cheapest
rate in the EU.
The competition worked the opposite way
because there is a profit margin.
Who has the profit margin?
The owners of the large electricity
companies
I do not have a problem with the ESB
because we owned it.
However, the facts are the other ones in
the so-called market are creaming it off.
On average we are paying 38% higher prices
than other EU states and the average
across Europe.
The Government needs to introduce a
consumption levy, and it certainly needs
to be considered on data centres.
They are getting cut-price electricity.
They are making large profits.
It can be done.
We need to start thinking about low- and
middle-income households.
Government is fond of talking about people
who get up every morning, middle Ireland
and everything else.
I think middle Ireland are
on less than €75,000 gross.
We need to improve the solar panel grants
for homes so people can afford
them, and grade the cost as income goes
down in a household so those with lower
incomes get the best benefit or
free altogether.
Certainly, we need to target workers in
what Government likes to talk about as the
middle-income bracket.
We need to introduce plug-in solar.
That can be done.
For low-income households
solar is a quick and easy win to reduce
the amount of electricity
being used.
That is a key issue here.
Along with reducing the price rate we need
to reduce the amount being used.
We need to accelerate and increase the
number of homes being retrofitted.
I will make one point
I was contacted by the principal of a
national school yesterday morning.
The school got solar panels in the past
two years.
It is concerned now by reports that
the electricity it is feeding back into
the grid.
It is not going to get the credits on
that.
The Minister of State might take that away
for the Government to deal with because a
lot of people added solar panels on the
basis that
going to reduce the cost of the amount
they were using themselves, and to
sustainably generate a bit of electricity.
They are selling that to companies, and
now the private companies are going to get
that
free.
The point he is making is that the
Government subsidised it and householders
paid for it as well.
Government and householders paid for it.
Is it
going to be fed back into grid for the
private companies to receive
free of charge and make super profits on
it?
It is perverse what is going to happen.
Government needs to take that into
account, particularly the schools
situation and that of householders.
I ask
to take that back to his Government
colleagues to get it dealt with because we
should not allow that to happen.
People put them up in good faith and we
break that faith with people.
I start by saying this to everybody who
is impacted by the cost-of-living crisis,
the
cost of energy, childcare,
the failure of wages to keep pace with the
cost of living, inflation,
the cost of groceries and by the inequity
we see highlighted
in this motion and to those who are
suffering as a result of the
cost-of-living crisis as opposed to those
who are profiteering out of it, they
should get out on the streets this weekend
and demand a change in this Government's
priorities in advance of the budget.
Those who are doing that will be
assembling at the Garden of Remembrance at
1 o'clock in the Affordable Ireland
demonstration.
The reason they should do it is because
despite the fact that it has a three and a
half
page amendment
explaining why it is not going to accept
our
motion, fails to answer or address in any
serious way, or at
all, the central point of the motion.
Why is it that data centres owned by some
of richest people in
the world, making extraordinary profits,
are paying half the rate
per unit of electricity as is being paid
by ordinary working people
and householders who are being hammered
with the cost of living?
How could that be, and why is the
Government going to maintain
that status quo?
That in effect means those who are
struggling to pay their energy bills are
subsidising the data centres whose owners
are making obscene profits while those
data centres are directly
contributing to the inability of
households to pay their bills.
We now have a credible estimate that 8.5%
of your electricity bill
is as a result of data centres hoovering
up the electricity
and making you pay more while they pay
half the rate.
One could not make it up, but of course it
speaks to something wider in this country.
There is no cost-of-living crisis for the
big corporations, the multinationals and
speculators and the super-rich.
They are profiting from the cost-of-living
misery that ordinary people are suffering
and the Government is maintaining this
status quo.
Even if it has dire consequences for the
environment and the
economic well-being of ordinary people, it
is determined
to maintain that unjust status quo.
If the plight of people struggling with
the cost of living does not move this
Government, it should maybe consider what
newspapers like the Financial Times are
saying because all of this is
infrastructure for AI.
The Financial Times is now saying that the
entire American economy is one
big gamble on AI, and
now being told by the AI tech bros that it
could destroy humanity.
By the way, that is scaremongering at one
level, but anybody seriously
looking at it
is because the AI bubble may be about to
burst and they are looking for a bailout.
Yet again, they are looking for a bailout
so that ordinary people will pay the bill.
Our economy, more than any other, is a big
gamble on AI and the tech
bros.
That is a very dangerous thing for the
future of our economy and ordinary people
are
picking up the bill.
It is obvious the Government is not
listening and is committed to putting the
tech bros and billionaires before the
needs of ordinary people and that is why
we need to get out on the streets this
weekend, and why the workers balloting for
strike action are absolutely right to do
so.
This Topical Issue is about the fare
hikes - or the unfair hikes, as we might
call them.
The people who live in my constituency
already had their fares jacked up.
Those who get the train from Balbriggan or
Skerries were taken out of the Dublin
That was only last year.
We now have a situation whereby they will
be asked to pay more.
They are not getting any extra services;
not an additional carriage will be added.
The Government was very clear about that.
They will get nothing extra but will pay
more for the joy of squashing onto
overcrowded trains and standing at the
side of the road while ghost buses do not
turn up.
It is not fair.
Added to that, we had the NTA at the
committee this morning speaking to all the
Government backbenchers who, God love
them, are outraged at this but prepared to
do absolutely nothing about it.
The NTA confirmed this will not be for
additional services.
The Taoiseach was quite wrong when he told
me it would be for additional services.
The NTA was clear there
people getting public transport.
The Government does not give people an
opportunity to get public transport unless
it invests in it.
It is not investing in it; it is just
charging people more.
It is a political decision, not a decision
of the NTA.
The Government can reverse it
People are struggling with the cost of
living, including the cost of getting
in and out of work and of transport
generally, and we
need to increase the number of people
using public transport for climate
reasons.
The Government's response
to
increase fares to make the cost-of-living
situation worse for people and
reduce the number of people using public
transport.
The first point is self-evident: the 15%
increase is a significant hit
for people who use public transport,
particularly working people
who use it day in, day out.
We now have
confirmed by the NTA - which is absolutely
extraordinary - that it took this
decision knowing it would reduce the
number of people using the public
transport system, when everybody is
supposed to be committed to increasing the
use of public transport to reduce
congestion and to assist
with climate action.
How can
justify that?
It is beyond belief.
It must be that the Government does not
want people to use public transport.
The Tánaiste told us we would have a
budget for people who get up early in
the morning
not if
train.
The Government is saying those people will
pay more than an extra
€100 per year for the privilege of being
on public transport that is
inadequate and overcrowded.
In the middle of a cost-of-living crisis,
they are expected to fork out over €100
more per year.
The NTA acknowledges fewer people will use
public transport as a result.
They will still have to go to work,
college and so on.
How
they get there?
The Government is pushing people out of
public transport
into cars in the middle of a climate
crisis, which is incredible.
This is
100% a political choice.
A different political choice is possible.
The cost of undoing this and not going
ahead is €70 million.
In the previous budget, the Government
gave over €300 million in a special tax
break to Google, about €400 million in a
VAT cut to apartment developers and about
€700 million to the fast food giants.
To reverse this cut and go in the right
direction, we should reduce fares and move
towards free public transport, which is
what we need.
People are protesting.
They were outside the Dáil today at 6 p.m.
They will be on the streets again on
Saturday at 1 p.m.
in Parnell Square to build more and more
pressure on the Government to reverse this
hike.
thank the Deputies for submitting this
Topical
Issue, which I am taking on behalf of
the Minister for Transport,
he nor his officials are involved in the
day-to-day operation of public transport
services.
The NTA has statutory responsibility for
securing the provision of public passenger
transport services nationally, working
with the public transport operators, who
deliver the services and have
responsibility for day-to-day operational
matters.
The NTA also has statutory responsibility
for the regulation of fares charged to
passengers in respect of public transport
services provided under public service
obligation,
contracts.
In its capacity as fare regulator, the NTA
under its responsibilities within the
Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008 made
the decision to publish a new fares
from January 2027.
This is a critical step in standardisation
of the national fares structure and in
line with the national fares strategy
published in 2023 with the key objective
of the strategy providing more equitable
and consistent structure for all PSO
services.
Since 2022, we have seen inflation of
almost 21%, which has driven up the cost
of operating subsidised public transport
services with fuel, vehicle maintenance
and staff costs.
In the same period, public transport fares
have decreased through various measures
such as the 20% cost-of-living discount,
the young adult card discount of 50%
and the extension of free travel to
children under the age of nine.
This has widened the gap between what it
costs to run services and the revenue
fares bring in.
All the while, the NTA is seeking to
continue with a significant expansion and
enhancement of services.
There is a requirement to strike the right
balance in public transport fares to
enable further enhancements to the public
transport network in the coming years,
offer the most competitive fares to
younger and student passengers and ensure
value for money of the PSO subsidy to
society.
Fare revenue covers approximately 38% of
the cost of operating PSO services
nationally, compared to a 44% European
average, with the remaining costs funded
by the Exchequer.
While 2026 saw a substantial increase in
Exchequer funding, continued inflationary
pressures have increased the cost of
operating public transport services, which
has limited the NTA’s ability to improve
services or
new services to the Transport for Ireland
network as part of wider capital
investment under the national development
plan.
Ireland has maintained an effective
eight-year fare freeze alongside targeted
affordability measures, including the
young adult card, free travel for children
up to nine, and the 90-minute fare.
These measures compare favourably with
international practice and will continue
to provide substantial support to
passengers in 2027.
The adjustments to fares are required to
help offset the cost increases of recent
years, improve fare revenue recovery and
ensure the sustainability of the PSO
funding.
It is important to note that every euro
raised through fares goes directly back
into the network, supporting better
reliability, frequency and capacity and
continued roll-out of BusConnects,
Connecting Ireland and DART+.
I have no doubt the Deputies will
understand that maintaining affordable
fares must be balanced with ensuring a
financially sustainable transport system
capable of funding service improvements,
network expansion and fleet investment.
It is very brave of
to compare us to Europe.
If he wants to go down that road, it will
be a shame on him and his Government - let
us be honest.
He said he is maintaining affordable
fares.
Of course
not; he is increasing the fares.
He also tells us there will be significant
expansion and enhancement of services but
it has been confirmed that these unfair
fare hikes will just
tread water.
It will be the status quo.
They are not for new services, so my
constituents will pay more again this year
for the pleasure and the privilege of
being on overcrowded trains or standing on
the side of the road waiting for buses
that do not turn up.
This is nothing short of a disgrace and it
will be resisted.
We have time between now and when the
fares are due to go up.
This will be resisted.
Of course we need to dramatically increase
the investment in public
transport.
We are more than in favour of this.
The absence or
inadequacy of public transport in many
parts of the country, and particularly
The idea it should be paid for by hiking
up fares for people struggling
with a cost-of-living crisis in a way that
the NTA itself says
will deter people from using public
transport is unbelievable.
It has admitted that for every 10%
3% fewer people will use public transport.
The Government is driving them out of
public transport and into cars.
How can it possibly justify
this?
in a way,
an envious position.
It has the capacity, in terms of a massive
budget surplus, to protect people from the
cost-of-living crisis.
It is probably a position that governments
across the world would like to be in.
The Government can protect people from the
cost-of-living crisis but instead chooses
to impose extra costs on people.
It is quite incredible.
It is a targeted attack on those people
who use public transport.
It makes no sense from the point of view
of the cost-of-living crisis as it is
going to make it worse and it makes no
sense from the point of view of the
climate crisis as it will make it worse.
The main thing I would say is pressurise,
pressurise, pressurise.
Put pressure on those backbench TDs who
tell you that they agree with you, and
that they will raise it with their
Government colleagues, to show it in terms
of the position they
take on the budget if the Government does
not provide the money.
the three Deputies for their contributions
and for raising this Topical
Issue.
I assure them that the Government is
strongly committed to providing all
citizens with reliable and realistic
sustainable mobility options, and public
transport plays a key role in the delivery
of this goal.
To support this objective, in budget 2026
the Department of Transport secured €940
million of funding for public service
obligation and TFI Local Link services.
This is a significant 43% uplift, an
increase from €658.4 million
in 2025.
As I said earlier, Ireland's package of
fare measures compares very favourably
with many international peers.
The challenge is to balance affordability
for passengers with the long-term
financial sustainability needed to expand
and improve public transport services.
The NTA has identified approximately 140
new service initiatives and capacity
enhancements as part of its 2027 budget
submission to the Department of Transport.
Subject to the outcome of the annual
Estimates process, this represents the
biggest in-year and year-on-year
enhancement of services for many years.
The changes also represent an important
step towards standardising fares
nationwide in line with the national fares
strategy published in 2023.
The Government and the Department of
Transport, in partnership with the NTA and
operators, remain fully committed to
delivering a public transport system that
is reliable, accessible, affordable, and
capable of meeting the growing needs
of communities across the country.
It is, therefore, essential that the
public transport system remains well
funded and responsive to passenger needs
and adequate fare revenue is critical to
support this.
thank the three Deputies for raising
I want to raise the issue of generational
renewal and,
specifically, the need for a farm
succession scheme.
We have been talking about the age profile
of Irish farming for many years
but the figures tell us that we simply
have not shifted the dial.
Only around 4.3% of Irish farm holders are
under the age of
35 while almost 38% are over 65.
This should be a concern to all of us who
want to see the future of
the farm family succeed.
na Feirme, which represents more than
16,000 young farmers and
young rural people throughout the country,
has consistently highlighted this issue.
Its straightforward message is that young
people want to farm but access to land,
finance and timely succession can remain a
major barrier.
In the past we have tried different
approaches.
We had installation aid for young farmers
and we had the early retirement scheme.
More recently we introduced farm
succession partnerships, which provide a
tax credit of up to €25,000 over five
years.
We have other supports, such as the young
farmer scheme, complementary income
support for young farmers, the national
reserve and enhanced TAMS.
In the past few years we have had the
succession planning advice grant,
came in during Deputy McConalogue's time
as Minister for agriculture.
These are all valuable supports but the
age profiles tell us they have
not been
collectively.
The commission on generational renewal has
given us
a substantial body of work and
Among the proposals are the establishment
of a €25,000 payment
to establish a young farmer and a
generational renewal payment of up to
€25,000 for an older farmer transferring
the farm.
I appreciate that a comprehensive farm
succession scheme may not be achievable in
this budget but could a commitment be
given that we will now design
a proper
succession scheme?
We
learn from the shortcomings of the other
retirement schemes and establish a clear
pathway towards implementation.
Ultimately
the incentive has to be strong enough to
encourage succession not when a farmer
to invest,
develop the
farm and build a future
raising this very important issue and for
his advocacy on behalf of the agricultural
sector and young farmers in particular.
The challenge of generational renewal in
farming is widely recognised at national
and EU levels.
The programme for Government prioritises
supporting intergenerational farm
succession.
Food Vision 2030, our shared strategy for
the agrifood sector, states that
generational renewal in farming is
critically important to ensure the future
viability and social sustainability of the
Irish agrifood sector and of rural
Ireland.
This is a clear and fundamental point on
which we all agree.
There are a number of supports for
generational renewal available to farmers
These supports are complemented by a suite
of strong national taxation measures,
access to finance supports, and advisory,
education and training supports.
It is important that we have skilled,
innovative young farmers coming into the
sector to secure a viable and sustainable
future for farming in the country.
We recognise the need to consider whether
existing supports are having the desired
effect and how supports might best be
configured for the future.
farm succession is a complex issue and
there are many factors that impact
farmers' decisions.
This is why the Commission on Generational
Renewal in Farming was established
towards the end of my term as Minister.
The commission adopted an objective,
evidence-based approach
to examining all the factors involved and
engaged closely with stakeholders.
It produced a thorough analysis and made
31 recommendations across a wide range of
areas, including CAP supports, pensions,
taxation, access to finance, access to
land, collaborative arrangements, advisory
services, education and training, gender
This work will ensure that Ireland has a
well-researched basis to make optimal use
of the policy tools available to encourage
young people, who are the lifeblood of
farming, into the sector.
It ensures we have a comprehensive,
well-considered foundation for future
policy on generational renewal.
An implementation group in the Department
of agriculture has considered the
recommendations and progress is being
monitored on an ongoing basis.
Some of the recommendations may be
commenced in the short term but some will
be more medium term.
The current CAP is fully programmed.
Recommendations around CAP supports will
have to be considered in the context of
the next round, post 2027.
This is a point Deputy Dolan made in his
contribution.
Some recommendations on taxation have
already been implemented and more are
being examined in the context of the next
budget.
In relation to access to finance, we have
to work with the Strategic Banking
Corporation of Ireland and liaise with
finance providers on the funding
requirements of young farmers.
The Minister for agriculture is consulting
the Minister for Social Protection on the
recommendations around pensions.
Discussions with Teagasc are ongoing
regarding education and training and
advisory services recommendations.
The gender balance recommendation is being
progressed through the Department's women
in agriculture initiatives.
The EU Vision for Agriculture and Food
identified generational renewal as a
priority and this has been reflected in
the proposals for a post-2027 Common
Agricultural Policy.
I know that is the key focus of Deputy
Dolan in terms of wanting to make real
progress here.
The European Commission has also presented
its strategy for generational renewal in
agriculture.
The increased focus on generational
renewal at EU level is, of course, welcome
and the EU strategy comes to many of the
same conclusions as our own commission.
Regarding any formal farm succession
scheme, the Department and
Minister are engaging with the ten
recommendations in the report around CAP
supports.
These will need to be considered in the
context of the new round post 2027,
including the
CAP regulation and the new budget, and in
stakeholder consultations.
However, generational renewal should not
only be looked at through the lens of CAP
supports.
It is clear that an holistic approach is
required.
As noted by the Commission on Generational
Renewal in Farming, this is an issue for
all agrifood stakeholders to address
to support the environmental, social and
economic sustainability of farming and
enhance its image as a career.
What really shocked me when I met
on the ground.
It really is important that we encourage
young people to stick with the family
farm.
Part of that is that they need to see a
future in it so that they know they will
be able to take it over and invest in it
for the future.
What I am proposing here cannot simply be
viewed
It must be designed as a succession scheme
for the entire farm family.
I thank
for the work he did in setting up that
commission on generational renewal,
because that was important.
To have objective, evidence-based
recommendations now allows the Department
a chance to
a pathway forward.
I want to see that pathway coming.
important to recognise that an older
farmer cannot be made to feel that the
State is effectively telling them to stop
farming.
Farming is their livelihood, but
also their identity,
their home and often a place where they
have worked for generations.
At the same time, we cannot have a
situation where a son or daughter is
seeking to take over the family farm, but
they might be 35, 40 or 45 years old
before they get the opportunity to take
real control of the farm business.
This is why I believe the commission's
approach is worth pursuing.
Both sides of the transfer should be
provided.
Meaningful establishment capital
to the young farmer taking over and
financial security
to the farmer transferring the holding.
In principle, we already recognise this by
virtue of that tax credit of €25,000 over
the course of five years, but we need to
go further.
We should remember what happens when
succession occurs earlier.
A young farmer has a longer investment
horizon.
They can borrow and invest, improve the
family holding and adopt new technology
and everything that goes with it.
I understand that this might not be
possible in this year's budget, but it is
something the Government should pursue and
look at further.
Deputy Dolan again for taking up the
mantle in relation to this important
issue, and for trying to drive it on and
achieve real progress.
It is a crucial issue for maximising the
potential of Irish
agriculture and food production on this
island, and it will be driven by young
people coming into the sector.
That is why I set up the commission for
generational renewal
just about two years ago.
The
work done by the many good people who were
on that commission, under the
chairpersonship of Aidan O'Driscoll, was
foundational and important in
distilling what the
challenges
putting in place that evidential and
policy platform to consider how we can
go forward in attracting young people into
agriculture.
Many supports
already available, and we all acknowledge
they need to be built on.
The supports currently in place amounted
to €428
million in 2024, which is significant, but
we need to build on that further.
I will quote Aidan O'Driscoll, who was the
chair of the commission on generational
He said:
tables in farmhouses throughout this
country.
The rather sterile term “generational
renewal” translates on the ground into
intensely personal and family decisions,
which many farm families find difficult.
This crucial context is also reflected in
this report and addressed in
recommendations.
Those are important matters to consider as
well, but the key bottom line is that
agriculture has to be a sustainable
livelihood for people.
It is a really exciting time for Irish
agriculture and so many wonderful things
happening in it in terms of the
sustainability journey and that great
capacity through new learning and
technology and new ways of working with
the environment to be really productive
from a food-producing point of view, while
at the same time nurturing and protecting
the environment around us.
That can only be driven forward by young
people, and I thank
for the work he is doing in seeking to
drive it forward and
tools and supports within the next CAP,
which will see more and more young people
take up that career.
My question relates to periodic payment
orders, PPOs,
specifically a long-standing commitment by
the Minister for justice
a reality for families across the country.
At the moment, they are not.
Every year, the State Claims Agency has to
settle hundreds of medical negligence
cases.
A small number of those cases involve
families and individuals who have
catastrophic injuries, either at birth or
as a consequence of
a procedure that has gone very badly
wrong.
there are two options when a plaintiff is
seeking
compensation for those injuries.
It is either in the form of a lump sum or
of a periodic payment order.
I think most sensible people would
recognise that,
a lump sum to provide for somebody's care
until the end of their days, particularly
people who need 24-hour care, it is very
hard to estimate how long the person is
going to live and the nature of the care
in five, ten or 20 years.
Periodic payments orders,
are the answer, but we need to get the
formula right.
the issue
goes back to 2010, which is almost two
decades ago.
A High Court working group made a
recommendation in that year for the
establishment of periodic payment orders
instead of lump sums.
In 2017, that legislation was passed under
the civil liability Act.
It was groundbreaking because it linked
the payment, which was to
be updated every number of years,
to the
HICP.
In 2019,
there was a High Court case.
The court effectively said the periodic
payment orders were a dead letter because
of the construction of how they were
calculated.
Effectively, families and individuals were
running out of money because the actual
cost of providing for the individual far
exceeded the rate of inflation.
A review was promised.
There was an interdepartmental working
group.
It has reported and stipulated that
primary legislation is
needed to facilitate the Minister for
justice bringing forward a change in
secondary legislation.
That has happened.
The critical part of it,
is that the Minister for justice needs to
bring forward secondary legislation so
that periodic payment orders are based not
only on
HICP but also
the annual rate of change in health
workers' earnings.
That is the critical aspect.
I do not understand why the Government
will not act on this.
There are families out there like that of
Margaret Best.
Her son, Kenneth, was supposed to
only until
45.
He is now 57.
She ran out of money many years ago.
the family of Luke Miggins, who are
heading into their sixth interim
settlement.
It is completely unacceptable that they
had to go back to court every few years
and arrange for a large number of
assessments
to take place, at a cost to the State,
to get an updated payment for the care of
their son.
There has to be a better way.
We know what that better way is, and it is
in the gift of the Minister for justice.
When I asked the question last November,
we were told that the secondary
legislation was imminent, but we are nine
months on and
yet to see it.
When will we see the necessary, vital
legislative change to allow families to
get on with their lives and caring for
their loved ones, adult or child, with
catastrophic
very much for raising this very important
issue.
PPOs, as the Deputy set out very clearly,
are
an alternative to lump sum awards as a
method of paying compensation to
catastrophically injured people.
Instead of receiving compensation in one
tranche, as
laid out, a payment is made annually on an
agreed date.
The annual payment amount is calculated to
meet the cost of permanent and long-term
care and treatment.
An indexation rate is applied to the
annual payment amount to ensure the amount
keeps pace with inflation.
Part 3 of the Courts and Civil Law
(Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2023
contains amendments to the Civil Liability
Act 1961, which provide that indexation
of periodic payment orders will no longer
be
solely on the consumer price index.
Instead, the indexation rate for periodic
payment orders will be set by regulations
made by the Minister for justice with the
consent of the Minister for Finance.
The amendments arise from a High Court
decision on the existing indexation rate,
which found that it was not an appropriate
index for use with periodic payment
orders, PPOs.
The amendments proposed will allow greater
flexibility in the setting of the
indexation rate and set out the general
rule that a periodic payment order will be
adjusted on an annual basis by reference
to an index specified under the section.
In 2024, the then Minister for justice
published two reports relating to
compensation payments in personal injury
cases.
A working group on the indexation rate for
periodic payment orders was established to
advise on an appropriate index following a
High Court determination that the index
Its report recommended that the PPO
indexation rate should be based on a
combination of the
annual rate of change in nominal hourly
health earnings.
The amount of a yearly periodic payment
payable should be based on a periodic
payment order indexation rate comprising
80% of average annual rate
of change in nominal hourly health
earnings added to 20% of
the harmonised index of consumer prices.
Where a court makes a lump sum award in a
personal injury case, it uses the discount
rate to determine the size of the award
necessary to compensate a person for
future losses.
The rate reflects what an award recipient
would likely receive in return if the
award amount were invested.
Separately, an independent expert working
group was set up to advise on an
appropriate discount rate for use in
catastrophic injury cases.
Its report recommended that the discount
rate should remain unchanged from the rate
set by the High Court in 2014 and
subsequently confirmed by the Court of
Appeal and plaintiffs in catastrophic
injury cases should continue to be
considered as having a risk-averse
profile.
It also recommended that an expert group
should meet at a maximum of every three
years to reassess the discount rate and
that a trigger mechanism
should be introduced to enable a review of
the discount rate if there is a marked
change in economic circumstances or if the
rate is successfully challenged in
court.
I take a particular interest in
the very large
resources spent by our State is spent.
It is not just about what is spent but how
it is spent.
The State Claims Agency spent over €109
million
last year on legal fees for itself and
plaintiffs.
It spent about €115 million the year
before.
That is an enormous amount of money.
That the State Claims Agency has
to agree interim pay orders
with these families and spend the State's
money doing so is outrageous.
The recommendations of these reports have
been with the Department of justice for
two years.
The Minister said last November they were
imminent.
What is the delay?
Why are officials and the Minister not
thinking
about the impact on these families?
Surely it is not rocket science in terms
of what needs to be legislated for.
It is very clear - it is the HICP and
health workers' earnings.
We need to see action.
While the Minister for justice cannot be
here in person this evening, I will pass
on the key points the Deputy has made and
her strong advocacy on this important
issue.
As I mentioned,
a working group on the indexation rate for
periodic payment orders was established to
advise on an appropriate index following a
High Court determination that the index
used in primary legislation was
unworkable.
As part of a two-stage process, the
primary legislation governing PPOs has
been amended to allow for the Minister for
Justice, Home Affairs and Migration to set
the rate by way of secondary legislation,
as the Deputy outlined.
The Periodic Payment Orders Indexation
Rate - Report of the Inter Departmental
Working Group was submitted to the
Minister on 26 April 2024.
The Minister approved the recommendations
shortly afterwards on 21 May 2024.
Drafting instructions were issued to the
Office of
Parliamentary Counsel
on 13 August 2024.
Drafting of the regulations is continuing
and Department officials are working
closely with officials in the Office of
the Parliamentary Counsel
and the State Claims Agency to finalise
the regulations.
Once this work is completed, the
regulations require the consent of the
Minister for Finance before they
become operational.
That outlines the timeline
where
at.
I take the Deputy's point on the urgency
and importance of bringing that to
conclusion to bring a more streamlined and
optimal approach in how
this important mechanism works.
I will feed back Deputy Sherlock's clear
work and advocacy on this issue
to the Minister,
I raise the topic of online safety and the
regulation of social media platforms,
which is a very topical issue given the EU
KIDS Act, which we have been
slowly learning about over the course of
this week, as well as the focus on it
during Ursula von der Leyen's state of the
Union
just yesterday and the online safety
conference run by the Minister of State's
Department last week.
I will start by talking about what we are
trying to make safe and what the harms
are.
Across my constituency, including Dundrum,
Stillorgan, Foxrock and Goatstown,
and across the entire country, we are
contacted as representatives by parents
who are at their wits' end trying to
figure out how to manage this.
They are so concerned at the dangers they
see.
When we design solutions to regulate these
tech platforms to mitigate online harms,
we have to think of what those harms are
to find the right solutions.
The first category is mental health
concerns.
Primary among them is the addictive nature
of these products, what it means for all
of us and what it is doing to our brains.
There are also issues around self-harm
being promoted,
eating disorders and with the newest tools
on the block, chatbots,
we see people brought to suicide,
essentially being nurtured
bit by bit toward suicidal ideation and in
some cases actually carrying out the act
of suicide because an automated machine
advised them this was a good idea.
The second category one might talk about
is disinformation.
There is polarisation, riots in the
streets fomented online,
radicalisation in particular of young men
and the massive threat to democracy posed
by the disinformation that flows online
particularly at election times.
The other category we need to capture is
scams.
Scams are insidious.
They are increasing and AI is
turbocharging them.
They come in the form of romance scams or
networking scams where relationships
are built and people are drifted towards
crypto scams, where they are carved out of
their entire wealth and that of those
around them in a
clinical and
corporate way.
The solutions we come up with need to
address these harms.
We need to make these products safe.
If they are not safe, they should not be
on the market in the first place.
I referenced addiction.
It is a key part of the business model.
The algorithms driving social media and
informing
what we see on our screens are designed
right now - they were not always - - to
keep our eyes on the screen and they are
boosted by the AI technology that
underpins them.
Age assurance and bans are one thing but
they
are
major issues with them,
in a few different strands.
They are privacy, where we are required to
hand over official documentation,
rights, where they essentially block from
online participation
people who are expected to be cut off, and
online is not all bad.
They do not work as we have seen in
Australia and France, for example, and
they leave behind this cesspit of the
internet that those of us who
subject to the ban have to deal with.
Therefore, while I welcome the
announcements this week and while I hope
fervently that the European Union has
learned from
the ban in Australia has been, its
inefficacy, and from the French experience
where the courts have
challenged the mechanism of the ban,
I have major concerns about how it will
wash out, what the details will be
and how it will be implemented.
As far as I can see so far, those
categories of harm will not be addressed
Deputy Gibney for raising this and for her
clear
articulation of the dangers and challenges
we all have to deal with in how we respond
and protect young people.
Online safety, and particularly the
protection of young people online, is
crucial to all of us and is also a
whole-of-government priority.
It is timely that we are discussing this
topic, given the developments at EU level
which have been moving in recent times,
particularly
this week with President von der Leyen's
address and outline
of the European Commission's approach and
the publication of the proposal for a new
EU regulation, entitled the EU KIDS Act.
The proposal addresses child safety online
in two main ways.
First, it will introduce a graduated
approach to access to social media for
children.
Children under 13 will not have access to
social media, with some
very limited exceptions for child-friendly
services.
Children aged between 13 and 15 may have
mini accounts, set up by parents or
guardians with only age appropriate
content and children over 15 may have
autonomous accounts.
Second, it will introduce new obligations
on social media that prohibit design
features such as infinite scroll and push
notification during sleeping hours.
The proposal will also introduce new
obligations on more than just social
media.
It will also apply to online video games,
Al companions and chatbots.
Now that the Commission’s proposal has
been published, the discussions will move
to the Council and the European
Parliament.
As online safety of children and young
people is a priority for Ireland's EU
Presidency, we will give priority to those
negotiations.
Ensuring online safety regulation is up to
date and fit for purpose means that this
will continue to be an evolving area.
Moreover, given the breadth of online
safety, it requires a variety of
approaches.
The European Commission is preparing
proposals to amend the audiovisual and
media services directive, which are
expected to include new measures on
content, including harmful content.
President von der Leyen also announced
yesterday that a proposal for a new
digital fairness Act will issue this
autumn.
This is due to include important new
online consumer protections.
As with the EU KIDS Act, the Irish
Presidency will give priority to the
negotiations on these safety proposals as
they emerge.
also seen developments in the USA, where
platforms have settled cases.
We are clear that any improvements to
child safety that can be made in other
jurisdictions must be implemented in the
EU,
too.
Once today’s proposals take effect,
together with existing regulation, we will
have secured that and
gone further.
thank Deputy Gibney for raising it.
This is something we will continue
through the remainder of our Presidency.
As we said from the outset, the
Government's objective is to do this
collectively, working at EU level because
we believe that is the way to have the
most impact on the protection of children
and
the implementability of regulations
thank the Minister of State for the
response.
The first issue I have with it is the
focus on age.
I raised today the topic of online safety,
not online safety for children.
I appreciate that, as legislators, we have
a particular role to play in protecting
people who cannot protect themselves as
well as everyone else but if we only talk
about blocking children and making things
safe for children, we are not addressing
online safety, because everyone else still
has to deal with it.
Let us talk about age assurance and bans.
One of the groups in society that has
digital literacy challenges that are
unique from those of everyone else is
older people.
At some stage will we see bans for older
people?
What do we think about that in terms of
the right to online participation and so
on?
The focus on age is wrong because it does
not deal with the tools and the addictive
nature of the tools.
In all the things
listed - and I appreciate the detail and I
look forward to the detail coming out -
algorithms are not mentioned.
Yet, we are blue in the face on this side
of the House telling the Government to fix
the algorithms because they are the thing
that will get
to the business model.
of the main issues with the proposals put
forward by the EU is privacy.
We
all have to hand over
official documentation to enforce these
bans and I am not assured by
the methods people are talking about
because people will essentially
handing over official documentation to
states, private companies or third
parties, all of which involve a raft of
privacy issues.
I could go on but the main issue I have is
that there is corporate capture in
Brussels and Dublin, which means all these
beautiful shiny rules that are set out -
these directives, proposals and ideas -
have for years all promised to do the same
thing, fix these issues and address online
safety.
Yet, they are carved out by the time they
ever reach the end of the process and then
they are simply not enforced.
to take on big tech
in Dublin and in Europe and we need to
actually fix these issues, because nothing
I heard gives me the comfort and feeling
of safety we need to provide to the people
who are calling me every day at their
wits' end because of what their children
are experiencing online, and what we are
all experiencing online.
Deputy.
I outlined clearly in my initial response
the progress we have seen.
While we all agree appropriate
safeguards and rails are needed given the
impact social media can have on,
society generally, a key priority for all
of us has to be the protection of young
people and vulnerable people, particularly
children in relation to what
they are experiencing as the first
generation
Collectively, at European level, driven by
the Irish Presidency of the EU,
we have seen progress on that, in the
announcements this week which I
outlined earlier.
no doubt, and
social media and the type of activity we
have seen on it is affecting society in
terms of behaviours and radicalisation of
people.
We all have to be open in considering how
to address that and how to ensure
the space is regulated in a way that
serves society well.
The Government is open to engaging and
discussing that and trying to find an
appropriate way forward.
Key to that is having debates and
discussions, such as the one Deputy Gibney
is having today with the points she raised
on the floor of the Dáil.
We will continue to engage with her and
across the Oireachtas on how we can
address this important issue.
Back to school costs are having an
enormous impact on families.
The most recent cost of education survey
showed that parents are now paying almost
€1,800 per year for a child in primary
school and almost €3,000 per year for a
child in secondary school.
Even more worrying is that the number of
parents taking loans to cover these costs
has doubled in just one year.
Parents are being crippled by the cost of
school uniforms, materials and the
so-called voluntary contributions, which
many parents feel forced to pay and which
are used to subsidise the education system
because our schools are chronically
underfunded.
In recent years, more and more parents
have an additional cost on top of this, as
many schools now require them to purchase
ICT equipment, such as laptops, for their
children.
During the summer months, many parents
contacted me outlining the significant
cost they are facing because the school
requires them to purchase a laptop for
their child or children for the upcoming
school year.
Parents
in touch with me who had to pay up to
€1,000 between the cost of the device and
the insurance to go with it.
That has a massive impact on families who
have to deal with rising costs right
across the board and who are really
struggling with the cost of living at the
moment.
One father with a child doing the leaving
certificate told me
he had to pay €1,000 for his child's
device.
That comes on top of the €6,000 in college
fees he will have to pay for his other two
children, who are attending university.
One mother told me she had to pay €700 for
her child's device.
The child is going into
She has another daughter
will have to purchase one in two years.
She said that they were made to feel that
she would be left out of class work if she
did not have the laptop.
Another mother told me she had two
children in school
had to purchase a laptop.
She said
has
become very expensive.
Parents are not being given an option to
shop around for more affordable models.
they are put under significant pressure to
purchase these devices.
The Government's failure to regulate this
is a dereliction of its duty.
The Government is insisting that devices
are not needed and not mandatory but
guidance without enforcement does not
offer any comfort at all.
The resulting growing digital divide risks
creating a two-tier education system where
a family's income determines whether a
child can participate fully in learning.
That is completely unacceptable.
If the Government is serious about
reducing back-to-school costs and about
equality of access, it must properly fund
schools' digital infrastructure and stop
expecting families to bridge that gap.
Expecting parents to pay up to €1,000 on
top of all of the other back-to-school
costs simply will not cut it.
I ask the Minister of State to outline how
the Government is going to address this
problem and ensure that families do not
continue to struggle every year as the
return to school comes around,
particularly in
of these digital devices.
Deputy O'Hara for raising this matter.
I am answering on behalf of the Minister
for Education and Youth, Deputy Hildegarde
Naughton.
At the outset, I will state that there is
no requirement for any student to have a
personal device in school.
On 25 May this year, the Minister for
Education and Youth communicated directly
with all schools and boards of management
to set out the Department's position that
there is no requirement for a personal
device for junior cycle or
leaving certificate.
The Minister requested schools to be
cognisant of the view of all parents in
relation to the use of digital devices and
the associated costs and set out the need
for schools to engage with all parents,
and not just the parents' association,
before deciding on an approach regarding
devices.
As the Deputy will no doubt
responsibility for the day-to-day
management of
schools.
Decisions regarding the use and deployment
of digital technology in schools is
therefore a matter for the board of
management of each school in the context
of its digital learning planning.
Schools, in consultation with all parents,
are responsible for decisions on the use
of digital technology, including tablet
devices, laptops and learning platforms,
and how best to manage their integration
into classroom practice, reflective of
their own context and requirements.
As mentioned, schools have been advised to
consult with members of the school
community, including parents, when
planning for the introduction of digital
technologies, including devices, with cost
and other implications being fully
considered by the boards of management
before a decision is made.
Government is keenly aware of the
challenges faced by educators and parents
in relation to the cost of digital
technology, including tablets.
The Department continues to work to help
support schools and families meet these
costs as part of an overall ongoing
commitment to reduce financial pressure on
families and
ensure students are supported to succeed.
To support ICT in schools, €200 million
was allocated under the digital strategy
for schools, with the most recent tranche
of €35 million issuing in January of this
year.
Schools have flexibility to use their ICT
grants to meet local priorities, including
infrastructure, maintenance and device
provision, within available resources.
The digital strategy for schools
in teaching and learning.
It is concerned with the deeper embedding
of digital technologies in education to
develop digital literacy and competency
and critical thinking and to enhance
collaborative learning.
It is not merely about replacing physical
textbooks and resources with digital
versions accessed via a digital
device.
The Department commissioned OECD research
on the impact of digital technologies on
student learning and this was published in
September last year.
This research highlights that access to
digital devices alone does not guarantee
improved learning outcomes and that their
successful use depends on thoughtful
pedagogical alignment and teacher and
student digital
The Minister will continue to engage with
education stakeholders on this matter but
it is worth nothing that the
decision on the deployment of technology
in schools remains with the school and its
board of management.
Each school is best placed to determine
how best technology can support teaching
and learning in its own context.
We all recognise that digital education
has an important role to play but it has
to be fair and equitable.
The Minister of State mentioned that the
Minister has communicated with schools.
She wrote a letter to schools about the
use of digital devices.
That is not good enough because it has not
made any meaningful difference.
As I said earlier, guidance without
enforcement simply has not worked.
There needs to be a review of the roll-out
of these devices.
We need to ensure there is a consistent
approach and supports for schools.
I do not understand why that has not
happened.
Telling schools to avail of the ICT fund
is a cop-out because the Government has
cut €15 million from ICT grants for
schools, with the total down to €35
million.
You cannot cut the fund and then tell
schools to rely on it to provide these
devices.
It is completely unfair that the cost is
being heaped onto parents.
There need to be supports for families who
are struggling to pay and an overall
review of the roll-out of the devices.
The Government should restore the funding
for ICT and provide proper support for
schools for digital devices so that no
child will be disadvantaged because they
cannot afford expensive technology.
Otherwise, we are going to continue seeing
parents being put under pressure and a
growing digital divide both between
schools and within schools and
classrooms, where some children will have
a device and some children will not, with
those children being made to feel left
out.
These are enormous costs.
A sum of €1,000 for a device is not
affordable to families.
The Government should know that.
It should be acting on this.
You cannot continue to put this burden on
families because families are at breaking
point when it comes to rising costs right
across the board, particularly when
children are going back to school.
I ask that the Minister for education and
the Government as a whole finally get a
handle on
and start to treat
seriously.
Deputy O'Hara.
There is real recognition from the
Government of the pressures on families
at back-to-school time.
That is why we put a number of supports in
place
such as the back-to-school allowance.
It is also why the Government engages with
boards of management in
schools to make sure that those costs are
fully considered at school level and are
managed.
In the Minister's communication to schools
and boards of management this year, she
emphasised the importance of minimising
that cost burden on students and their
families where digital devices are used as
part of school life.
She requested that school authorities have
regard to a number of key principles.
The guidance
reflects the established departmental
approach to the general management of
school-related costs, which was set out in
Circular
32/2017 and Circular 65/2010.
This guidance is intended to support
boards of management in making decisions
that promote affordability, equity and
value for money.
A number of measures are in place to
support educators and parents as part of
the Department of education's ongoing
commitment to reducing financial pressure
on families and ensuring that every
student is supported.
These measures include an instruction from
the Department to schools to consult with
parents and the school community on
ensuring that costs are reasonable for
parents and how to avoid costs acting as a
barrier.
For example, where possible, generic
rather than branded items should be
specified.
an important issue.
It is one
Government and schools always need to be
cognisant of.
It is important
we all collectively work together to make
sure that the real cost burden families
face in relation to school costs is
managed as best
possible while ensuring that students have
what they need to have the best possible
and optimal education.
I thank the Deputy for raising this matter
today.
I
certainly pass his feedback and the key
points he has raised